<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: error-list.xsl,v 1.2 2009/09/10 17:17:57 NormanWalsh Exp $ -->
<error-list xmlns="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-error">
   <error code="XC0023">It is a dynamic error if a select expression or match pattern returns a node type that is not allowed by the step.</error>
   <error code="XD0004">It is a dynamic error if no subpipeline is selected by the p:choose and no default is provided.</error>
   <error code="XD0005">It is a dynamic error if more than one document appears on the connection for this input port.</error>
   <error code="XD0006">If sequence is not specified, or has the value false, then it is a dynamic error unless exactly one document appears on the declared port.</error>
   <error code="XD0007">If sequence is not specified on p:output, or has the value false, then it is a dynamic error if the step does not produce exactly one document on the declared port.</error>
   <error code="XD0008">It is a dynamic error if a document sequence appears where a document to be used as the context node is expected.</error>
   <error code="XD0009">It is a dynamic error if the element attribute on p:namespaces is specified and it does not identify a single element node.</error>
   <error code="XD0010">It is a dynamic error if the match expression on p:viewport does not match an element or document.</error>
   <error code="XD0011">It is a dynamic error if the resource referenced by a p:document element does not exist, cannot be accessed, or has an XML content type and is not a well-formed XML document.</error>
   <error code="XD0012">It is a dynamic error if any attempt is made to dereference a URI where the scheme of the URI reference is not supported.</error>
   <error code="XD0013">It is a dynamic error if the specified namespace bindings are inconsistent; that is, if the same prefix is bound to two different namespace names.</error>
   <error code="XD0014">It is a dynamic error for any unqualified attribute names other than “name”, “namespace”, or “value” to appear on a c:param element.</error>
   <error code="XD0015">It is a dynamic error if the specified QName cannot be resolved with the in-scope namespace declarations.</error>
   <error code="XD0016">It is a dynamic error if the select expression on a p:input returns atomic values or anything other than element or document nodes (or an empty sequence).</error>
   <error code="XD0017">It is a dynamic error if the running pipeline attempts to invoke a step which the processor does not know how to perform.</error>
   <error code="XD0018">It is a dynamic error if the c:parameter-set parameter list contains any elements other than c:param.</error>
   <error code="XD0019">It is a dynamic error if any option value does not satisfy the type required for that option.</error>
   <error code="XD0020">It is a dynamic error if the combination of serialization options specified or defaulted is not allowed.</error>
   <error code="XD0021">It is a dynamic error for a pipeline to attempt to access a resource for which it has insufficient privileges or perform a step which is forbidden.</error>
   <error code="XD0022">It is a dynamic error if a processor that does not support PSVI annotations attempts to invoke a step which asserts that they are required.</error>
   <error code="XD0025">It is a dynamic error if the namespace attribute is specified on c:param, the name contains a colon, and the specified namespace is not the same as the in-scope namespace binding for the specified prefix.</error>
   <error code="XD0026">It is a dynamic error if the select expression makes reference to the context node, size, or position when the context item is undefined.</error>
   <error code="XD0028">It is a dynamic error if any attribute value does not satisfy the type required for that attribute.</error>
   <error code="XD0030">It is a dynamic error if a step is unable or incapable of performing its function.</error>
   <error code="XD0033">It is a dynamic error if the name specified is not the name of an in-scope option or variable.</error>
   <error code="XD0034">On steps which allow independent specification of a namespace and a name, it is a dynamic error to specify a new namespace or prefix if the lexical value of the specified name contains a colon.</error>
   <error code="XD1000">It is a dynamic error if the element (or document element) passed to p:make-map is not a c:param-set element.</error>
   <error code="XD1001">It is a dynamic error if the computed value does not match the specified sequence type.</error>
   <error code="XD1002">It is a dynamic error if any of the c:param elements are invalid.</error>
   <error code="XD1003">If an input port provides a set of acceptable content types, it is a dynamic error if an input document that arrives on the port has a content type that does not match any content type in that set.</error>
   <error code="XD1004">It is a dynamic error if the select is used and any input document is not an XML document.</error>
   <error code="XD1005">It is a dynamic error if the body is not correctly encoded per the value of the encoding attribute.</error>
   <error code="XS0001">It is a static error if there are any loops in the connections between steps: no step can be connected to itself nor can there be any sequence of connections through other steps that leads back to itself.</error>
   <error code="XS0002">All steps in the same scope must have unique names: it is a static error if two steps with the same name appear in the same scope.</error>
   <error code="XS0003">It is a static error if any declared input is not connected.</error>
   <error code="XS0004">It is a static error to declare two or more options on the same step with the same name.</error>
   <error code="XS0005">It is a static error if the primary output port of any step is not connected.</error>
   <error code="XS0006">It is a static error if the primary output port has no explicit connection and the last step in the subpipeline does not have a primary output port.</error>
   <error code="XS0007">It is a static error if two subpipelines in a p:choose declare different outputs.</error>
   <error code="XS0008">It is a static error if any element in the XProc namespace has attributes not defined by this specification unless they are extension attributes.</error>
   <error code="XS0009">It is a static error if the p:group and p:catch subpipelines declare different outputs.</error>
   <error code="XS0010">It is a static error if a pipeline contains a step whose specified inputs, outputs, and options do not match the signature for steps of that type.</error>
   <error code="XS0011">It is a static error to identify two ports with the same name on the same step.</error>
   <error code="XS0014">It is a static error to identify more than one output port as primary.</error>
   <error code="XS0015">It is a static error if a compound step has no contained steps.</error>
   <error code="XS0017">It is a static error to specify that an option is both requiredand has a default value.</error>
   <error code="XS0018">If an option is required, it is a static error to invoke the step without specifying a value for that option.</error>
   <error code="XS0020">It is a static error if the binding attribute on p:namespaces is specified and its value is not the name of an in-scope binding.</error>
   <error code="XS0022">In all cases except the p:output of a compound step, it is a static error if the port identified by a p:pipe is not in the readable ports of the step that contains the p:pipe.</error>
   <error code="XS0024">It is a static error if the content of the p:inline element does not consist of exactly one element, optionally preceded and/or followed by any number of processing instructions, comments or whitespace characters.</error>
   <error code="XS0025">It is a static error if the expanded-QName value of the type attribute is in no namespace or in the XProc namespace.</error>
   <error code="XS0026">It is a static error if the port specified on the p:log is not the name of an output port on the step in which it appears or if more than one p:log element is applied to the same port.</error>
   <error code="XS0027">It is a static error if an option is specified with both the shortcut form and the long form.</error>
   <error code="XS0028">It is a static error to declare an option or variable in the XProc namespace.</error>
   <error code="XS0029">It is a static error to specify a connection for a p:output inside a p:declare-step for an atomic step.</error>
   <error code="XS0030">It is a static error to specify that more than one input port is the primary.</error>
   <error code="XS0031">It is a static error to use an option on an atomic step that is not declared on steps of that type.</error>
   <error code="XS0032">It is a static error if no connection is provided and the default readable port is undefined.</error>
   <error code="XS0036">All the step types in a pipeline or library must have unique names: it is a static error if any step type name is built-in and/or declared or defined more than once in the same scope.</error>
   <error code="XS0037">It is a static error if any step directly contains text nodes that do not consist entirely of whitespace.</error>
   <error code="XS0038">It is a static error if any required attribute is not provided.</error>
   <error code="XS0039">It is a static error if the port specified on the p:serialization is not the name of an output port on the pipeline in which it appears or if more than one p:serialization element is applied to the same port.</error>
   <error code="XS0041">It is a static error to specify both binding and element on the same p:namespaces element.</error>
   <error code="XS0042">It is a static error to attempt to provide a connection for an input port on the declaration of an atomic step.</error>
   <error code="XS0044">It is a static error if any element in the XProc namespace or any step has element children other than those specified for it by this specification. In particular, the presence of atomic steps for which there is no visible declaration may raise this error.</error>
   <error code="XS0048">It is a static error to use a declared step as a compound step.</error>
   <error code="XS0051">It is a static error if the except-prefixes attribute on p:namespaces does not contain a list of tokens or if any of those tokens is not a prefix bound to a namespace in the in-scope namespaces of the p:namespaces element.</error>
   <error code="XS0052">It is a static error if the URI of a p:import cannot be retrieved or if, once retrieved, it does not point to a p:library, p:declare-step, or p:pipeline.</error>
   <error code="XS0053">It is a static error to import a single pipeline if that pipeline does not have a type.</error>
   <error code="XS0057">It is a static error if the exclude-inline-prefixes attribute does not contain a list of tokens or if any of those tokens (except #all or #default) is not a prefix bound to a namespace in the in-scope namespaces of the element on which it occurs.</error>
   <error code="XS0058">It is a static error if the value #default is used within the exclude-inline-prefixes attribute and there is no default namespace in scope.</error>
   <error code="XS0059">It is a static error if the pipeline element is not p:pipeline, p:declare-step, or p:library.</error>
   <error code="XS0060">It is a static error if the processor encounters an explicit request for a previous version of the language and it is unable to process the pipeline using those semantics.</error>
   <error code="XS0061">It is a static error if a use-when expression refers to the context or attempts to refer to any documents or collections.</error>
   <error code="XS0062">It is a static error if a required version attribute is not present.</error>
   <error code="XS0063">It is a static error if the value of the version attribute is not a xs:decimal.</error>
   <error code="XS1001">It is a static error if the code attribute is missing from any but the last p:catch, if the last p:catch has a code, or if any error code is repeated.</error>
   <error code="XS1002">It is a static error if there is no primary input port.</error>
   <error code="XS1003">It is a static error if an expression does not have a closing right curly bracket or if an unescaped right curly bracket occurs outside of an expression.</error>
   <error code="XS1004">It is a static error if the step attribute is not specified, and there is no default readable port. It is a static error if the port attribute is not specified, and the step identified has no primary output port.</error>
   <error code="XS1005">It is a static error if the port attribute is not specified, and the step identified has no primary output port.</error>
   <error code="XS1006">It is a static error if the encoding specified is not supported by the implementation.</error>
   <error code="XS1007">It is a static error if an encoding is specified and the content type is an XML media type.</error>
   <error code="XS1008">It is a static error if the content type value specifies a character set and the encoding attribute is absent.</error>
   <error code="XS1009">It is a static error if an encoding is specified and the content of the p:inline contains any XML markup.</error>
   <error code="XS1100">It is a static error if there are any loops in the connections between steps and variables: no step can refer to a variable if there is any sequence of connections from that step that leads back to the input that provides the context node for the expression that defines the value of the variable.</error>
</error-list>
