<?xml-model href="../../schema/dbspec.rng"
  type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<specification xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
               xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
               xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
               xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
               xml:id='xproc'
               class="ed"
               version="5.0-extension w3c-xproc">
<info>
<title>XProc 3.0: An XML Pipeline Language</title>
<!-- defaults to date formatted <pubdate>2014-12-18</pubdate> -->
<copyright><year>2018</year><holder>@@FIXME:</holder></copyright>

<bibliorelation type="isformatof" xlink:href="specification.xml">XML</bibliorelation>
<authorgroup>
  <author>
    <personname>Achim Berndzen</personname>
  </author>
  <author>
    <personname>Gerrit Imsieke</personname>
  </author>
  <author>
    <personname>Erik Siegel</personname>
  </author>
  <author>
    <personname>Norman Walsh</personname>
  </author>
</authorgroup>
<abstract>
<para>This specification describes the syntax and semantics of
<citetitle>XProc 3.0: An XML Pipeline Language</citetitle>, a language for
describing operations to be performed on documents.</para>

<para>An XML Pipeline specifies a sequence of operations to be
performed on documents. Pipelines generally accept
documents as input and produce documents as output.
Pipelines are made up of simple steps which
perform atomic operations on documents and constructs similar to
conditionals, iteration, and exception handlers which control which
steps are executed.</para>
</abstract>

<legalnotice role="status">

<para><emphasis>This section describes the status of this document at
the time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this
document.</emphasis></para>

<para>This document is derived from
<link xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2010/REC-xproc-20100511/">XProc:
An XML Pipeline Language</link> published by the W3C.</para>
</legalnotice>
</info>

<section xml:id="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>An XML Pipeline specifies a sequence of operations to be
performed on a collection of input documents. Pipelines take documents
as their input and produce documents as their output.</para>

<para>A <glossterm>pipeline</glossterm> consists of steps. Like
pipelines, steps take documents as their inputs and
produce documents as their outputs. The inputs of a step
come from the web, from the pipeline document, from the inputs to the
pipeline itself, or from the outputs of other steps in the pipeline.
The outputs from a step are consumed by other steps, are outputs of
the pipeline as a whole, or are discarded.</para>

<para>There are three kinds of steps: atomic steps, compound steps,
and multi-container steps. Atomic steps carry out single operations
and have no substructure as far as the pipeline is concerned. Compound
steps and multi-container steps control the execution of other steps,
which they include in the form of one or more subpipelines.</para>

<para><biblioref linkend="std-components"/>
defines a standard library of steps. Pipeline implementations
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> support additional types of steps as well.
</para>

<para><xref linkend="fig-xival"/> is a graphical representation of a
simple pipeline that performs XInclude processing and validation on a
document.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-xival">
      <title>A simple, linear XInclude/Validate pipeline</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <alt>A simple, linear XInclude/Validate pipeline</alt>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="graphics/sch-xinclude-validate-pipeline.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>This is a pipeline that consists of two atomic steps, XInclude and Validate with XML
      Schema. The pipeline itself has two inputs, “source” (a source document) and “schemas” (a
      sequence of W3C XML Schemas). The XInclude step reads the pipeline input “source” and produces
      a result document. The Validate with XML Schema step reads the pipeline input “schemas” and
      the result of the XInclude step and produces its own result document. The result of the
      validation, “result”, is the result of the pipeline. (For consistency across the step
      vocabulary, the standard input is usually named “source” and the standard output is
      usually named “result”.) </para>
    <para>The pipeline document determines how the steps are connected together inside the pipeline,
      that is, how the output of one step becomes the input of another.</para>
    <para>The pipeline document for this pipeline is shown in <xref linkend="ex1"/>.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex1">
      <title>A simple, linear XInclude/Validate pipeline</title>
      <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/fig1.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>

<para>The example in <xref linkend="ex1"/> is very verbose. It makes
all of the connections seen in the figure explicit. In practice,
pipelines do not have to be this verbose. By default, Where inputs and
outputs are connected between sequential sibling steps, they do not
have to be made explicit.</para>

<para>The same pipeline, using XProc defaults, is shown in <xref
linkend="ex1-abbr"/>.</para>

<example xml:id="ex1-abbr">
  <title>A simple, linear XInclude/Validate pipeline (simplified)</title>
  <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/fig1-abbr.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
</example>

<para><xref linkend="fig-style-proc"/> is a more complex example: it
performs schema validation with an appropriate schema and then styles
the validated document.</para>

<figure xml:id="fig-style-proc">
  <title>A validate and transform pipeline</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <alt>A validate and transform pipeline</alt>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="graphics/sch-transform.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>The heart of this example is the conditional. The “choose” step
evaluates an XPath expression over a test document. Based on the
result of that expression, one or another branch is run. In this
example, each branch consists of a single validate step.</para>

<example xml:id="ex2">
  <title>A validate and transform pipeline</title>
  <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/fig2.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
</example>

<para>This example, like the preceding, relies on XProc defaults for
simplicity. It is always valid to write the fully explicit form if you
prefer. This example also takes advantage of using the <tag class="attribute">href</tag>
attribute directly on <tag>p:with-input</tag> as a shortcut for the
<tag>p:document</tag> connection.</para>

    <para>The media type for pipeline documents is <literal>application/xml</literal>. Often,
      pipeline documents are identified by the extension <filename class="extension"
      >.xpl</filename>.</para>
    <para>In this specification the words <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>, <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119>,
        <rfc2119>should</rfc2119>, <rfc2119>should not</rfc2119>, <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> and
        <rfc2119>recommended</rfc2119> are to be interpreted as described in <biblioref
        linkend="rfc2119"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="pipeline-concepts">
    <title>Pipeline Concepts</title>
    <para><termdef xml:id="dt-pipeline">A <firstterm>pipeline</firstterm> is a set of connected
        steps, with outputs of one step flowing into inputs of another.</termdef> A pipeline is
      itself a <glossterm>step</glossterm> and must satisfy the constraints on steps. Connections
      between steps occur where the input of one step is connected to the output of another. </para>
    <para>The result of evaluating a pipeline (or <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>) is the result
      of evaluating the steps that it contains, in an order consistent with the connections between
      them. A pipeline must behave as if it evaluated each step each time it is encountered. Unless
      otherwise indicated, implementations <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> assume that steps are

functional (that is, that their outputs depend only on their
<link linkend="input-output" >inputs</link> and
<glossterm baseform="option">options</glossterm>) or side-effect
free.</para>

    <para>The pattern of connections between steps will not always completely determine their order
      of evaluation. <impl>The evaluation order of steps not connected to one another is
          <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm></impl>.</para>
    <section xml:id="step-concept">
      <title>Steps</title>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-step">A <firstterm>step</firstterm> is the basic computational unit
          of a pipeline.</termdef> A typical step has zero or more inputs, from which it receives
        documents to process, zero or more outputs, to which it sends document results, and
        can have options.</para>
      <para>There are three kinds of steps: <glossterm baseform="atomic step">atomic</glossterm>,
          <glossterm baseform="compound step">compound</glossterm>, and <glossterm
          baseform="multi-container step">multi-container</glossterm>.</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-atomic-step">An <firstterm>atomic
step</firstterm> is a step that performs a unit of processing
on its input,
such as XInclude or transformation, and has no internal
<glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. </termdef> Atomic steps carry out
fundamental operations and can perform arbitrary amounts of
computation, but they are indivisible. An XSLT step, for example,
performs XSLT processing; a Validate with XML Schema step validates
one input with respect to some set of XML Schemas, etc.</para>

      <para>There are many <emphasis>types</emphasis> of atomic steps. The standard library of
        atomic steps is described in <biblioref linkend="std-components"/>, but implementations
          <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> provide others as well. <impl>It is
            <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> what additional step types, if any, are
          provided. </impl> Each use, or instance, of an atomic step invokes the processing defined
        by that type of step. A pipeline may contain instances of many types of steps and many
        instances of the same type of step.</para>
      <para>Compound steps, on the other hand, control and organize the flow of documents through a
        pipeline, reconstructing familiar programming language functionality such as conditionals,
        iterators and exception handling. They contain other steps, whose evaluation they
        control.</para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-compound-step">A <firstterm>compound step</firstterm> is a step that
          contains a <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>.</termdef> That is, a compound step differs
        from an atomic step in that its semantics are at least partially determined by the steps
        that it contains.</para>
      <para>Finally, there are two “multi-container steps”: <tag>p:choose</tag> and
        <tag>p:try</tag>. <termdef xml:id="dt-multi-container-step">A <firstterm>multi-container
            step</firstterm> is a step that contains several alternate <glossterm
            baseform="subpipeline">subpipelines</glossterm>. </termdef> Each subpipeline is
        identified by a non-step wrapper element: <tag>p:when</tag> and <tag>p:otherwise</tag> in
        the case of <tag>p:choose</tag>, <tag>p:group</tag> and <tag>p:catch</tag> in the case of
          <tag>p:try</tag>. </para>
      <para>The output of a multi-container step is the output of exactly one of its subpipelines.
        In this sense, a multi-container step functions like a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>.
        However, evaluating a multi-container step may involve evaluating, or partially evaluating,
        more than one of its subpipelines. It's possible for steps in a partially evaluated pipeline
        to have side effects that are visible outside the processor, even if the final output of the
        multi-container step is the result of some other subpipeline. For example, a web server
        might record that some interaction was performed, or a file on the local file system might
        have been modified.</para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-container">A compound step or multi-container step is a
            <firstterm>container</firstterm> for the steps directly within it or within non-step
          wrappers directly within it.</termdef>
        <termdef xml:id="dt-contained-steps">The steps that occur directly within, or within
          non-step wrappers directly within, a step are called that step's <firstterm>contained
            steps</firstterm>. In other words, “container” and “contained steps” are inverse
          relationships.</termdef>
        <termdef xml:id="dt-ancestors">The <firstterm>ancestors</firstterm> of a step, if it has
          any, are its <glossterm>container</glossterm> and the ancestors of its
          container.</termdef>
      </para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-subpipeline">Sibling steps (and the connections between them) form a
            <firstterm>subpipeline</firstterm>.</termdef>
        <termdef xml:id="dt-last-step">The <firstterm>last step</firstterm> in a subpipeline is its
          last step in document order.</termdef></para>

      <para xml:id="p.subpipeline"
        role="element-syntax element-syntax-language-construct hanging-indent">
        <code>subpipeline</code>&#xa0;=&#xa0;(<tag>p:variable</tag>|<tag>p:for-each</tag>|<tag>p:viewport</tag>|<tag>p:choose</tag>|<tag>p:if</tag>|<tag>p:group</tag>|<tag>p:try</tag>|<code
          xlink:href="#p.atomic">p:<replaceable>standard-step</replaceable></code>|<code
          xlink:href="#p.atomic"><replaceable>pfx:user-pipeline</replaceable></code>)+ </para>

      <note xml:id="note-udp">
        <para>User-defined pipelines (identified with
              <code><replaceable>pfx:user-pipeline</replaceable></code> in the preceding syntax
          summary) are atomic. A pipeline <emphasis>declaration</emphasis> may contain a
          subpipeline, but the invocation of that pipeline is atomic and does not contain a
          subpipeline.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Steps have “ports” into which inputs and outputs are connected. Each step has a number
        of input ports and a number of output ports; a step can have zero input ports and/or zero
        output ports. (All steps have an implicit output port for reporting errors that
          <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be declared.) The names of all ports on each step must be
        unique on that step (you can't have two input ports named “source”, nor can you have an
        input port named “schema” and an output port named “schema”). </para>
      <para>A Step may have zero or more <link linkend="options">options</link>, all with unique
        names.</para>
      <para>All of the different instances of steps (atomic or compound) in a pipeline can be
        distinguished from one another by name. If the pipeline author does not provide a name for a
        step, a default name is <link linkend="step-names">manufactured automatically</link>.</para>
      <section xml:id="step-names">
        <title>Step names</title>
        <para>The <tag class="attribute">name</tag> attribute on any step can be used to give it a
          name. The name must be unique within its scope, see <xref linkend="scoping"/>.</para>
        <para>If the pipeline author does not provide an explicit name, the processor manufactures a
          default name. All default names are of the form
            “<literal>!1</literal><replaceable>.m</replaceable><replaceable>.n</replaceable>…” where
            “<replaceable>m</replaceable>” is the position (in the sense of counting sibling
          elements) of the step's highest ancestor element within the pipeline document or library
          which contains it, “<replaceable>n</replaceable>” is the position of the next-highest
          ancestor, and so on, including both steps and non-step wrappers. For example, consider the
          pipeline in <xref linkend="ex2"/>. The <tag>p:declare-step</tag> step has no name, so it gets
          the default name “<literal>!1</literal>”; the <tag>p:choose</tag> gets the name
            “<literal>!1.1</literal>”; the first <tag>p:when</tag> gets the name
            “<literal>!1.1.1</literal>”; the <tag>p:otherwise</tag> gets the name
            “<literal>!1.1.2</literal>”, etc. If the <tag>p:choose</tag> had a name, it would
          not have received a default name, but it would still have been counted and its first
            <tag>p:when</tag> would still have been “<literal>!1.1.1</literal>”.</para>
        <para>Providing every step in the pipeline with an interoperable name has several
          benefits:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>It allows implementers to refer to all steps in an interoperable fashion, for
              example, in error messages.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pragmatically, we say that <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm> are identified by
              a step name/port name pair. By manufacturing names for otherwise anonymous steps, we
              include implicit connections without changing our model.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>In a valid pipeline that runs successfully to completion, the manufactured names
          aren't visible (except perhaps in debugging or logging output).</para>
        <note xml:id="def-name-ncname">
          <para>The format for defaulted names does not conform to the requirements of an <link
              xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-names/#NT-NCName">NCName</link>. This is an
            explicit design decision; it prevents pipelines from using the defaulted names on
              <tag>p:pipe</tag> elements. If an explicit connection is required, the pipeline author
            must provide an explicit name for the step.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

<section xml:id="documents">
<title>Documents</title>

<para>An XProc pipeline processes documents.
<termdef xml:id="dt-document">A <firstterm>document</firstterm> is a
<glossterm>representation</glossterm> and its
<glossterm>document properties</glossterm>.</termdef>.
<termdef xml:id="dt-representation">A <firstterm>representation</firstterm>
is a data structure used by an XProc processor to refer to the actual
document content.</termdef></para>

<para>Documents have associated with them a set of properties. The properties
are key/value pairs. <termdef xml:id="dt-document-properties">The
<firstterm>document properties</firstterm> are exposed to the XProc
pipeline as a map (<code>map(xs:QName, item())</code>).</termdef></para>

<para>Several property keys are defined by this specification:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>content-type</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of the “<code>content-type</code>”
key identifies the media type (<biblioref linkend="rfc2046"/>) of the
representation. The “<code>content-type</code>” <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
always be present. The processor is responsible for assuring that the
<code>content-type</code> property matches the content type of each document
produced on every output port.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>base-uri</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of the “<code>base-uri</code>” key identifies the
base URI of the document. If no such key is present, the document has
no base URI. The processor is responsible for assuring that the <code>base-uri</code>
property matches the base URI of each document produced on every output port.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Other property keys may also be present, including user
defined properties.</para>

<section xml:id="document-types">
<title>Document Types</title>

<para>From an XProc perspective, there are two kinds of documents: XML
documents and non-XML documents. Non-XML documents can be further subdivided
into text documents and binary documents. Text documents are called
out specially because they can be easily represented inline within a
pipeline.</para>

<section xml:id="xml-documents">
<title>XML Documents</title>

<para>Representations of XML documents are instances of
the <biblioref linkend="xpath-datamodel"/>. They are identified by
an XML media type. <termdef xml:id="dt-XML-media-type">The
“<literal>application/xml</literal>” and “<literal>text/xml</literal>
media types and all media types of the form
“<literal>application/<replaceable>something</replaceable>+xml</literal>”
are <firstterm baseform="XML media type">XML media types</firstterm>.
</termdef>
</para>

<para>In order to be consistent with the XPath data model, all general
and external parsed entities <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be fully expanded
in XML documents; they <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> contain any representation of
<biblioref linkend="xml-infoset-rec"/>
<literal role="infoset-property">unexpanded entity reference
information items</literal>.</para>

<para><impl>The level of support for typed values in XDM instances
in an XProc pipeline is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="text-documents">
<title>Text Documents</title>

<para>Text documents are non-XML documents.
<impl>Representations of text documents are are
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl>
</para>

<para>Text documents are identified by a text media type.
<termdef xml:id="dt-text-media-type">Media types of the form
“<literal>text/<replaceable>something</replaceable></literal>”
are <firstterm baseform="text media type">text media types</firstterm>.
</termdef>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="non-xml-documents">
<title>Non-XML Documents</title>

<para><impl>Representations of non-XML documents are
are <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl>
They are identified by media types that are not
<glossterm baseform="XML media type">XML media types</glossterm>.
</para>

<para>Implementors are free to optimize by storing them in convenient
formats, caching them on disk, etc.</para>

</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="media-type-match">
<title>Matching Media Types</title>

<para feature="media-type-match">When an input document arrives on a
port, it must be match at least one of the media types specified on
that input port. It matches if the port specifies no media types or if
the media type of the input document is compatible with at least one
of the specified media types. Two media types are compatible if:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para feature="xml-media-types-compatible">They are both <glossterm
baseform="XML-media-type">XML media types</glossterm>
(<code>application/xml</code> is compatible with <code>image/svg+xml</code>),
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para feature="text-media-types-compatible">they are both <glossterm
baseform="text-media-type">text media types</glossterm>
(<code>text/plain</code> is compatible with <code>text/csv</code>),
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para feature="other-media-types-equal">or they are equal when
compared with the Unicode codepoint collation
(<code>image/png</code> is compatible with <code>image/png</code>).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para feature="impl-media-type-equal"><impl>It is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> what additional
content types are considered equal.</impl>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para><error code="D0038">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if an input document arrives on a port and it does not match the
allowed media types.</error></para>

</section>

</section>

<section xml:id="input-output">
<title>Inputs and Outputs</title>

<para>Most steps have one or more inputs and one
or more outputs. <xref linkend="fig-atomic-step"/> illustrates
symbolically an <glossterm>atomic step</glossterm> with two inputs and
one output.</para>

      <figure xml:id="fig-atomic-step">
        <title>An atomic step</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <alt>An atomic step with two inputs and one output</alt>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="graphics/atomic-step.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

<para>All atomic steps are defined by a <tag>p:declare-step</tag>. The
declaration of an atomic step type defines the input ports, output
ports, and options of all steps of that type. For example, every
<tag>p:validate-with-xml-schema</tag> step has two inputs, named
“<literal>source</literal>” and “<literal>schema</literal>”, one
output named “<literal>result</literal>”, and the same set of options.
</para>
      <para>Like atomic steps, top level, user-defined pipelines also have declarations. The
        situation is slightly more complicated for the other compound steps because they don't have
        separate declarations; each instance of the compound step serves as its own declaration. On
        these compound steps, the number and names of the outputs can be different on each instance
        of the step.</para>
      <para><xref linkend="fig-compound-step"/> illustrates symbolically a compound step with one
        subpipeline and one output. As you can see from the diagram, the output from the compound
        step comes from one of the outputs of the subpipeline within the step.</para>
      <figure xml:id="fig-compound-step">
        <title>A compound step</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <alt>A compound step with two inputs and one output</alt>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="graphics/compound-step.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-declared-inputs">The input ports declared on a step are its
            <firstterm>declared inputs</firstterm>.</termdef>
        <termdef xml:id="dt-declared-outputs">The output ports declared on a step are its
            <firstterm>declared outputs</firstterm>.</termdef> When a step is used in a pipeline, it
        is connected to other steps through its inputs and outputs. </para>

         <para>When a step is used, all of the <glossterm>declared inputs</glossterm> of the step
               <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be connected. Each connection binds the input to a data
            source that may be from a variety of sources (see <xref linkend="connections"/>). <error
               code="S0003">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any declared input is not
               connected.</error></para>
         <para>The <glossterm>declared outputs</glossterm> of a step are only connected when they
            are used by another step or expression.  Usually, this connection is made in reverse
            where the use of the output describes the connection (see <xref linkend="connections"
            />).</para>

<para>The <glossterm>primary output port</glossterm> of a step
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be connected to some consumer. <error
code="S0005">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
primary output port of any step is not connected.</error> Other
outputs can remain unconnected. Any documents produced on an
unconnected output port are discarded.</para>

<para>Primary input and primary output ports may be implicitly
connected if no explicit connection is given, see <xref
linkend="primary-input-output"/>.</para>

<para>Output ports on compound steps have a dual nature: from the
perspective of the compound step's siblings, its outputs are just
ordinary outputs and can be connected the sames other
<glossterm>declared outputs</glossterm>. From the perspective of the
subpipeline inside the compound step, they are inputs into which
something may be connected to produce the output of the compound
step.</para>

<para>Within a compound step, the <glossterm>declared
outputs</glossterm> of the step can be connected to any of the various
available outputs of <glossterm baseform="contained steps">contained
steps</glossterm> as well as other data sources
(see <xref linkend="connections"/>). If a (non-primary)
output port of a compound step is left unconnected, it produces an
empty sequence of documents from the perspective of its
siblings.</para>

      <para>Each input and output on a step is declared to accept or produce either a single
        document or a sequence of documents. It <emphasis>is not</emphasis> an error to connect a
        port that is declared to produce a sequence of documents to a port that is declared to
        accept only a single document. It is, however, an error if the former step actually produces
        more than one document at run time.</para>
      <para>It is also not an error to connect a port that is declared to produce a single document
        to a port that is declared to accept a sequence. A single document is the same as a sequence
        of one document.</para>
      <para>An output port may have more than one connection: it may be connected to more than one
        input port, more than one of its container's output ports, or both. At runtime this will
        result in distinct copies of the output. </para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-signature">The <firstterm>signature</firstterm> of a step is the set
          of inputs, outputs, and options that it is declared to accept.</termdef> The declaration
        for a step provides a fixed signature which all its instances share.</para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-matches">A step <firstterm>matches</firstterm> its signature if and
          only if it specifies an input for each declared input, it specifies no inputs that are not
          declared, it specifies an option for each option that is declared to be required, and it
          specifies no options that are not declared.</termdef> In other words, every input and
        required option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be specified and only inputs and options that are
        declared <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> be specified. Options that aren't required do not have to be
        specified.</para>
      <para>Steps <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> also produce error, warning, and informative messages.
        These messages are captured and provided on the <port>error</port> port inside of a
          <tag>p:catch</tag>. <impl>Outside of a <link linkend="p.try">try/catch</link>, the
          disposition of error messages is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm></impl>. </para>

<para><impl>How inputs are connected to documents outside the pipeline
is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>

<para><impl>How pipeline outputs are connected to documents outside
the pipeline is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>

<para>Input ports <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> specify a content type, or list of
content types, that they accept. Input documents must
<link linkend="media-type-match">match</link> the specified content types.</para>

<section xml:id="external-docs">
        <title>External Documents</title>
        <para>It's common for some of the documents used in processing a pipeline to be read from
          URIs. Sometimes this occurs directly, for example with a <tag>p:document</tag> element.
          Sometimes it occurs indirectly, for example if an implementation allows the URI of a
          pipeline input to be specified on the command line or if an <tag>p:xslt</tag> step
          encounters an <tag>xsl:import</tag> in the stylesheet that it is processing. It's also
          common for some of the documents produced in processing a pipeline to be written to
          locations which have, or at least could have, a URI. </para>
        <para>The process of dereferencing a URI to retrieve a document is often more interesting
          than it seems at first. On the web, it may involve caches, proxies, and various forms of
          indirection. <impl>Resolving a URI locally may involve resolvers of various sorts and
            possibly appeal to <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm> mechanisms such as
            catalog files.</impl></para>
        <para>In XProc, the situation is made even more interesting by the fact that many
          intermediate results produced by steps in the pipeline have base URIs. <impl>Whether (and
            when and how) or not the intermediate results that pass between steps are ever written
            to a filesystem is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
        <para><impl>In Version 3.0 of XProc, how (or if) implementers provide local resolution
            mechanisms and how (or if) they provide access to intermediate results by URI is
              <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
        </para>
        <para>Version 3.0 of XProc does not require implementations to guarantee that multiple
          attempts to dereference the same URI always produce consistent results.</para>
        <note xml:id="note-unsatisfying">
          <para>On the one hand, this is a somewhat unsatisfying state of affairs because it leaves
            room for interoperability problems. On the other, it is not expected to cause such
            problems very often in practice. </para>
          <para>If these problems arise in practice, implementers are encouraged to use the existing
            extension mechanisms to give users the control needed to circumvent them. Should such
            mechanisms become widespread, a standard mechanism could be added in some future version
            of the language.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="primary-input-output">
      <title>Primary Inputs and Outputs</title>
      <para>As a convenience for pipeline authors, each step may have one input port designated as
        the primary input port and one output port designated as the primary output port.</para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-primary-input-port">If a step has a document input port which is
          explicitly marked “<code>primary='true'</code>”, or if it has exactly one document input
          port and that port is <emphasis>not</emphasis> explicitly marked
            “<code>primary='false'</code>”, then that input port is the <firstterm>primary input
            port</firstterm> of the step.</termdef> If a step has a single input port and that port
        is explicitly marked “<code>primary='false'</code>”, or if a step has more than one input
        port and none is explicitly marked as the primary, then the primary input port of that step
        is undefined. A step can have at most one primary input port.</para>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-primary-output-port">If a step has a document output port which is
          explicitly marked “<code>primary='true'</code>”, or if it has exactly one document output
          port and that port is <emphasis>not</emphasis> explicitly marked
            “<code>primary='false'</code>”, then that output port is the <firstterm>primary output
            port</firstterm> of the step.</termdef> If a step has a single output port and that port
        is explicitly marked “<code>primary='false'</code>”, or if a step has more than one output
        port and none is explicitly marked as the primary, then the primary output port of that step
        is undefined. A step can have at most one primary output port.</para>
      <para>The special significance of primary input and output ports is that they are connected
        automatically by the processor if no explicit connection is given. Generally speaking, if
        two steps appear sequentially in a subpipeline, then the primary output of the first step
        will automatically be connected to the primary input of the second.</para>
      <para>Additionally, if a compound step has no declared outputs and the <glossterm>last
          step</glossterm> in its subpipeline has an unconnected primary output, then an implicit
        primary output port will be added to the compound step (and consequently the last step's
        primary output will be connected to it). This implicit output port has no name. It inherits
        the <tag class="attribute">sequence</tag> property of the port connected to it. This rule
        does not apply to <tag>p:declare-step</tag>; step declarations must provide explicit names
        for all of their outputs.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="connections">
      <title>Connections</title>
      <para>Steps are connected together by their input ports and output ports. <error code="S0001"
          >It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if there are any loops in the connections
          between steps: no step can be connected to itself nor can there be any sequence of
          connections through other steps that leads back to itself.</error></para>

         <para><termdef xml:id="dt-connection">A <firstterm>connection</firstterm> associates an
               input or output port with some data source.</termdef>  Such a connection represents a
            binding between the port's name and the data source as described by various locations,
            inline expressions, or readable ports.</para>
         <para>An input port can be connected to:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>The output port of some other step.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>A fixed, inline document or sequence of documents.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>A document read from a URI.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>One of the inputs declared on one of its
                  <glossterm>ancestors</glossterm>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>A special port provided by an ancestor compound step, for example,
                     “<port>current</port>” in a <tag>p:for-each</tag> or <tag>p:viewport</tag>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>When an input accepts a sequence of documents, the documents can come from any
            combination of these locations.</para>
         <para>In contrast, output ports are connected when they are referenced by another input
            port, <glossterm baseform="declared outputs">declared output</glossterm> or other
            expression and may be connected to:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>The input port or input context of some other step.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>An option assigned with <tag>p:with-option</tag> or a
<tag>p:variable</tag> in a compound step.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>One of the outputs declared on its container. </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

         <para>As with an input, the output can be a sequence of documents constructed from any
            combination of the above.</para>
         <para>An output port may have multiple consumers and this results in multiple connections.
            A subset of these connections are the input port connections for various sibling or
            contained steps.</para>
         <para>Within the context of a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>, the <glossterm>declared
               outputs</glossterm> of the compound step must describe their connections.  The set of
            possibilities for this connection is exactly the same set as for any other input port
            within the current <glossterm>environment</glossterm>.</para>


<section xml:id="depends">
<title>Additional dependent connections</title>

<para>The connections between input and output ports form the basis
of the pipeline graph. Any step that depends on the output of another step
is guaranteed to be run after the step on which it depends.</para>

<para>However, it is sometimes the case that one step depends on
another in ways that are not apparent in the input and output
connections. Consider, for example, a pipeline that interacts with two
different web services. It may very well be the case that one web
service has to run before the other, even though the latter does not
consume any output from the former.</para>

<para>In these cases, the pipeline author can add an explicit
dependency with the <tag class="attribute">depends</tag> attribute.
The <tag class="attribute">depends</tag> attribute is allowed on any
step element. The value of the attribute is a space separated list of step names.
<error code="S0073">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any
specified name is not the name of an in-scope step.</error>
</para>

<para>The connections specified by the
<tag class="attribute">depends</tag> attribute taken together with
the input and output connections must not form a cycle in the graph.
</para>

</section>



      <section xml:id="namespace-fixup">
        <title>Namespace Fixup on XML Outputs</title>
        <para>XProc processors are expected, and sometimes required, to perform <glossterm>namespace
            fixup</glossterm> on XML outputs. Unless the semantics of a step explicitly says otherwise:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The in-scope namespaces associated with a node (even those that are inherited from
              namespace bindings that appear among its ancestors in the document in which it appears
              initially) are assumed to travel with that node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Changes to one part of a tree (wrapping or unwrapping a node or renaming an
              element, for example) do not change the in-scope namespaces associated with the
              descendants of the node so changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>As a result, some steps can produce XML documents which have no direct serialization
          (because they include nodes with conflicting or missing namespace declarations, for
          example). <termdef xml:id="dt-namespace-fixup">To produce a serializable
              <glossterm>XML</glossterm> document, the XProc processor must sometimes add additional
            namespace nodes, perhaps even renaming prefixes, to satisfy the constraints of
              <glossterm>Namespaces in XML</glossterm>. This process is referred to as
              <firstterm>namespace fixup</firstterm>.</termdef>
        </para>
        <para>Implementors are encouraged to perform <glossterm>namespace fixup</glossterm> before
          passing documents between steps, but they are not required to do so. Conversely, an
          implementation which <emphasis>does</emphasis> serialize between steps and therefore must
          perform such fixups, or reject documents that cannot be serialized, is also
          conformant.</para>
        <para>Except where the semantics of a step explicitly require changes, processors are
          required to preserve the information in the documents and fragments they manipulate. In
          particular, the information corresponding to the <biblioref linkend="xml-infoset-rec"/>
          properties <literal role="infoset-property">attributes</literal>, <literal
            role="infoset-property">base URI</literal>, <literal role="infoset-property"
            >children</literal>, <literal role="infoset-property">local name</literal>, <literal
            role="infoset-property">namespace name</literal>, <literal role="infoset-property"
            >normalized value</literal>, <literal role="infoset-property">owner</literal>, and
            <literal role="infoset-property">parent</literal>
          <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be preserved.</para>
        <para>The information corresponding to <literal role="infoset-property">prefix</literal>,
            <literal role="infoset-property">in-scope namespaces</literal>, <literal
            role="infoset-property">namespace attributes</literal>, and <literal
            role="infoset-property">attribute type</literal>
          <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> be preserved, with changes to the first three only as required
          for <glossterm>namespace fixup</glossterm>. In particular, processors are encouraged to
          take account of prefix information in creating new namespace bindings, to minimize
          negative impact on prefixed names in content.</para>
        <para><impl>Except for cases which are specifically called out in <biblioref
              linkend="std-components"/>, the extent to which namespace fixup, and other checks for
            outputs which cannot be serialized, are performed on intermediate outputs is
              <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
        <para>Whenever an implementation serializes pipeline contents, for example for pipeline
          outputs, logging, or as part of steps such as <tag>p:store</tag> or
            <tag>p:http-request</tag>, it is a dynamic error if
          that serialization could not be done so as to produce a document which is both well-formed
          and namespace-well-formed, as specified in <glossterm>XML</glossterm> and
            <glossterm>Namespaces in XML</glossterm>, regardless of what serialization method, if
          any, is called for.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="environment">
      <title>Environment</title>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-environment">The <firstterm>environment</firstterm> is a
          context-dependent collection of information available within subpipelines.</termdef> Most
        of the information in the environment is static and can be computed for each subpipeline
        before evaluation of the pipeline as a whole begins. The in-scope bindings have to be
        calculated as the pipeline is being evaluated.</para>
      <para>The environment consists of:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A set of readable ports. <termdef xml:id="dt-readable-ports">The <firstterm>readable
                ports</firstterm> are a set of step name/port name pairs.</termdef> Inputs and
            outputs can only be connected to readable ports.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A default readable port. <termdef xml:id="dt-default-readable-port">The
                <firstterm>default readable port</firstterm>, which may be undefined, is a specific
              step name/port name pair from the set of readable ports.</termdef></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A set of in-scope bindings. <termdef xml:id="dt-in-scope-bindings">The
                <firstterm>in-scope bindings</firstterm> are a set of name-value pairs, based on
                <glossterm>option</glossterm> and <glossterm>variable</glossterm>
              bindings.</termdef></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-empty-environment">The <firstterm>empty environment</firstterm>
          contains no readable ports, an undefined default readable port and no in-scope
          bindings.</termdef>
      </para>
      <para>Unless otherwise specified, the environment of a <glossterm baseform="contained steps"
          >contained step</glossterm> is its <glossterm>inherited environment</glossterm>. <termdef
          xml:id="dt-inherited-environment">The <firstterm>inherited environment</firstterm> of a
            <glossterm baseform="contained steps">contained step</glossterm> is an environment that
          is the same as the environment of its <glossterm>container</glossterm> with the <link
            linkend="dt-standard-modifications">standard modifications</link>. </termdef></para>
      <para>The <phrase xml:id="dt-standard-modifications">standard modifications</phrase> made to
        an inherited environment are:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The declared inputs of the container are added to the <glossterm>readable
              ports</glossterm>.</para>
          <para>In other words, contained steps can see the inputs to their container.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The union of all the declared outputs of all of the step's sibling steps are added
            to the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>.</para>
          <!--
          <para>The union of all the declared outputs of all of the containers's
              <glossterm>contained steps</glossterm> are added to the <glossterm>readable
              ports</glossterm>.</para>
              -->
          <para>In other words, sibling steps can see each other's outputs in addition to the
            outputs visible to their container.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If there is a preceding sibling step element:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If that preceding sibling has a <glossterm>primary output port</glossterm>, then
                that output port becomes the <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Otherwise, the <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> is undefined.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If there <emphasis>is not</emphasis> a preceding sibling step element: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the container has a <glossterm>primary input port</glossterm>, the
                  <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> is that <glossterm>primary input
                  port</glossterm>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Otherwise, the default readable port is unchanged.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

<para>A step with no parent inherits the <glossterm>empty
environment</glossterm>. </para>

<para>Variables and options are lexically scoped. The environment of a step
also includes the <glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> for all of
the variables and options “visible” from its lexical position. Variables
and options can shadow each other, only the lexically most recent bindings
are visible.</para>

         <section xml:id="initial-environment">
            <title>Initial Environment</title>
            <para>When a pipeline is invoked by a processor, an initial environment is constructed.
                  <termdef xml:id="dt-initial-environment">An <firstterm>initial
                     environment</firstterm> is a <glossterm>connection</glossterm> for each of the
                     <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm> and a set of option bindings used to
                  construct the <glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm>.</termdef> This environment
               is used in place of the <glossterm>empty environment</glossterm> that might have
               otherwise been provided.</para>
            <para>An invoked pipeline's <glossterm>initial environment</glossterm> is different from
               the environment constructed for the sub-pipeline of a declared step.  The initial
               environment is constructed for the initial invocation of the pipeline by the
               processor by the outside application.  Steps that are subsequently invoked construct
               an environment as specified in <xref linkend="declare-pipelines"/>.</para>
            <para>When constructing an <glossterm>initial environment</glossterm>, an implementation
               is free to provide any set of mechanisms to construct connections for the input ports
               of the invoked step. These mechanisms are not limited to the variety of mechnisms
               described within this specification. Any extensions are implementation
               defined.</para>
            <para>The set of <glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> are constructed from a set of
               option name/value pairs.  Each option value can be a simple string value, a specific
               data type instance (e.g. xs:dateTime), or a more complex value like a map item.  How
               these values are specified is implementation defined.</para>
         </section>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="xpath-context">
      <title>XPath in XProc</title>

<para>XProc uses XPath 3.1 as an expression language. XPath expressions
are evaluated by the XProc processor in several places: on compound
steps, to compute the default values of options and the values of
variables; on atomic steps, to compute the actual values of options.
</para>

      <para>XPath expressions are also passed to some steps. These expressions are evaluated by the
        implementations of the individual steps.</para>
      <para>This distinction can be seen in the following example:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/xpathcontext.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      <para>The select expression on the variable “<varname>home</varname>” is evaluated by the
        XProc processor. The value of the variable is “<uri>http://example.com/docs</uri>”.</para>
      <para>The <option>href</option> option of the <tag>p:load</tag> step is evaluated by the XProc
        processor. The actual <literal>href</literal> option received by the step is simply the
        string literal “<uri>http://example.com/docs/document.xml</uri>”. (The select expression on
        the <literal>source</literal> input of the <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step is also
        evaluated by the XProc processor.) </para>
      <para>The XPath expression “<literal>@role='chapter'</literal>” is passed literally to the
          <literal>test</literal> option on the <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step. That's because the
        nature of the <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> is that <emphasis>it evaluates</emphasis> the
        expression. Only some options on some steps expect XPath expressions. </para>
      <para>The XProc processor evaluates all of the XPath expressions in <tag class="attribute"
          >select</tag> attributes on variables, options, and inputs, in <tag
          class="attribute">match</tag> attributes on <tag>p:viewport</tag>, and in <tag
          class="attribute">test</tag> attributes on <tag>p:when</tag> steps.</para>

        <section xml:id="xproc-xpath-context-31">
          <title>Processor XPath Context</title>
<para>When the XProc processor evaluates an XPath expression using
XPath, unless otherwise indicated by a particular step, it does so
with the following static context:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>XPath 1.0 compatibility mode</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>False</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known namespaces</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The namespace declarations in-scope for the containing element. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default element/type namespace</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The null namespace.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default function namespace</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The default function namespace is <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions</literal>, as defined in
                  <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/>. Function names that do
                  not contain a colon always refer to the default function namespace, any in-scope
                  binding for the default namespace <emphasis>does not</emphasis> apply. This
                  specification does not provide a mechanism to override the default function
                  namespace.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>In-scope schema definitions</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>A basic XPath 3.1 XProc processor includes the following named type
                  definitions in its in-scope schema definitions:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>All the primitive atomic types defined in <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-2"
                      />, with the exception of <literal>xs:NOTATION</literal>. That is:
                        <literal>xs:string</literal>, <literal>xs:boolean</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:decimal</literal>, <literal>xs:double</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:float</literal>, <literal>xs:date</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:time</literal>, <literal>xs:dateTime</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:duration</literal>, <literal>xs:QName</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:anyURI</literal>, <literal>xs:gDay</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:gMonthDay</literal>, <literal>xs:gMonth</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:gYearMonth</literal>, <literal>xs:gYear</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:base64Binary</literal>, and <literal>xs:hexBinary</literal>.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>The derived atomic type <literal>xs:integer</literal> defined in
                        <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-2"/>. </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>The types <literal>xs:anyType</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:anySimpleType</literal>,
                      <literal>xs:yearMonthDuration</literal>,
                      <literal>xs:dayTimeDuration</literal>, <literal>xs:anyAtomicType</literal>,
                        <literal>xs:untyped</literal>, and <literal>xs:untypedAtomic</literal>
                      defined in <biblioref linkend="xpath-datamodel"/>. </para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>In-scope variables</term>
              <listitem>
<para>Variables and options are lexically scoped. The union of the
<glossterm>specified options</glossterm> and the variables that
are “visible” from the step's lexical position are available
as variable bindings to the XPath processor.
Variables and options can shadow each other, only the lexically most
recent bindings are visible.</para>

<note xml:id="note-no-value">
<para>An option that has neither a specified value nor a default value
will not appear as an in-scope variable. Consequently, an attempt to
refer to that variable will raise an error.</para>
</note>

              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Context item static type</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Document.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Function signatures</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The signatures of the <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/> in namespaces <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions</literal>,
                  <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/math</literal>, <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map</literal> and
                  <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array</literal>. Additionally the function signatures defined in <xref
                    linkend="xpath-extension-functions"/>. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known collations</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Implementation-defined but <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> include the Unicode code
                  point collation. <impl>The version of Unicode supported is
                      <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>, but it is recommended that the
                    most recent version of Unicode be used.</impl>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default collation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Unicode code point collation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Static base URI</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The base URI of the element on which the expression occurs.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known documents</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known default collection type</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><literal>item()*</literal></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known decimal formats</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>And the following dynamic context:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>context item</term>
              <listitem>
<para>A document. The document is either specified with a
<glossterm>connection</glossterm> or is taken from the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>. <error code="D0008">It
is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a document sequence
appears where a document to be used as the context node is
expected.</error>
</para>

<para>When the context node has a non-XML content type, XPath
expressions are evaluated in the context of the corresponding
<glossterm>proxy document</glossterm>.
<termdef xml:id="dt-proxy-document">A <firstterm>proxy document</firstterm> is
an empty document node.</termdef>.</para>

<para>If there is no explicit connection and there is no default
readable port then the context node is undefined.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>context position and context size</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The context position and context size are both “1”. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Variable values</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The union of the in-scope options and variables are available as variable
                  bindings to the XPath processor. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Named functions</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/> and the <xref
                    linkend="xpath-extension-functions"/>. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Current dateTime</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The point in time returned as the current dateTime is
                      <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Implicit timezone</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The implicit timezone is
                    <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default language</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default language is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default calendar</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default calendar is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default place</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default place is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available documents</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available documents (those that may be retrieved with a URI)
                    is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available text resources</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available text resources (those that may be retrieved with a URI)
                is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available collections is
                      <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default collection</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available URI collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available URI collections is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default URI collection</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default URI collection is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Environment variables</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The list of available environment variables is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="step-xpath-context-31">
          <title>Step XPath Context</title>
          <para>When a step evaluates an XPath expression using XPath 3.1, unless otherwise
            indicated by a particular step, it does so with the following static context:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>XPath 1.0 compatibility mode</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>False</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known namespaces</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The namespace declarations in-scope for the containing element.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default element/type namespace</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The null namespace.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default function namespace</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The default function namespace is <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions</literal>, as defined in
                  <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/>. Function names that do
                  not contain a colon always refer to the default function namespace, any in-scope
                  binding for the default namespace <emphasis>does not</emphasis> apply. This
                  specification does not provide a mechanism to override the default function
                  namespace.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>In-scope schema definitions</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The same as the <xref linkend="xproc-xpath-context-31"/>. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>In-scope variables</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None, unless otherwise specified by the step. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Context item static type</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Document.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Function signatures</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The signatures of the <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/> in namespaces <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions</literal>,
                  <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/math</literal>, <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map</literal> and
                  <literal>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array</literal>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known collations</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Implementation-defined but <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> include the Unicode code
                  point collation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default collation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Unicode code point collation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Static base URI</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The base URI of the element on which the expression occurs.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known documents</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known default collection type</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>item()*</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Statically known decimal formats</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>And the following initial dynamic context:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>context item</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The document node of the document that appears on the primary input of the
                  step, unless otherwise specified by the step.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>context position and context size</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The context position and context size are both “1”, unless otherwise specified
                  by the step. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Variable values</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None, unless otherwise specified by the step. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Named functions</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <biblioref linkend="xpath31-functions"/>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Current dateTime</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>An implementation-defined point in time. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Implicit timezone</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The implicit timezone is
                    <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default language</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default language is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default calendar</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default calendar is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default place</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The defualt place is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available documents</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available documents (those that may be retrieved with a URI)
                    is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available text resources</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available text resources (those that may be retrieved with a URI)
                  is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default collection</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>None. </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Available URI collections</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The set of available URI collections is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default URI collection</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The default URI collection is <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Environment variables</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><impl>The list of available environment variables is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <note xml:id="note-amendments">
            <para>Some steps may also provide for implementation-defined or implementation-dependent
              amendments to the contexts. Those amendments are in addition to any specified by
              XProc.</para>
          </note>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xpath-extension-functions">
      <title>XPath Extension Functions</title>

      <para>The XProc processor <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> support the
        additional functions described in this section in XPath expressions
        evaluated by the processor. These functions <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be supported
        in XPath expressions evaluated by a step.</para>

      <note role="editorial">
        <title>Editorial Note</title>
        <para>Explain the reasons for this restriction: Interoperability of processors, functions are mostly
        pointless in step context, step may defer XPath evalution to third party software (or web services).</para>
      </note>

      <section xml:id="f.system-property">
        <title>System Properties</title>
        <para>XPath expressions within a pipeline document can interrogate the processor for
          information about the current state of the pipeline. Various aspects of the processor are
          exposed through the <function>p:system-property</function> function in the pipeline
          namespace:</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:string</type>
<methodname>p:system-property</methodname>
<methodparam><type>xs:string</type><parameter>property</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The <varname>$property</varname> string <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> have the form of an
<link xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-30/#doc-xquery30-EQName">EQName</link>.
If it is a QName, it is expanded using the namespace declarations in
scope for the expression. <error code="D0015">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a QName is specified and it cannot be
resolved with the in-scope namespace declarations.</error> The
<function>p:system-property</function> function returns the string
representing the value of the system property identified by the EQName.
If there is no such property, the empty string <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
be returned.</para>

<para>Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> provide the following
system properties, which are all in the XProc namespace:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:episode</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a string which <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> be unique for each invocation
                of the pipeline processor. In other words, if a processor is run several times in
                succession, or if several processors are running simultaneously, each invocation of
                each processor should get a distinct value from <varname>p:episode</varname>.</para>
              <para>The unique identifier must be a valid <link
                  xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/#NT-Name">XML name</link>. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:locale</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a string which identifies the current environment (usually the OS) 
                language. This is useful for, for example, message
                localization purposes. <impl>The exact format of the language string is
                    <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> but <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> be
                  consistent with the <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute.</impl></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:product-name</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a string containing the name of the implementation, as defined by the
                implementer. This should normally remain constant from one release of the product to
                the next. It should also be constant across platforms in cases where the same source
                code is used to produce compatible products for multiple execution platforms.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:product-version</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a string identifying the version of the implementation, as defined by
                the implementer. This should normally vary from one release of the product to the
                next, and at the discretion of the implementer it may also vary across different
                execution platforms. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:vendor</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a string which identifies the vendor of the processor.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:vendor-uri</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns a URI which identifies the vendor of the processor. Often, this is the
                URI of the vendor's web site.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:version</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns the version(s) of XProc implemented by the processor
                as a space-separated list. For example, a processor that
                supports XProc 1.0 would return “1.0”; a processor that supports
                XProc 1.0 and 2.0 would return “1.0 2.0”; a processor that
                supports only XProc 2.0 would return “2.0”.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:xpath-version</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns the version(s) of XPath implemented by the processor
                for evaluating XPath expressions on XProc elements. The result
                is a space-separated list of versions supported. For example, a
                processor that only supports XPath 2.0 would return “2.0”; a
                processor that supports XPath 2.0 and XPath 3.0 could return
                “2.0 3.0”; a processor that supports only XPath 2.0 would return
                “2.0”.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><varname>p:psvi-supported</varname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Returns true if the implementation supports passing PSVI annotations between
                steps, false otherwise.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

<para>Implementations may support additional system properties but such properties
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be in a namespace and <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be
in the XProc namespace.</para>

      </section>
      <section xml:id="f.step-available">
        <title>Step Available</title>
        <para>The <function>p:step-available</function> function reports whether or not a particular
          type of step is understood by the processor.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:boolean</type>
<methodname>p:step-available</methodname>
<methodparam><type>xs:string</type><parameter>step-name</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The <varname>$step-type</varname> string <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
have the form of an
<link xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-30/#doc-xquery30-EQName">EQName</link>.
If it is a QName, it is expanded using the namespace declarations in
scope for the expression. The
<function>p:step-available</function> function returns true if and
only if the processor knows how to evaluate steps of the specified
type.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="f.iteration-position">
<title>Iteration Position</title>

<para>Both <tag>p:for-each</tag> and <tag>p:viewport</tag> process a
sequence of documents. The iteration position is the position of the
current document in that sequence: the first document has position 1, the
second 2, etc. The <function>p:iteration-position</function> function
returns the iteration position of the nearest
ancestor <tag>p:for-each</tag> or <tag>p:viewport</tag>.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:integer</type>
<methodname>p:iteration-position</methodname>
<void/>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>If there is no <tag>p:for-each</tag> or <tag>p:viewport</tag>
among the ancestors of the element on which the expression involving
<function>p:iteration-position</function> occurs, it returns 1.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="f.iteration-size">
<title>Iteration Size</title>

<para>Both <tag>p:for-each</tag> and <tag>p:viewport</tag> process a
sequence of documents. The iteration size is the total number of documents
in that sequence. The <function>p:iteration-size</function> function
returns the iteration size of the nearest
ancestor <tag>p:for-each</tag> or <tag>p:viewport</tag>.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:integer</type>
<methodname>p:iteration-size</methodname>
<void/>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>If there is no <tag>p:for-each</tag> or <tag>p:viewport</tag>
among the ancestors of the element on which the expression involving
<function>p:iteration-size</function> occurs, it returns 1.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="f.version-available">
<title>Version Available</title>

<para>Returns true if and only if the processor supports the version
specified.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:boolean</type>
<methodname>p:version-available</methodname>
<methodparam><type>xs:string</type><parameter>version</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>A version 1.0 processor will return <literal>true()</literal> when
<code>p:version-available('1.0')</code> is evaluated.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="f.xpath-version-available">
<title>XPath Version Available</title>

<para>Returns true if and only if the processor supports the XPath version
specified.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>xs:boolean</type>
<methodname>p:xpath-version-available</methodname>
<methodparam><type>xs:string</type><parameter>version</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>A processor that supports XPath 2.0 will return <literal>true()</literal> when
<code>p:xpath-version-available('2.0')</code> is evaluated.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="f.make-map">
<title>Make Map</title>

<para>XProc uses maps to pass parameters to steps. Sometimes
it is convenient to represent these maps as XML documents. This function
reads such an XML document and produces a map.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>map(xs:QName,item())</type>
<methodname>p:make-map</methodname>
<methodparam><type>item()</type><parameter>param-set</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The map returned contains (exclusively) the parameters that are
represented by the <parameter>param-set</parameter> item.</para>

<para>The <parameter>param-set</parameter> provided
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <tag>c:param-set</tag> element or a
document. If it is a document, <tag>c:param-set</tag>
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be the document element.
<error code="D0035">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if the element (or document element) passed to
<function>p:make-map</function> is not a <tag>c:param-set</tag>
element.</error></para>

<para>Only <tag>c:param</tag> children of the <tag>c:param-set</tag>
element are considered, all other nodes are ignored. The parameters
represented by those <tag>c:param</tag> children
are added to the map that is returned.
<error code="D0037">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if any of the <tag>c:param</tag> elements are invalid.</error>
</para>

<note xml:id="ednote-what-is-valid" role="editorial">
<title>Editorial Note</title>
<para>Must tie down what “valid” means wrt the c:param element.</para>
</note>
</section>

<section xml:id="f.document-properties">
<title>Document properties</title>

<para>This function retrieves the <glossterm>document properties</glossterm>
of a document as a map.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>map(xs:QName,item())</type>
<methodname>p:document-properties</methodname>
<methodparam><type>document-node()</type><parameter>doc</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The map returned contains (exclusively) the document properties
associated with the <parameter>doc</parameter> specified.</para>

<para feature="document-properties-non-xml-document">The context node
for the <function>p:document-properties</function> function must be an
XPath document node. In order to access the document properties of a
non-XML document, the processor is responsible for manufacturing an
empty document node for this purpose and for maintaining the
association between that empty document node and the corresponding
non-XML document.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="f.document-properties-document">
<title>Document properties document</title>

<para>This function retrieves the <glossterm>document properties</glossterm>
of a document as an XML document.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>document-node()</type>
<methodname>p:document-properties-document</methodname>
<methodparam><type>document-node()</type><parameter>doc</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The document returned is a <code>p:document-properties</code>
document that contains (exclusively) the document properties
associated with the <parameter>doc</parameter> specified. Each key in the
properties becomes an element, each value becomes the content of that element.
For atomic values other than string, an <tag
class="attribute">xsi:type</tag> attribute is added to identify the
type of the value.</para>

<para feature="document-properties-non-xml-document">The context node
for the <function>p:document-properties-document</function> function must be an
XPath document node. In order to access the document properties of a
non-XML document, the processor is responsible for manufacturing an
empty document node for this purpose and for maintaining the
association between that empty document node and the corresponding
non-XML document.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="f.document-property">
<title>Document property</title>

<para>This function retrieves a single value from the
<glossterm>document properties</glossterm> of a document.</para>

<methodsynopsis>
<type>item()</type>
<methodname>p:document-property</methodname>
<methodparam><type>document-node()</type><parameter>doc</parameter></methodparam>
<methodparam><type>xs:QName</type><parameter>key</parameter></methodparam>
</methodsynopsis>

<para>The item returned is the value of the “<code>$key</code>” property
in the document properties. An empty sequence is returned if no such key
exists.</para>

<para feature="document-properties-non-xml-document">The context node
for the <function>p:document-property</function> function must be an
XPath document node. In order to access the document properties of a
non-XML document, the processor is responsible for manufacturing an
empty document node for this purpose and for maintaining the
association between that empty document node and the corresponding
non-XML document.</para>
</section>

      <section xml:id="other-xpath-extension-functions">
        <title>Other XPath Extension Functions</title>
        <para><impl>It is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> if the processor supports
            any other XPath extension functions.</impl> Additional extension functions, if any,
            <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> use any of the XProc namespaces. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="psvi-support">
      <title>PSVIs in XProc</title>
      <para>XML documents flow between steps in an XProc pipeline. <xref
          linkend="infoset-conformance"/> identifies the properties of those documents that
          <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be available. Implementations <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> also have the
        ability to pass PSVI annotations between steps.</para>
      <para><impl>Whether or not the pipeline processor supports passing PSVI annotations between
          steps is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
        <impl>The exact PSVI properties that are preserved when documents are passed between steps
          is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
      <para>A pipeline can use the <varname>p:psvi-supported</varname> system property to determine
        whether or not PSVI properties can be passed between steps.</para>
      <para>A pipeline can assert that PSVI support is required with the <tag class="attribute"
          >psvi-required</tag> attribute:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On a <tag>p:declare-step</tag>, <tag class="attribute"
              >psvi-required</tag> indicates whether or not the declared step requires PSVI support.
              <error code="D0022">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a processor that
              does not support PSVI annotations attempts to invoke a step which asserts that they
              are required.</error></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>On a <tag>p:library</tag>, the <tag class="attribute">psvi-required</tag> attribute
            provides a default value for all of its <tag>p:declare-step</tag>
            <emphasis>children</emphasis> that do not specify a value themselves.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Many of the steps that an XProc pipeline can use are transformative in nature. The
          <tag>p:delete</tag> step, for example, can remove elements and attributes; the
          <tag>p:label-elements</tag> step can add attributes; etc. If PSVI annotations were always
        preserved, the use of such steps could result in documents that were inconsistent with their
        schema annotations.</para>
      <para>In order to avoid these inconsistencies, most steps <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> produce
        PSVI annotated results even when PSVI passing is supported.</para>
      <para>If PSVI passing is supported, the following constraints apply:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> faithfully transmit any PSVI properties
            produced on step outputs to the steps to which they are connected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When only a subset of the input is processed by a step (because a <tag
              class="attribute">select</tag> expression appears on an input port or a <tag
              class="attribute">match</tag> expression is used to process only part of the input),
            any PSVI annotations that appear on the selected input <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
            preserved in the resulting documents passed to the step.</para>
          <para>Note that ID/IDREF constraints, and any other whole-document constraints, may not be
            satisfied within the selected portion, irrespective of what its PSVI properties
            claim.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an output of a compound step is connected to an output which includes PSVI
            properties, those properties <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be preserved on the output of the
            compound step, <emphasis>except</emphasis> for the output of <tag>p:viewport</tag> which
              <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> contain any PSVI properties.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an implementation supports XPath 2.0, the data model constructed with which to
            evaluate XPath expressions and match patterns <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> take advantage
            of as much PSVI information as possible. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Except as specified above, or in the descriptions of individual steps,
            implementations <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> include PSVI properties in the outputs of
            steps defined by this specification. <impl>It is
                <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> what PSVI properties, if any, are
              produced by extension steps.</impl></para>
          <para>The exceptions in the standard XProc steps are the
              <tag>p:validate-with-xml-schema</tag>, <tag>p:validate-with-relax-ng</tag>, and
              <tag>p:validate-with-schematron</tag> steps, <tag>p:xslt</tag> (when XSLT 2.0 is
            used), <tag>p:xquery</tag>, <tag>p:identity</tag>, and <tag>p:split-sequence</tag>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <note xml:id="note-psvi">
        <para>A processor that supports passing PSVI properties between steps is always free to do
          so. Even if <code>psvi-required="false"</code> is explicitly specified, it is not an error
          for a step to produce a result that includes additional PSVI properties, provide it does
          not violate the constraints above.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

<section xml:id="value-templates">
<title>Value Templates</title>

<para>An attribute or text node in a pipeline may, in particular
circumstances, contain embedded expressions enclosed between curly
brackets. Attributes and text nodes that use (or are permitted to use)
this mechanism are referred to respectively as <glossterm
baseform="attribute value template">attribute value
templates</glossterm> and <glossterm baseform="text value
template">text value templates.</glossterm>.</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-value-template">Collectively,
attribute value templates and text value templates are referred to as
<firstterm baseform="value template">value templates</firstterm>.</termdef>
</para>

<para>A value template is a string that contains zero or more
expressions delimited by curly brackets. Outside an expression, a
doubled left or right curly brackets (“<literal>{{</literal>” or
“<literal>}}</literal>”) represents a literal, single bracket and does
not start or end an expression. Once an expression begins, it extends
to the first unmatched right curly bracket that is not within a string
literal or comment.</para>

<para>Value templates are not recursive. Curly brackets inside an
expression are part of that expression and are not recognized as
nested value templates.</para>

<para>
<error code="S0066">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if
an expression does not have a closing right curly bracket or if an
unescaped right curly bracket occurs outside of an expression.
</error>
</para>

<para>It is a static error if the string contained between matching curly
brackets in a value template, when interpreted as an XPath expression,
contains errors. The error is signaled using the appropriate
XPath error code.</para>

<para>
<error code="D0050">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the
XPath expression in an AVT or TVT can not be evaluated.</error>
</para>

<para>
<error code="D0051">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the XPath
expression in an AVT or TVT evaluates to something to other than a sequence
containing atomic values or nodes.</error> Function, array and map items are
explicitly excluded here because they do not have a string representation.
</para>

<section xml:id="attribute-value-templates">
<title>Attribute Value Templates</title>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-attribute-value-template">In an attribute
that is designated as an <firstterm>attribute value
template</firstterm>, an expression can be used by surrounding the
expression with curly brackets (<code>{}</code>), following the
general rules for <glossterm baseform="value template">value
templates</glossterm></termdef>.</para>

<para>Curly brackets are not treated specially in an attribute value
in an XProc pipeline unless the attribute is specifically designated
as one that permits an attribute value template. Option shortcuts
permit attribute value templates.
<impl>Whether or not an extension attribute permits attribute value
templates is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
In an element
syntax summary, the value of an attribute that allows attribute value
templates is surrounded by
curly brackets.</para>

<para>An attribute value template can be seen as an alternating
sequence of zero or more “fixed” (non-expression) parts and expression
parts. Each expression is evaluated with an undefined context
node.</para>

<para>The result of the attribute value template is the concatentation
of the fixed parts and the string-value of the result of evaluating
each expression part.</para>

<note xml:id="note-dynerr">
<para>This process can generate dynamic errors, for example if the
sequence contains an element with a complex content type (which cannot
be atomized).</para>
</note>

<para>The string value of the attribute is the result of the attribute
value template as an <type>xs:untypedAtomic</type>.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="text-value-templates">
<title>Text Value Templates</title>

<para>This section describes how text nodes are processed when they
are designated text value templates. All text nodes that are the
descendants of a <tag>p:inline</tag> element are text value templates
unless the <tag>p:inline</tag> has an <tag
class="attribute">expand-text</tag> attribute with the value
“<code>false</code>”. Text nodes that are not the descendants of
a <tag>p:inline</tag> are never text value templates.</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-text-value-template">In a text node that is
designated as a <firstterm>text value template</firstterm>,
expressions can be used by surrounding each expression with curly
brackets (<code>{}</code>), following the
general rules for <glossterm baseform="value template">value
templates</glossterm>.</termdef>
</para>

<para>A text value template can be seen as an alternating sequence of
zero or more “fixed” (non-expression) parts and expression parts. Each
expression is evaluated with an undefined context node.</para>

<para>This produces a sequence of strings (the fixed parts) and items
(the results of evaluating each expression). Any items that are
non-string atomic values are converted to strings by taking their
string value. Strings are converted into text nodes.</para>

<para>The result of the text value template is this sequence of nodes.
Adjacent text nodes are combined into a single text node.</para>

<note xml:id="unlike-xslt-tvts">
<para>Unlike XSLT, in XProc, text value templates are not atomized
and converted to single text nodes. It is possible to insert nodes with
text value templates in XProc, for example, if the XPath
expressions refer to variables that have node content.</para>
</note>

<para>If the node to be inserted with a text value template is a document
node, all children of the document node are inserted. If the node is an attribute
it is added to an element parent if and only if the attribute either has
no siblings in the XDM sequence or has only attributes as preceding siblings.
<error code="D0052">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the XPath
expression in a TVT evaluates to an attribute and either the parent is not an
element or the attribute has a preceding sibling that it not an attribute.</error>
</para>

<note>
<para>The treatment of attribute nodes within text value templates in XProc 3.0 is
in line with the concept of element constructors in XQuery, so that an attributes
only sequence needs to be at the beginning of the XDM sequence to be added.
</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="options">
<title>Options</title>

<para>Some steps accept options. Options are name/value pairs. The
value of an option can be specified as a default on the step, can be
provided by the caller of the step (overriding any default), or may be
undefined.</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-option">An <firstterm>option</firstterm>
is a name/value pair. The name <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an <link
xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/#dt-expname">expanded
name</link>. The value may be any XDM value.</termdef>
</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-declared-options">The options declared on a
step are its <firstterm>declared options</firstterm>.</termdef> Option
names are always expressed as literal values, pipelines cannot
construct option names dynamically. </para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-specified-options">The options on a step
which have specified values, either because a <tag>p:with-option</tag>
element specifies a value or because the declaration included a
default value, are its <firstterm>specified options</firstterm>.</termdef>
</para>

<para><impl>How outside values are specified for pipeline options on
the pipeline initially invoked by the processor is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl> In other words,
the command line options, APIs, or other mechanisms available to
specify such options values are outside the scope of this
specification.</para>

<para>Some steps require a set of name/value pairs for the operations
they perform. For example, an XSLT stylesheet might have required
parameters or an XQuery query might have external variables.
In the XProc Step Library, the standard way to pass such values to
the step is to use an option named “<literal>parameters</literal>”
whose value is a map item value
<biblioref linkend="lastcall-xslt30"/>.
The map item contains the
mapping of between the names and the values whose interpretation is
specific to the step.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="variables">
<title>Variables</title>

<para>Variables are name/value pairs. Pipeline authors can create
variables to hold computed values.</para>

<para><termdef xml:id="dt-variable">A <firstterm>variable</firstterm>
is a name/value pair. The name <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an <link
xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/#dt-expname">expanded
name</link>. The value may be any XDM value.</termdef>
</para>

<para>Variables and options may shadow each other.</para>
</section>

    <section xml:id="security-considerations">
      <title>Security Considerations</title>
      <para>An XProc pipeline may attempt to access arbitrary network resources: steps such as
          <tag>p:load</tag> and <tag>p:http-request</tag> can attempt to read from an arbitrary URI;
        steps such as <tag>p:store</tag> can attempt to write to an arbitrary location;
          <tag>p:exec</tag> can attempt to execute an arbitrary program. Note, also, that some
        steps, such as <tag>p:xslt</tag> and <tag>p:xquery</tag>, include extension mechanisms which
        may attempt to execute arbitrary code. </para>
      <para>In some environments, it may be inappropriate to provide the XProc pipeline with access
        to these resources. In a server environment, for example, it may be impractical to allow
        pipelines to store data. In environments where the pipeline cannot be trusted, allowing the
        pipeline to access arbitrary resources or execute arbitrary code may be a security
        risk.</para>
      <para><error code="D0021">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> for a pipeline to
          attempt to access a resource for which it has insufficient privileges or perform a step
          which is forbidden.</error>
        <impl>Which steps are forbidden, what privileges are needed to access resources, and under
          what circumstances these security constraints apply is
            <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl>
      </para>
      <para>Steps in a pipeline may call themselves recursively which could result in pipelines
        which will never terminate.</para>
      <para>A conformant XProc processor may limit the resources available to any or all steps in a
        pipeline. A conformant implementation may raise dynamic errors, or take any other corrective
        action, for any security problems that it detects.</para>
    </section>

<section xml:id="versioning-considerations">
<title>Versioning Considerations</title>

<para>A pipeline author <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> identify the version of XProc
for which a particular pipeline was authored by setting the
<tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute. The
<tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute can be specified on
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> or <tag>p:library</tag>.
If specified, the value of
the <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
<type>xs:decimal</type>. <error code="S0063">It is a
<glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the value of the
<tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute is not a
<type>xs:decimal</type>.</error></para>

<para>The version of XProc defined
by this specification is “<literal>3.0</literal>”.</para>

<para>A pipeline author <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> identify the version of XProc
on the document element of a pipeline document.
<error code="S0062">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a
required
<tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute
is not present.</error></para>

<para>The version identified applies
to the element on which the
<tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute appears and all of its descendants,
unless or until another version is explicitly identified.</para>

<para>When a processor encounters an explicit version (other than a
version which it implements), it proceeds in backwards- or
forwards-compatible mode. </para>

<section xml:id="vers-backcomp">
<title>Backwards-compatible Mode</title>
<para>If the processor encounters a request for a previous version of
XProc (e.g., if a "3.0" processor encounters an explicit request for
the "1.0" language), it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> process the pipeline
as if it was a processor for the requested version: it
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> enforce the semantics
of the requested version, it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> report steps not
known in that version as errors, etc.
<error code="S0060">It
is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the processor encounters
an explicit request for a previous version of the language and it is
unable to process the pipeline using those semantics.</error></para>
</section>

<section xml:id="vers-forwcomp">
<title>Forwards-compatible Mode</title>

<para>If the processor encounters an explicit version which it does
not recognize, it processes the pipeline in forwards-compatible mode.
Forwards-compatible mode relaxes several static errors, turning them
into dynamic errors so that a pipeline author can write a pipeline
which conditionally uses new language features.</para>

<para>In forwards-compatible mode:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>On any element in the XProc namespace, unrecognized attributes
(other than extension attributes) are ignored.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>On any step in the XProc namespace, unknown options are ignored.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If a step in the XProc namespace includes an unknown input port
with an explicit connection, the connection is treated normally for
the purpose of computing the dependencies in the pipeline but it is
otherwise ignored. Unknown input ports <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119>
be treated as
<glossterm baseform="primary input port">primary input ports</glossterm>;
it will always be an error if they are used but not explicitly
connected.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If a step in the pipeline includes an explicit connection to an
unknown output port on a step in the XProc namespace, the connection
is treated normally for the purpose of computing the dependencies in
the pipeline. An empty sequence of documents <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
appear on that connection.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>As a consequence of the rules above, future specifications
<rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> change the semantics of existing step
types without changing their names. Although they may add new input
and output ports, such changes should be done with care; they
<rfc2119>should</rfc2119>
in some sense be limited to ancillary inputs and outputs and they
<rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be
<glossterm baseform="primary input port">primary input ports</glossterm>.
</para>

<section xml:id="vers-forwcomp-ex">
<title>Examples</title>

<para>In forwards-compatible mode, it is not a static error to
encounter the following step:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p:string-replace match="div/@class" replace="newclass">
  <p:with-input port="ancillary">
    <p:document href="doc.xml"/>
  </p:with-input>
</p:string-replace>]]></programlisting>

<para>The processor will simply ignore the “<port>ancillary</port>” port.
</para>

          <para>Suppose that XProc version 3.0 changes the definition of the <tag>p:xslt</tag> step
            so that it has an additional output port, <code>messages</code>. Then consider the
            following pipeline: </para>
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p:declare-step xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
                version="99.0">
<p:input port="source"/>
<p:output port="result"/>

  <p:xslt name="style">
    <p:with-input port="stylesheet">
      <p:document href="style.xsl"/>
    </p:with-input>
  </p:xslt>

  <p:sink/>

  <p:count>
    <p:with-input port="source">
      <p:pipe step="style" port="messages"/>
    </p:with-input>
  </p:count>
</p:declare-step>]]></programlisting>

<para>When run by a "99.0" or later processor, it will count the
documents that appear on the <code>messages</code> port. When run by a
“1.0” processor in forwards-compatible mode, the binding to the
“<port>messages</port>” port is not a static error.
Dynamically, the "1.0" processor will always produce
a count of zero, because an empty sequence of documents will always
appear on the <code>messages</code> port.</para>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="syntax">
    <title>Syntax Overview</title>
    <para>This section describes the normative XML syntax of XProc. This syntax is sufficient to
      represent all the aspects of a pipeline, as set out in the preceding sections. <termdef
        xml:id="dt-XML">XProc is intended to work equally well with <biblioref linkend="xml10"/> and
          <biblioref linkend="xml11"/>. Unless otherwise noted, the term
        “<firstterm>XML</firstterm>” refers equally to both versions.</termdef>
      <termdef xml:id="dt-Namespaces-in-XML">Unless otherwise noted, the term <firstterm>Namespaces
          in XML</firstterm> refers equally to <biblioref linkend="xmlns10"/> and <biblioref
          linkend="xmlns11"/>.</termdef>
      <impl>Support for pipeline documents written in XML 1.1 and pipeline inputs and outputs that
        use XML 1.1 is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
    </para>
    <para>Elements in a pipeline document represent the pipeline, the steps it contains, the
      connections between those steps, the steps and connections contained within them, and so on.
      Each step is represented by an element; a combination of elements and attributes specify how
      the inputs and outputs of each step are connected and how options are
      passed.</para>
    <para>Conceptually, we can speak of steps as objects that have inputs and outputs, that are
      connected together and which may contain additional steps. Syntactically, we need a mechanism
      for specifying these relationships.</para>
    <para><glossterm baseform="container">Containment</glossterm> is represented naturally using
      nesting of XML elements. If a particular element identifies a <glossterm>compound
        step</glossterm> then the step elements that are its immediate children form its
        <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>.</para>
    <para>The connections between steps are expressed using names and references to those
      names.</para>
    <para>Six kinds of things are named in XProc:</para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Step types,</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Steps,</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Input ports),</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Output ports,</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Options and variables</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section xml:id="namespaces">
      <title>XProc Namespaces</title>
      <para>There are three namespaces associated with XProc:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri type="xmlnamespace">http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc</uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The namespace of the XProc XML vocabulary described by this specification; by
              convention, the namespace prefix “<literal>p:</literal>” is used for this
              namespace.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri type="xmlnamespace">http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step</uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The namespace used for documents that are inputs to and outputs from several
              standard and optional steps described in this specification. Some steps, such as
                <tag>p:http-request</tag> and <tag>p:store</tag>, have defined input or output
              vocabularies. We use this namespace for all of those documents. The conventional
              prefix “<literal>c:</literal>” is used for this namespace.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri type="xmlnamespace">http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-error</uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The namespace used for errors. The conventional prefix “<literal>err:</literal>”
              is used for this namespace. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>This specification also makes use of the prefix “<literal>xs:</literal>” to refer to the
          <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-1"/> namespace <uri type="xmlnamespace"
          >http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema</uri>. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="scoping">
      <title>Scoping of Names</title>

<para>Names are used to identify step types, steps, ports, options and
variables. Step types, options, and variables are named with EQNames.
Steps and ports are named with NCNames. The scope of a name is a
measure of where it is available in a pipeline. <termdef
xml:id="dt-visible">If two names are in the same scope, we say that
they are <firstterm>visible</firstterm> to each other.
</termdef></para>
      <para>The scope of the names of the step types is the pipeline in which they are declared,
        including any declarations imported from libraries via <tag>p:import</tag>. Nested pipelines
        inherit the step types in scope for their parent.</para>
      <para>In other words, the step types that are in scope in a <tag>p:declare-step</tag> are:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The standard, built-in types (<tag>p:declare-step</tag>, <tag>p:choose</tag>, etc.).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any implementation-provided types. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any step types declared in the <tag>p:declare-step</tag> children of the pipeline element. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The types of any <tag>p:declare-step</tag>s that are
            imported. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any types that are in the scope of any <tag>p:library</tag> that is imported.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any step types that are in scope for the pipeline's parent
              <tag>p:declare-step</tag>, if it has one. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The type of the pipeline itself, if it has one. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The step types that are in scope in a <tag>p:library</tag> are:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The standard, built-in types (<tag>p:declare-step</tag>, <tag>p:choose</tag>, etc.).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any implementation-provided types. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any step types declared in the library (the
              <tag>p:declare-step</tag> children of the <tag>p:library</tag> element). </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The types of <tag>p:declare-step</tag>s that are imported
            into the library. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any types that are in the scope of any <tag>p:library</tag> that is imported.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><error code="S0036">All the step types in a pipeline or library <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
          have unique names: it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any step type name is
          built-in and/or declared or defined more than once in the same scope.</error></para>

<para>The scope of the names of the steps themselves is determined by
the <glossterm>environment</glossterm> of each step. In general, the
name of a step, the names of its sibling steps, the names of any steps
that it contains directly, the names of its ancestors, and the names
of the siblings of its ancestors are all in a common scope. <error
code="S0002">All steps in the same scope <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> have
unique names: it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if two steps
with the same name appear in the same scope.</error></para>

<para>The scope of an input or output port name is the step on which
it is defined. The names of all the ports on any step
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be unique.</para>

<para>Taken together, these uniqueness constraints guarantee that the
combination of a step name and a port name uniquely identifies exactly
one port on exactly one in-scope step.</para>

<para>The scope of option and variable names is determined by where
they are declared. When an option is declared with <tag>p:option</tag>
(or a variable with <tag>p:variable</tag>), unless otherwise
specified, its scope consists of the sibling elements that follow its
declaration and the descendants of those siblings.
</para>
</section>
    <section xml:id="xml-base-attribute">
      <title>Base URIs and xml:base</title>

<para>If a relative URI appears in an option of type <type>xs:anyURI</type>,
the base URI against which it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be made absolute is the base
URI of the <tag>p:option</tag> element. If the option value is
specified using a <link linkend="option-shortcut">syntactic
shortcut</link>, the base URI of the step element on which the shortcut
attribute appears <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be used. In general,
whenever a relative URI appears in an <type>xs:anyURI</type>,
its base URI is the base URI of the nearest ancestor element.</para>

<para>The pipeline author can control the base URIs of elements within
the pipeline document with the <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag>
attribute. The <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> attribute
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> appear on any element in a pipeline and has the
semantics outlined in <biblioref linkend="xml-base"/>.</para>

</section>
    <section xml:id="xml-id-attribute">
      <title>Unique identifiers</title>
      <para>A pipeline author can provide a globally unique identifier for any element in a pipeline
        with the <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attribute.</para>
      <para>The <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attribute <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> appear on any
        element in a pipeline and has the semantics outlined in <biblioref linkend="xml-id"
        />.</para>
    </section>

<section xml:id="syntax-docs-ports">
<title>Associating Documents with Ports</title>

<para> A document or a sequence of documents can be connected to a
port in four ways: <glossterm>by source</glossterm>, <glossterm>by
URI</glossterm>, by providing an <glossterm>inline
document</glossterm>, or by making it
<glossterm baseform="empty-sequence">explicitly empty</glossterm>.
Each of these mechanisms is allowed on the <tag>p:with-input</tag> and
<tag>p:output</tag> elements. Specification <glossterm>by
URI</glossterm>, by providing an <glossterm>inline document</glossterm>, or by making it
  <glossterm baseform="empty-sequence">explicitly empty</glossterm> is allowed on <tag>p:input</tag>.</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Specified by URI</term>
<listitem>
<para><termdef xml:id="dt-by-URI">A document is specified
<firstterm>by URI</firstterm> if it is referenced with a
URI.</termdef> The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute on the
<tag>p:document</tag> element is used to refer to
documents by URI.</para>
            <para>In this example, the input to the <tag>p:identity</tag> step named
                “<literal>otherstep</literal>” comes from “<uri>http://example.com/input.xml</uri>”. </para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/identity.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Specified by source</term>
          <listitem>
            <para><termdef xml:id="dt-by-source">A document is specified <firstterm>by
                  source</firstterm> if it references a specific port on another step.</termdef> The
                <tag class="attribute">step</tag> and <tag class="attribute">port</tag> attributes
              on the <tag>p:pipe</tag> element are used for this purpose. </para>
            <para>In this example, the “<literal>source</literal>” input to the
                <tag>p:xinclude</tag> step named “<literal>expand</literal>” comes from the
                “<literal>result</literal>” port of the step named
              “<literal>otherstep</literal>”.</para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/xinclude.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>See the description of <tag>p:pipe</tag> for a complete description of the ports
              that can be connected.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Specified inline</term>
          <listitem>
            <para><termdef xml:id="dt-inline-document">An <firstterm>inline document</firstterm> is
                specified directly in the body of the element to which it connects.</termdef> The
              content of the <tag>p:inline</tag> element is used for this purpose. </para>
            <para>In this example, the “<literal>stylesheet</literal>” input to the XSLT step named
                “<literal>xform</literal>” comes from the content of the <tag>p:with-input</tag> element
              itself.</para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/xslt.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>Inline documents are considered “quoted”. The pipeline processor passes them
              literally to the port, even if they contain elements from the XProc namespace or other
              namespaces that would have other semantics outside of the <tag>p:inline</tag>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Specified explicitly empty</term>
          <listitem>
            <para><termdef xml:id="dt-empty-sequence">An <firstterm>empty sequence</firstterm> of
                documents is specified with the <tag>p:empty</tag> element.</termdef>
            </para>
            <para>In this example, the “<literal>source</literal>” input to the XSLT 2.0 step named
                “<literal>generate</literal>” is explicitly empty:</para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/xslt-empty.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>If you omit the connection on a primary input port, a connection to the
                <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> will be assumed. Making the connection
              explicitly empty guarantees that the connection will be to an empty sequence of
              documents.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>Note that a <tag>p:input</tag>, <tag>p:with-input</tag>, or <tag>p:output</tag> element may contain more than one
          <tag>p:pipe</tag>, <tag>p:document</tag>, or <tag>p:inline</tag>
        element. If more than one <glossterm>connection</glossterm> is provided, then the specified
        sequence of documents is made available on that port in the same order as the
        connections.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="documentation">
      <title>Documentation</title>
      <para>Pipeline authors may add documentation to their pipeline documents with the
          <tag>p:documentation</tag> element. Except when it appears as a descendant of
          <tag>p:inline</tag>, the <tag>p:documentation</tag> element is completely ignored by
        pipeline processors, it exists simply for documentation purposes. If a
          <tag>p:documentation</tag> is provided as a descendant of <tag>p:inline</tag>, it has no
        special semantics, it is treated literally as part of the document to be provided on that
        port. The <tag>p:documentation</tag> element has no special semantics when it appears in
        documents that flow through the pipeline.</para>
      <para>Pipeline processors that inspect the contents of <tag>p:documentation</tag> elements and
        behave differently on the basis of what they find are <emphasis>not conformant</emphasis>.
        Processor extensions <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be specified with <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="annotations">
      <title>Processor annotations</title>
      <para>Pipeline authors may add annotations to their pipeline documents with the
          <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> element. <impl>The semantics of <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> elements are
            <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl> Processors
          <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> specify a way for their annotations to be identified, perhaps
        with <link linkend="extension-attributes">extension attributes</link>.</para>
      <para>Where <tag>p:documentation</tag> is intended for human consumption,
          <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> elements are intended for processor consumption. A processor might,
        for example, use annotations to identify some particular aspect of an implementation, to
        request additional, perhaps non-standard features, to describe parallelism constraints,
        etc.</para>
      <para>When a <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> appears as a descendant of <tag>p:inline</tag>, it has no
        special semantics; in that context it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be treated literally as part
        of the document to be provided on that port. The <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> element has no
        special semantics when it appears in documents that flow through the pipeline. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="extension-attributes">
      <title>Extension attributes</title>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-extension-attribute">An element from the XProc namespace
            <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> have any attribute not from the XProc namespace, provided that
          the expanded-QName of the attribute has a non-null namespace URI. Such an attribute is
          called an <firstterm>extension attribute</firstterm>.</termdef>
      </para>
      <para>The presence of an extension attribute must not cause the connections between steps to
        differ from the connections that would arise in the absence of the attribute. They must not
        cause the processor to fail to signal an error that would be signaled in the absence of the
        attribute.</para>
      <para>A processor which encounters an extension attribute that it does not implement
          <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> behave as if the attribute was not present.</para>
    </section>

<section xml:id="use-when">
<title>Conditional Element Exclusion</title>

<para>Any element in the XProc namespace may have a
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> attribute which
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> contain an XPath expression that can be
evaluated statically. If the attribute is present and the effective boolean
value of the expression is false, then the element and all of its descendants
are effectively excluded from the pipeline document. If a node is effectively
excluded, the processor <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> behave as if the element
was not present in the document.</para>

<para xml:id="p.use-when">Elements that are not in the XProc namespace <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> also
have a <tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> attribute, but the attribute must
be in the XProc namespace. The semantics of a
<tag class="attribute">p:use-when</tag> attribute
on an element not in the XProc namespace are the same as the semantics of a
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> attribute on an element in the XProc
namespace.</para>

<para>Conditional element exclusion occurs before any static analysis
of the pipeline.</para>

<note xml:id="note-excl-use-when">
<para>The effective exclusion of <tag class="attribute">use-when</tag>
processing occurs after XML parsing and has no effect on well-formedness
or validation errors which will be reported in the usual way. Note also that
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> is not performed when it occurs on the
descendant of a <tag>p:inline</tag> element.</para>
</note>

<para>For the purposes of evaluating a <tag class="attribute">use-when</tag>
expression, the context node, position, and size are all undefined. No
<glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> are available. There are no
readable ports. There are no available documents or available collections.
</para>

<para>There are some additional restrictions on the XPath extension functions
that are available in a <tag class="attribute">use-when</tag>
expression:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The <literal>p:episode</literal> system property
<rfc2119>should not</rfc2119> be used. <impl>The value of
the <literal>p:episode</literal> system property in a
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> expression is
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <function>p:step-available</function> function cannot be used
to test for the availability of extension steps (because the libraries
that declare them may not have been imported). <impl>The results of testing
for steps not in the XProc namespace in a
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> expression are
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The steps available and possibly other aspects of the expression may
depend on the version specified for a pipeline, see
<xref linkend="versioning-considerations"/>. For example, in a “1.0” pipeline,
the processor <rfc2119>should not</rfc2119> report that “2.0” steps are
available.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><error code="S0061">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a
<tag class="attribute">use-when</tag>
expression refers to the context or attempts to refer to any documents
or collections.</error>
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="syntax-summaries"><title>Syntax Summaries</title>

<para>The description of each element in the pipeline namespace is
accompanied by a syntactic summary that provides a quick overview of
the element's syntax:</para>

      <e:rng-fragment name="SomeElement" role="nosummary">
        <grammar xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <define xmlns:sa="http://xproc.org/ns/syntax-annotations" name="SomeElement"
            sa:class="language-example">
            <element name="some-element">
              <attribute name="reqd-attribute">
                <data type="some-type"/>
              </attribute>
              <optional>
                <attribute name="some-attribute">
                  <data type="some-type"/>
                </attribute>
              </optional>
              <optional>
                <attribute name="avt-attribute" sa:avt="true">
                  <data type="some-type"/>
                </attribute>
              </optional>
              <zeroOrMore>
                <choice>
                  <ref name="Some"/>
                  <ref name="Elements"/>
                  <ref name="Allowed"/>
                </choice>
              </zeroOrMore>
              <optional>
                <ref name="OtherElements"/>
              </optional>
            </element>
          </define>
          <define name="Some"><element name="some"><empty/></element></define>
          <define name="Elements"><element name="elements"><empty/></element></define>
          <define name="Allowed"><element name="allowed"><empty/></element></define>
          <define name="OtherElements"><element name="other-elements"><empty/></element></define>
        </grammar>
      </e:rng-fragment>
      <para>The content model fragments in these tableaux are presented in a simple, compact
        notation. In brief:</para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A name represent exactly one occurrence of an element with that name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Parentheses are used for grouping. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Elements or groups separated by a comma (“,”) represent an ordered sequence: a
            followed by b followed by c: (a,b,c).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Elements or groups separated by a vertical bar (“|”) represent a choice: a or b or
            c: (a | b | c).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Elements or groups separated by an ampersand (“&amp;”) represent an unordered
            sequence: a and b and c, in any order: (a &amp; b &amp; c).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An element or group followed by a question mark (“?”) is optional; it may or may not
            occur but if it occurs it can occur only once.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An element or group followed by an asterisk (“*”) is optional and may be repeated;
            it may or may not occur and if it occurs it can occur any number of times. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An element or group followed by a plus (“+”) is required and may be repeated; it
            must occur at least once, and it can occur any number of times. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Required attributes are bold. Optional attributes are followed by a question mark.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If an attribute value is an attribute value template, its type is shown
          in curly brackets: “<code>{ some-type }</code>”.</para>
        </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para xml:id="common-attr">For clarity of exposition,
some attributes and elements are elided from
the summaries:</para><itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>An <tag class="attribute">xml:id</tag> attribute is allowed on any element. It has
  the semantics of <biblioref linkend="xml-id"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>An <tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> attribute is allowed on any element. It has
  the semantics of <biblioref linkend="xml-base"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>A <tag class="attribute">use-when</tag> attribute is allowed on any element, see <xref linkend="use-when"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>A <tag class="attribute">depends</tag> attribute is allowed on any step element, see <xref linkend="depends"/>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>The <tag>p:documentation</tag> and <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> elements are not shown, but
  they are allowed anywhere.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Attributes that are <link linkend="option-shortcut">syntactic shortcuts for option
  values</link> are not shown.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The types given for attributes should be understood as follows:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>ID</type>, <type>NCName</type>, <type>NMTOKEN</type>,
    <type>NMTOKENS</type>, <type>anyURI</type>, <type>boolean</type>,
    <type>integer</type>, <type>string</type>: As per <biblioref
    linkend="xmlschema-2"/> including whitespace normalization as
    appropriate.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>EQName</type>: With whitespace normalization as per
    <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-2"/> for QNames. Note, however, that
    QNames that have no prefix are always in no-namespace, irrespective of the
    default namespace.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>QNameList</type>: As a whitespace separated list of
    QNames, per the definition above.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>PrefixList</type>: As a list with <literal
    role="infoset-property">item type</literal> <type>NMTOKEN</type>,
    per <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-2"/>, including whitespace
    normalization.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>ExcludeInlinePrefixes</type>: As a <type>PrefixList</type>
    per the definition above, with the following extensions: the tokens
    <literal>#all</literal> and <literal>#default</literal> may appear.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>XPathExpression</type>, <type>XSLTMatchPattern</type>:
    As a string per <biblioref linkend="xmlschema-2"/>, including
    whitespace normalization, and the further requirement to be a
    conformant Expression per <biblioref linkend="xpath31"/> or Match
    pattern per <biblioref linkend="xslt20"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para><type>MediaTypes</type>:
    As a whitespace separated list of media types as defined in
    <biblioref linkend="rfc2046"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

    <section xml:id="common-errors">
      <title>Common errors</title>
      <para>A number of errors apply generally:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0059">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the pipeline
              element is not <tag>p:declare-step</tag> or
                <tag>p:library</tag>.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0008">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any element in
              the XProc namespace has attributes not defined by this specification unless they are
                <glossterm baseform="extension
attribute">extension attributes</glossterm>.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0038">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any required
              attribute is not provided.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0077">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the value on an
            attribute of an XProc element does not satisfy the type required for that attribute.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="D0028">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any attribute
              value does not satisfy the type required for that attribute.</error></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0044">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any element in
              the XProc namespace or any step has element children other than those specified for it
              by this specification. In particular, the presence of atomic steps for which there is
              no visible declaration may raise this error. </error></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0037">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if any step directly
              contains text nodes that do not consist entirely of whitespace.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="D0019">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any option value
              does not satisfy the type required for that option.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="S0015">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a compound step
              has no <glossterm>contained steps</glossterm>.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="D0012">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any attempt is
              made to dereference a URI where the scheme of the URI reference is not
              supported.</error> Implementations are encouraged to support as many schemes as is
            practical and, in particular, they <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> support both the
              <literal>file:</literal> and <literal>http(s):</literal> schemes. <impl>The set of URI
              schemes actually supported is <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><error code="D0030">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a step is unable
              or incapable of performing its function.</error> This is a general error code for
            “step failed” (e.g., if the input isn't of the expected type or if attempting to process
            the input causes the implementation to abort). Users and implementers who create
            extension steps are encouraged to use this code for general failures.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In most steps which use a select expression or match pattern, any kind of node can
            be identified by the expression or pattern. However, some expressions and patterns on
            some steps are only applicable to some kinds of nodes (e.g., it doesn't make sense to
            speak of adding attributes to a comment!). </para>
          <para><error code="C0023">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a select
              expression or match pattern returns a node type that is not allowed by the
              step.</error>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If an XProc processor can determine statically that a dynamic error will
          <emphasis>always</emphasis> occur, it <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> report that error statically
        provided that the error <emphasis>does not</emphasis> occur among the descendants of a
          <tag>p:try</tag>. Dynamic errors inside a <tag>p:try</tag>
        <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be reported statically. They must be raised dynamically so that
          <tag>p:catch</tag> processing can be performed on them. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="steps">
    <title>Steps</title>
    <para>This section describes the core language steps of XProc; the full
vocabulary of standard, atomic steps is described in
<biblioref linkend="std-components"/>.</para>

<para>The following dynamic errors are described in the atomic step vocabulary.
They are repeated here so that the list of dynamic errors is wholly contained
within this specification.</para>

<note xml:id="ednote-dup-derrs" role="editorial">
<title>Editorial Note</title>
<para>This is not the right long term solution.</para>
</note>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0014">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> for any unqualified attribute
names other than “<literal>name</literal>”,
“<literal>namespace</literal>”, or “<literal>value</literal>” to
appear on a <code>c:param</code> element.</error></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0025" >It is a <glossterm>dynamic
error</glossterm> if the <tag class="attribute" >namespace</tag>
attribute is specified on <code>c:param</code>,
the <tag class="attribute">name</tag> contains
a colon, and the specified namespace is not the same as the in-scope
namespace binding for the specified prefix.</error></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0018">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the <code>c:parameter-set</code>
parameter list contains
any elements other than <tag>c:param</tag>.</error></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0034">On steps which allow independent specification
of a namespace and a name, it is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> to specify a new namespace or
prefix if the lexical value of the specified name contains a
colon.</error></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section xml:id="pipelines">
<title>Pipelines</title>

<para>The document element of a pipeline document is
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> which declares a pipeline that can be
evaluated by an XProc processor.</para>

<para>It encapsulates the behavior of a
<glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. Its children declare inputs,
outputs, and options that the pipeline exposes and identify the steps
in its subpipeline.
</para>

<para>Viewed from the outside, a <tag>p:declare-step</tag> is a black
box which performs some calculation on its inputs and produces its
outputs. From the pipeline author's perspective, the computation
performed by the pipeline is described in terms of
<glossterm>contained steps</glossterm> which read the pipeline's
inputs and produce the pipeline's outputs.</para>

<para>A <tag>p:declare-step</tag> element can also be nested inside
other <tag>p:declare-step</tag> or <tag>p:library</tag> elements in
which case it simply declares a pipeline that will be run
elsewhere.</para>

<para>For more details, see <xref linkend="p.declare-step"/>.</para>

<section xml:id="example-pipeline"
         role="tocsuppress">
<title>Example</title>
<para>A pipeline might accept a document as input; perform XInclude, validation, and
transformation; and produce the transformed document as its output.</para>
<example xml:id="ex.p.pipeline">
  <title>A Sample Pipeline Document</title>
  <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/pipeline.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
</example>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="p.for-each">
<title>p:for-each</title>

<para>A for-each is specified by the <tag>p:for-each</tag> element. It
is a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm> that processes a sequence of
documents, applying its <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> to each
document in turn.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="ForEach"/>

<para>When a pipeline needs to process a sequence of documents using a
subpipeline that only processes a single document, the
<tag>p:for-each</tag> construct can be used as a wrapper around that
subpipeline. The <tag>p:for-each</tag> will apply that subpipeline to
each document in the sequence in turn.</para>
<para>The result of the <tag>p:for-each</tag> is a
        sequence of documents produced by processing each individual document in the input sequence.
        If the <tag>p:for-each</tag> has one or more output ports, what appears on each of those
        ports is the sequence of documents that is the concatenation of the sequence produced by
        each iteration of the loop on the port to which it is connected. If the iteration source for
        a <tag>p:for-each</tag> is an empty sequence, then the subpipeline is never run and an empty
        sequence is produced on all of the outputs. </para>

<para>The <tag>p:for-each</tag> has a single anonymous input: its
<glossterm>connection</glossterm> is provided by the
<tag>p:with-input</tag>. If no iteration sequence is explicitly provided,
then the iteration source is read from the <glossterm>default readable
port</glossterm>.</para>

<para>The processor provides each document, one at a time, to the
          <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> represented by the children of the
          <tag>p:for-each</tag> on a port named <port>current</port>.</para>
<para>For each declared
        output, the processor collects all the documents that are produced for that output from all
        the iterations, in order, into a sequence. The result of the <tag>p:for-each</tag> on that
        output is that sequence of documents.</para>
      <!--
<para>The <glossterm>environment</glossterm> of a <tag>p:for-each</tag> is its
inherited environment
with the <link linkend="dt-standard-modifications">standard modifications</link>.</para>
-->
      <para>The environment inherited by the <glossterm>contained steps</glossterm> of a
          <tag>p:for-each</tag> is the <glossterm>inherited environment</glossterm> with these
        modifications:</para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The port named “<port>current</port>” on the <tag>p:for-each</tag> is added to the
              <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The port named “<port>current</port>” on the <tag>p:for-each</tag> is made the
              <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><para>If the <tag>p:for-each</tag> has a <glossterm>primary output
          port</glossterm> (explicit or <link linkend="primary-input-output">supplied by
          default</link>) and that port has no <glossterm>connection</glossterm>, then it is
        connected to the <glossterm>primary output port</glossterm> of the <glossterm>last
          step</glossterm> in the <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. <error code="S0006">It is a
            <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the primary output port has no explicit
          connection and the <glossterm>last step</glossterm> in the subpipeline does not have a
          primary output port.</error></para>
<para>Note that outputs declared for a
          <tag>p:for-each</tag> serve a dual role. Inside the <tag>p:for-each</tag>, they are used
        to read results from the subpipeline. Outside the <tag>p:for-each</tag>, they provide the
        aggregated results.</para>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">sequence</tag> attribute on a
          <tag>p:output</tag> inside a <tag>p:for-each</tag> only applies inside the step. From the
        outside, all of the outputs produce sequences.</para><section
        xml:id="for-each-xpath-context">
        <title>XPath Context</title>
        <para>Within a <tag>p:for-each</tag>, the <function>p:iteration-position</function> and
            <function>p:iteration-size</function> are taken from the sequence of documents that will
          be processed by the <tag>p:for-each</tag>. The total number of documents is the
            <function>p:iteration-size</function>; the ordinal value of the current document (the
          document appearing on the <port>current</port> port) is the
            <function>p:iteration-position</function>.</para>
        <note xml:id="impl1">
          <title>Note to implementers</title>
          <para>In the case where no XPath expression that must be evaluated by the processor makes
            any reference to <function>p:iteration-size</function>, its value does not actually have
            to be calculated (and the entire input sequence does not, therefore, need to be buffered
            so that its size can be calculated before processing begins).</para>
        </note>
      </section><section xml:id="example-for-each" role="tocsuppress">
        <title>Example</title>
        <para>A <tag>p:for-each</tag> might accept a sequence of chapters as its input, process each
          chapter in turn with XSLT, a step that accepts only a single input document, and produce a
          sequence of formatted chapters as its output.</para>
        <example xml:id="ex.p.for-each">
          <title>A Sample For-Each</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/for-each.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>The <code>//chapter</code> elements of the document are selected. Each chapter is
          transformed into HTML and XSL Formatting Objects using an XSLT step. The resulting HTML
          and FO documents are aggregated together and appear on the <literal>html-results</literal>
          and <literal>fo-results</literal> ports, respectively, of the <literal>chapters</literal>
          step itself.</para>
      </section></section>

<section xml:id="p.viewport">
<title>p:viewport</title>

<para>A viewport is specified by the <tag>p:viewport</tag> element. It
is a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm> that processes a single XML
document, applying its <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> to one or
more subtrees of the document. </para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Viewport"/>

<para>The result of the <tag>p:viewport</tag> is a copy of the
original document where the selected subtrees have been replaced by
the results of applying the subpipeline to them.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:viewport</tag> has a single anonymous input: its
<glossterm>connection</glossterm> is provided by the
<tag>p:with-input</tag>. If no document is explicitly provided,
then the viewport source is read from the <glossterm>default readable
port</glossterm>. If the <tag>p:viewport</tag> input is a sequence,
each document in the sequence is processed in turn producing a sequence
on the output.</para>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">match</tag> attribute specifies
        an XSLT match pattern. Each matching node in the source document is wrapped in a document
        node, as necessary, and provided, one at a time, to the viewport's
          <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> on a port named <port>current</port>. The base URI of
        the resulting document that is passed to the subpipeline is the base URI of the matched
        element or document. <error code="D0010">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the
            <tag class="attribute">match</tag> expression on <tag>p:viewport</tag> does not match an
          element or document.</error>
      </para>
<para>After a match is found, the entire subtree rooted at that match is processed as a
        unit. No further attempts are made to match nodes among the descendants of any matched
        node.</para>
<para>The environment inherited by the <glossterm>contained steps</glossterm> of
        a <tag>p:viewport</tag> is the <glossterm>inherited environment</glossterm> with these
        modifications:</para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The port named “<port>current</port>” on the <tag>p:viewport</tag> is added to the
              <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The port named “<port>current</port>” on the <tag>p:viewport</tag> is made the
              <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist><para>The <tag>p:viewport</tag> must contain a single, <glossterm>primary
          output port</glossterm> declared explicitly or <link linkend="primary-input-output"
          >supplied by default</link>. If that port has no <glossterm>connection</glossterm>, then
        it is connected to the <glossterm>primary output port</glossterm> of the <glossterm>last
          step</glossterm> in the <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. <error code="S0006">It is a
            <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the primary output port is unconnected and the
            <glossterm>last step</glossterm> in the subpipeline does not have a primary output
          port.</error></para>
<para>What appears on the output from the <tag>p:viewport</tag> will
        be a copy of the input document where each matching node is replaced by the result of
        applying the subpipeline to the subtree rooted at that node. In other words, if the match
        pattern matches a particular element then that element is wrapped in a document node and
        provided on the <port>current</port> port, the subpipeline in the <tag>p:viewport</tag> is
        evaluated, and the result that appears on the <port>output</port> port replaces the matched
        element. </para>
<para>If no documents appear on the <port>output</port> port, the matched
        element will effectively be deleted. If exactly one document appears, the contents of that
        document will replace the matched element. If a sequence of documents appears, then the
        contents of each document in that sequence (in the order it appears in the sequence) will
        replace the matched element.</para>
<para>The output of the <tag>p:viewport</tag> itself is a
        single document that appears on a port named “<literal>result</literal>”. Note that the
        semantics of <tag>p:viewport</tag> are special. The <port>output</port> port in the
          <tag>p:viewport</tag> is used only to access the results of the subpipeline. The output of
        the step itself appears on a port with the fixed name “<literal>result</literal>” that is
        never explicitly declared.</para><section xml:id="viewport-xpath-context">
        <title>XPath Context</title>
        <para>Within a <tag>p:viewport</tag>, the <function>p:iteration-position</function> and
            <function>p:iteration-size</function> are taken from the sequence of documents that will
          be processed by the <tag>p:viewport</tag>. The total number of documents is the
            <function>p:iteration-size</function>; the ordinal value of the current document (the
          document appearing on the <port>current</port> port) is the
            <function>p:iteration-position</function>.</para>
        <note xml:id="impl2">
          <title>Note to implementers</title>
          <para>In the case where no XPath expression that must be evaluated by the processor makes
            any reference to <function>p:iteration-size</function>, its value does not actually have
            to be calculated (and the entire input sequence does not, therefore, need to be buffered
            so that its size can be calculated before processing begins).</para>
        </note>
      </section><section xml:id="example-viewport" role="tocsuppress">
        <title>Example</title>
        <para>A <tag>p:viewport</tag> might accept an XHTML document as its input, add an
            <tag>hr</tag> element at the beginning of all <tag>div</tag> elements that have the
          class value “chapter”, and return an XHTML document that is the same as the original
          except for that change.</para>
        <example xml:id="ex.p.viewport">
          <title>A Sample Viewport</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/viewport.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>The nodes which match <code>h:div[@class='chapter']</code> in the input document are
          selected. An <code>hr</code> is inserted as the first child of each <code>h:div</code> and
          the resulting version replaces the original <code>h:div</code>. The result of the whole
          step is a copy of the input document with a horizontal rule as the first child of each
          selected <code>h:div</code>.</para>
      </section></section>

<section xml:id="p.choose">
<title>p:choose</title>

<para>A choose is specified by the <tag>p:choose</tag> element. It is
a <glossterm>multi-container step</glossterm> that selects exactly one
of a list of alternative <glossterm baseform="subpipeline"
>subpipelines</glossterm> based on the evaluation of XPath
expressions.</para>

      <e:rng-pattern name="Choose"/>

<para>A <tag>p:choose</tag> contains an arbitrary number of
alternative <glossterm
baseform="subpipeline">subpipelines</glossterm>, exactly one of which
will be evaluated. <error code="S0074">It is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:choose</tag> has neither a
<tag>p:when</tag> nor a <tag>p:otherwise</tag>.</error></para>

<para>The list of alternative subpipelines consists of zero or more
subpipelines guarded by an XPath expression, followed optionally by a
single default subpipeline.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:choose</tag> considers each subpipeline in turn and
selects the first (and only the first) subpipeline for which the guard
expression evaluates to true in its context. If there are no
subpipelines for which the expression evaluates to true, the default
subpipeline, if it was specified, is selected.</para>

<para>After a <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> is selected, it is
evaluated as if only it had been present.</para>

<para>The outputs of the <tag>p:choose</tag> are taken from the
outputs of the selected <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. The
outputs <emphasis>available</emphasis> from the <tag>p:choose</tag>
are union of all of the outputs declared in any of its alternative
subpipelines.</para>

<para>Consider a <tag>p:choose</tag> that has two alternative
subpipelines where one declares output ports “A” and “B” and the other
declares output ports “B” and “C”. The outputs available from the
<tag>p:choose</tag> are “A”, “B”, and “C”. No documents appear on any
outputs not declared in the subpipline actually selected.</para>

<para>In order to maintain consistency with respect to the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>, if any subpipeline has a
<glossterm>primary output port</glossterm>, even implicitly, then
<emphasis>every</emphasis> subpipline must have exactly the same
primary output port. In some cases, this may require making the implicit
primary output explicit in order to assure that it has the same name.
</para>

<para>As a convenience to authors, it is not an error if some
subpipelines declare outputs that can produce sequences and some do
not. Each output of the <tag>p:choose</tag> is declared to produce a
sequence if that output is declared to produce a sequence in any of
its subpipelines.</para>

<para><error code="D0004">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
error</glossterm> if no <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> is selected
by the <tag>p:choose</tag> and no default is provided.</error></para>

<para>The <tag>p:choose</tag> can specify the context node against
which the XPath expressions that occur on each branch are evaluated.
The context node is specified as a <glossterm>connection</glossterm>
in the <tag>p:with-input</tag>. If no explicit connection is provided,
the <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> is used. If the
context node is connected to <tag>p:empty</tag>, or is unconnected and
the <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> is undefined, the
context item is undefined. <error code="D0005">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if more than one document appears
on the connection for this input port.</error>
</para>

<para>Each conditional <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> is
represented by a <tag>p:when</tag> element. The default branch is
represented by a <tag>p:otherwise</tag> element.</para>

<section xml:id="p.when"><title>p:when</title><para>A
          when specifies one subpipeline guarded by a test expression. </para>
        <e:rng-pattern name="When"/>
        <para>Each <tag>p:when</tag> branch of the <tag>p:choose</tag> has a <tag class="attribute"
            >test</tag> attribute which <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> contain an XPath expression. That
          XPath expression's effective boolean value is the guard for the
            <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> contained within that
          <tag>p:when</tag>.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:when</tag> can specify a context node against which
its <tag class="attribute">test</tag> expression is to be evaluated.
That context node is specified as a <glossterm>connection</glossterm>
for the <tag>p:with-input</tag>. If no context is specified on the
<tag>p:when</tag>, the context of the <tag>p:choose</tag> is
used.</para>
<para><error code="D0005">If the <tag
class="attribute">collection</tag> attribute is not specified, or if
its value is false,
it is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
more than one document appears on the connection for the <tag>p:when</tag>
test expression.</error> If the collection attribute has the value true,
then the default collection will contain all of the documents that appeared
on that input and the context item will be undefined.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="p.otherwise"
><title>p:otherwise</title><para>An otherwise specifies the default
branch; the subpipeline selected if no test expression on any
preceding <tag>p:when</tag> evaluates to true.</para>

        <e:rng-pattern name="Otherwise"/>
      </section><section xml:id="example-choose" role="tocsuppress">
        <title>Example</title>
        <para>A <tag>p:choose</tag> might test the version attribute of the document element and
          validate with an appropriate schema.</para>
        <example xml:id="ex.p.choose">
          <title>A Sample Choose</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/choose.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
      </section></section>

<section xml:id="p.if">
<title>p:if</title>

<para>A <tag>p:if</tag> specifies a single subpipeline guarded by a test expression.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="If"/>

<para>The <tag>p:if</tag> has a <tag class="attribute">test</tag>
attribute which <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> contain an XPath expression.
That XPath expression's effective boolean value is the guard for the
<glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> contained within it.
</para>

<para>The <tag>p:if</tag> can specify a context node against which
its <tag class="attribute">test</tag> expression is to be evaluated.
That context node is specified as a <glossterm>connection</glossterm>
for the <tag>p:with-input</tag>. If no context is specified on the
<tag>p:if</tag>, the context comes from the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>.</para>

<para><error code="D0005">If the <tag
class="attribute">collection</tag> attribute is not specified, or if
its value is false,
it is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
more than one document appears on the connection for the <tag>p:if</tag>
test expression.</error> If the collection attribute has the value true,
then the default collection will contain all of the documents that appeared
on that input and the context item will be undefined.
</para>

<para>If the effective boolean value of the test expression is true, then
the subpipline will be run. If it is not run, then none of the output ports
on the <tag>p:if</tag> will produce any documents.</para>
</section>

    <section xml:id="p.group"><title>p:group</title><para>A group is specified by the
          <tag>p:group</tag> element. In a <tag>p:try</tag>, it is a non-step wrapper, everywhere
        else, it is a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>. A group encapsulates the behavior of its
          <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="Group"/>
      <para>A <tag>p:group</tag> is a convenience wrapper for a collection of steps. </para><section
        xml:id="example-group" role="tocsuppress">
        <title>Example</title>
        <example xml:id="ex.p.group">
          <title>An Example Group</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/group.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </example>
      </section></section>

<section xml:id="p.try">
<title>p:try</title>

<para>A try/catch is specified by the <tag>p:try</tag> element. It is
a <glossterm>multi-container step</glossterm> that isolates a
<glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>, preventing any dynamic errors that
arise within it from being exposed to the rest of the pipeline.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Try"/>

<para>The <tag>p:group</tag> represents the initial subpipeline and
the recovery (or “catch”) pipelines are identified with
<tag>p:catch</tag> elements. The <tag>p:finally</tag> pipeline always
runs after the <tag>p:try</tag>.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:try</tag> step evaluates the initial subpipeline and,
if no errors occur, the outputs of that pipeline are the outputs of
the <tag>p:try</tag> step. However, if any errors occur, the
<tag>p:try</tag> abandons the first subpipeline, discarding any output
that it might have generated, and considers the recovery
subpipelines.</para>

<para>Each <tag>p:catch</tag> pipeline is considered in document
order. All except the last <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> have a
<tag class="attribute">code</tag> attribute. If any of the specified error
codes matches the error that was raised in the <tag>p:group</tag>, then
that <tag>p:catch</tag> is selected as the recovery pipeline.
If the last <tag>p:catch</tag> does not have a <tag class="attribute">code</tag>
attribute, it is selected if no preceding <tag>p:catch</tag> has a
matching error code.
If there is no matching <tag>p:catch</tag>, the <tag>p:try</tag> fails.
<error code="S0064">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if the <tag class="attribute">code</tag> attribute is missing from
any but the last <tag>p:catch</tag> or if any error code is
repeated.</error></para>

<para>If the recovery subpipeline is evaluated, the outputs of the
recovery subpipeline are the outputs of the <tag>p:try</tag> step. If
the recovery subpipeline is evaluated and a step within that
subpipeline fails, the <tag>p:try</tag> fails.
Irrespective of whether the initial subpipeline succeeds or fails,
if any recovery pipelines are selected, and whether they succeed or fail,
the <tag>p:finally</tag> block is <emphasis>always</emphasis> run after
all other processing of the <tag>p:try</tag> has finished.</para>

<para>The outputs of the <tag>p:try</tag> are taken from the
outputs of the initial <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> or the recovery
subpipline if an error occurred in the initial subpipeline. The
outputs <emphasis>available</emphasis> from the <tag>p:try</tag>
are union of all of the outputs declared in any of its alternative
subpipelines.</para>

<para>Consider a <tag>p:try</tag> that has an initial
subpipeline that declares output ports “A” and “B” and a recovery
subpipeline that
declares output ports “B” and “C”. The outputs available from the
<tag>p:try</tag> are “A”, “B”, and “C”. No documents appear on any
outputs not declared in the subpipeline whose results are actually
returned.</para>

<para>In order to maintain consistency with respect to the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>, if any subpipeline has a
<glossterm>primary output port</glossterm>, even implicitly, then
<emphasis>every</emphasis> subpipline must have exactly the same
primary output port. In some cases, this may require making the implicit
primary output explicit in order to assure that it has the same name.
</para>

<para>As a convenience to authors, it is not an error if an output
port can produce a sequence in the initial subpipeline but not in the
recovery subpipeline, or vice versa. Each output of the
<tag>p:try</tag> is declared to produce a sequence if that output is
declared to produce a sequence in either of its subpipelines.</para>

<para>A pipeline author can cause an error to occur with the
<tag>p:error</tag> step.</para>

<para>The recovery subpipeline of a <tag>p:try</tag> is identified
with a <tag xml:id="p.catch">p:catch</tag>:</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Catch"/>

<para>The environment inherited by the <glossterm>contained
steps</glossterm> of the <tag>p:catch</tag> is the
<glossterm>inherited environment</glossterm> with this
modification:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The port named “<port>error</port>” on the <tag>p:catch</tag> is
added to the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>What appears on the <port>error</port> output port is an <link
linkend="err-vocab">error document</link>. The error document may
contain messages generated by steps that were part of the initial
subpipeline. Not all messages that appear are indicative of errors;
for example, it is common for all <tag>xsl:message</tag> output from
the XSLT component to appear on the <port>error</port> output port. It
is possible that the component which fails may not produce any
messages at all. It is also possible that the failure of one component
may cause others to fail so that there may be multiple failure
messages in the document.</para>

<para>Irrespective of which pipeline is evaluated, the last thing that
the <tag>p:try</tag> step does is evaluate the
<tag xml:id="p.finally">p:finally</tag>
pipeline. This happens <emphasis>even if</emphasis> the <tag>p:try</tag>
fails.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Finally"/>

<para>The <tag>p:finally</tag> has no inputs and no outputs. It exists
only to handle recovery and resource cleanup tasks. If cleanup tasks
require access to readable ports, put them in the <tag>p:catch</tag>
block of an enclosing <tag>p:try</tag>.</para>

<section xml:id="err-vocab">
<title>The Error Vocabulary</title>

<para>In general, it is very difficult to predict error behavior. Step
failure may be catastrophic (programmer error), or it may be the
result of user error, resource failures, etc. Steps may detect more
than one error, and the failure of one step may cause other steps to
fail as well.</para>

<para>The <tag>p:try</tag>/<tag>p:catch</tag> mechanism gives pipeline
authors the opportunity to process the errors that caused the
<tag>p:try</tag> to fail. In order to facilitate some modicum of
interoperability among processors, errors that are reported on the
<literal>error</literal> output port of a <tag>p:catch</tag>
<rfc2119>should</rfc2119> conform to the format described here.
</para>

<section xml:id="cv.errors">
<title>c:errors</title>

<para>The error vocabulary consists of a root element,
<tag>c:errors</tag> which contains zero or more <tag>c:error</tag>
elements.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Errors"/>

</section>

<section xml:id="cv.error">
<title>c:error</title>

<para>Each specific error is represented by an <tag>c:error</tag>
element:</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Error"/>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">name</tag> and <tag
class="attribute">type</tag> attributes identify the name and type,
respectively, of the step which failed.</para>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">code</tag> is an EQName which
identifies the error. For steps which have defined error codes, this
is an opportunity for the step to identify the error in a
machine-processable fashion. Many steps omit this because they do not
include the concept of errors identified by EQNames.</para>

<para>If the error was caused by a specific document, or by the
location of some erroneous construction in a specific document, the
<tag class="attribute">href</tag>, <tag class="attribute" >line</tag>,
<tag class="attribute">column</tag>, and <tag class="attribute"
>offset</tag> attributes identify this location. Generally, the error
location is identified either with line and column numbers or with an
offset from the beginning of the document, but not usually
both.</para>

<para>The content of the <tag>c:error</tag> element is any well-formed
XML. Specific steps, or specific implementations, may provide more
detail about the format of the content of an error
message.</para>

</section>
<section xml:id="error-example">
<title>Error Example</title>

<para>Consider the following XSLT stylesheet:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                version="1.0">

<xsl:template match="/">
  <xsl:message terminate="yes">
    <xsl:text>This stylesheet is </xsl:text>
    <emph>pointless</emph>
    <xsl:text>.</xsl:text>
  </xsl:message>
</xsl:template>

</xsl:stylesheet>]]></programlisting>

<para>If it was used in a step named “xform” in a <tag>p:try</tag>,
the following error document might be produced:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<c:errors xmlns:c="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc-step">
  <c:error name="xform" type="p:xslt"
             href="style.xsl" line="6">This stylesheet is <emph>pointless</emph>.</c:error>
</c:errors>]]></programlisting>

<para>It is not an error for steps to generate non-standard error
output as long as it is well-formed.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="example-try" role="tocsuppress">
<title>Example</title>
<para>A pipeline might attempt to process a document by dispatching it
to some web service. If the web service succeeds, then those results
are passed to the rest of the pipeline. However, if the web service
cannot be contacted or reports an error, the <tag>p:catch</tag> step
can provide some sort of default for the rest of the pipeline.</para>

<example xml:id="ex.p.trycatch">
<title>An Example Try/Catch</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/trycatch.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
</example>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="p.atomic"><title>Atomic Steps</title><para>In addition to the six step types
        described in the preceding sections, XProc provides a standard library of atomic step types.
        The full vocabulary of standards steps is described in <biblioref linkend="std-components"
        />.</para>
<para>All of the standard, atomic steps are invoked in the same way:</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="OtherAtomicStep"/>
      <para>Where “<replaceable>p:atomic-step</replaceable>” <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be in the XProc
        namespace and <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be declared in either the standard library for the
        XProc version supported by the processor or explicitly imported by the surrounding pipeline
        (see <xref linkend="versioning-considerations"/>). </para></section>
    <section xml:id="p.extension"><title>Extension Steps</title><para>Pipeline authors may also have
        access to additional steps not defined or described by this specification. Atomic extension
        steps are invoked just like standard steps:</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="OtherAtomicStep"/>
      <para>Extension steps <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be in the XProc namespace and there
          <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <glossterm>visible</glossterm> step declaration at the point
        of use (see <xref linkend="scoping"/>).</para>
<para>If the relevant step declaration has no
          <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>, then that step invokes the declared atomic step, which
        the processor must know how to perform. These steps are implementation-defined extensions.
        </para>
<para>If the relevant step declaration has a <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>, then
        that step runs the declared subpipeline. These steps are user- or implementation-defined
        extensions. Pipelines can refer to themselves (recursion is allowed), to pipelines defined
        in imported libraries, and to other pipelines in the same library if they are in a
        library.</para>
<para><error code="S0010">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a
          pipeline contains a step whose specified inputs, outputs, and options do not <glossterm
            baseform="matches">match</glossterm> the <glossterm>signature</glossterm> for steps of
          that type.</error></para>
<para><error code="D0017">It is a <glossterm>dynamic
            error</glossterm> if the running pipeline attempts to invoke a step which the processor
          does not know how to perform.</error></para>
<para><impl>The presence of other <glossterm
            baseform="compound step">compound steps</glossterm> is
            <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>; XProc provides no standard mechanism for
          defining them or describing what they can contain.</impl>
        <error code="S0048">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to use a declared step as a
            <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>.</error></para>

<section xml:id="option-shortcut">
<title>Syntactic Shortcut for Option Values</title>

<para>Namespace qualified attributes on a step are <glossterm
baseform="extension attribute" >extension attributes</glossterm>.
Attributes, other than <tag class="attribute" >name</tag>, that are
not namespace qualified are treated as a syntactic shortcut for
specifying the value of an option. In other words, the following two
steps are equivalent:</para>

<para>The first step uses the standard <tag>p:with-option</tag>
syntax:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<ex:stepType>
  <p:with-option name="option-name" select="'some value'"/>
</ex:stepType>]]></programlisting>

<para>The second step uses the syntactic shortcut:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<ex:stepType option-name="some value"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>There are some limitations to this shortcut
syntax:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>It only applies to option names that are not in a
namespace.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>It only applies to option names that are not otherwise used on
the step, such as “<literal>name</literal>”.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>If the option value includes curly braces, it is treated as
an <glossterm>attribute value template</glossterm>. The context node for
attribute value templates in an option shortcut value comes from the
default readable port for the step on which they occur. If there is no
such port, the context node is undefined.</para>

<para><error code="S0027">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if an
option is specified with both the shortcut form and the long
form.</error>
<error code="S0031">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to use
an option on an <glossterm>atomic step</glossterm> that is not
declared on steps of that type.</error>
</para>

<para>The syntactic shortcuts apply equally to standard atomic steps
and extension atomic steps.</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="other-elements">
<title>Other pipeline elements</title>

<section xml:id="p.input">
<title>p:input</title>

<para>The declaration of an input identifies the name of the
port, whether or not the port accepts a sequence, whether or not the
port is a <glossterm>primary input port</glossterm>, what content types it
accepts, and may provide a
default connection for the port.</para>

<para>An input <emphasis>declaration</emphasis> has the following
form:</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Input"/>

<para>The attributes that can appear on <tag>p:input</tag> are
<link linkend="common-attr">the common attributes</link> and:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">port</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">port</tag> attribute defines the name
of the port. <error code="S0011">It is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> to identify two ports with the same name on the same
step.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">sequence</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute" >sequence</tag> attribute determines
whether or not a sequence of documents is allowed on the port.
<error code="D0006">If <tag class="attribute">sequence</tag> is not
specified, or has the value false, then it is a <glossterm>dynamic
error</glossterm> unless exactly one document appears on the declared
port.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">primary</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">primary</tag> attribute is used to
identify the <glossterm>primary input port</glossterm>. An input port
is a <glossterm>primary input port</glossterm> if
<tag class="attribute">primary</tag> is specified with the value
<literal>true</literal> or if the step has only a single input port
and <tag class="attribute">primary</tag> is not specified.
<error code="S0030">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to specify
that more than one input port is the primary.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">select</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>If a connection is provided in the declaration, then
<tag class="attribute">select</tag> may be used to select a portion of the
input identified by the <tag>p:empty</tag>, <tag>p:document</tag>,
or <tag>p:inline</tag> elements in the
<tag>p:input</tag>. This select expression <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XPath
expression.
The selected nodes are returned as separate documents.
If such a document consists exclusively of text nodes, then it has a content
type of <literal>text/plain</literal>, otherwise it has a content type
of <literal>application/xml</literal>.
</para>

<para>The
<tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression applies
<emphasis>only</emphasis> if the default connection is used. If an
explicit connection is provided by the caller, then the default select
expression is ignored.
<error code="D0039">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> is used and any input
document is not an XML document.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">content-types</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">content-types</tag> attribute lists one
or more (space separated) content types that this input port will
accept. A content type must be of the form
“<literal><replaceable>type</replaceable>/<replaceable>subtype</replaceable>+<replaceable>ext</replaceable></literal>”
where any of <replaceable>type</replaceable>,
<replaceable>subtype</replaceable>, and <replaceable>ext</replaceable>
can be specified as “<literal>*</literal>” meaning “any”. The
“<literal>+<replaceable>ext</replaceable></literal>” is optional. Here
are some examples of content types for matching:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><simpara><literal>text/plain</literal>, plain text
documents</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara><literal>text/*</literal>, any kind of text
document.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara><literal>*/*+xml</literal>, any XML content type.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara><literal>*/*</literal>, any content type.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The media type of input documents must
<link linkend="media-type-match">match</link> the allowed content types.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">href</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is a shortcut for a
<tag>p:document</tag> child element with the specified
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute. <error code="S0081">If
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:input</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> allows the pipeline
author to exclude some namespace declarations in inline content, see <tag>p:inline</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>On a <tag>p:declare-step</tag> for an atomic step, the
<tag>p:input</tag> simply declares the input port. <error
code="S0042">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to attempt to
provide a connection for an input port on the declaration of an atomic
step.</error></para>

<para xml:id="note-pipe-excl">The <tag>p:pipe</tag> element is explicitly excluded from a
declaration because it would make the default value of an input
dependent on the execution of some part of the pipeline. Default
values are designed so that they can be computed statically. For the very
same reason <tag class="attribute">href</tag> is neither an attribute value template
on <tag>p:input</tag> nor on a <tag>p:document</tag> within a <tag>p:input</tag>.</para>

</section>
<section xml:id="p.with-input">
<title>p:with-input</title>

<para>An input <emphasis>connection</emphasis> has the following
form:</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="WithInput"/>

<para>The attributes that can appear on <tag>p:with-input</tag> are
<link linkend="common-attr">the common attributes</link> and:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">port</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>If the <tag class="attribute">port</tag> is specified, then this
is a binding for the specified port. If no port is specified, then:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>In a <tag>p:viewport</tag> or <tag>p:for-each</tag>, it is a
binding for the step's single, anonymous input port.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In a <tag>p:choose</tag> or <tag>p:when</tag>, it is a
binding for the context item for the test expression(s).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Elsewhere, it is a binding for the primary input port of the
step in which it occurs.
<error code="S0065">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if there
is no primary input port.</error>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para><error code="S0086">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
to provide more than one p:with-input for the same port.</error>
</para>

<para>If no connection is provided for a <glossterm>primary input
port</glossterm>, the input will be connected to the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>. <error code="S0032">It
is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if no connection is provided
and the <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> is
undefined.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">select</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>A <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> also be provided with a connection.
The <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression, if specified, applies the
specified XPath select expression to the document(s) that are read.
<error code="D0039">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> is used and any input
document is not an XML document.</error></para>

<para>Each selected node is wrapped in a document (unless it is a document)
and provided to the input port. In other words,</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/input-doc.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>provides a single document, but</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/input-select.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>provides a sequence of zero or more documents, one for each
<code>html:div</code> in <uri>http://example.org/input.html</uri>.
(Note that in the case of nested <code>html:div</code> elements, this
will result in the same content being returned in several
documents.)</para>

<para>A select expression can equally be applied to input read from
another step. This input:</para><programlisting
language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/input-port.txt"
parse="text"/></programlisting><para>provides a sequence of zero or
more documents, one for each <code>html:div</code> in the document (or
each of the documents) that is read from the <literal>result</literal>
port of the step named <literal>origin</literal>.</para>

<para>The base URI of the document that results from a select
expression is the base URI of the matched element or document.</para>

<para>If a document constructed by selection consists exclusively of
text nodes, then it has a content type of
<literal>text/plain</literal>, otherwise it has a content type of
<literal>application/xml</literal>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">href</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is a shortcut for a
<tag>p:document</tag> child element with the specified
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute. <error code="S0081">If
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:with-input</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:with-input</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">pipe</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> attribute is a shortcut for one or
more <tag>p:pipe</tag> children. The attribute value <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
space-separated list of port@step pairs of the form
“<replaceable>port-name</replaceable>@<replaceable>step-name</replaceable>”.
If “port-name” is omitted, the connection is to the primary output port of
the step named “step-name”. If the “@step-name” is omitted, the connection is
to the specified port on the same step as the step associated with the
current default readable port. An empty or all whitespace attribute value is a shortcut
for the binding to the default readable port.</para>
<para><error code="S0082">If
<tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:with-input</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:with-input</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> allows the pipeline
author to exclude some namespace declarations in inline content, see <tag>p:inline</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>An input declaration may include a default connection. If no
connection is provided for an input port which has a default
connection, then the input is treated as if the default connection
appeared.</para>

<para>A <tag>p:with-input</tag> element with no children
(<foreignphrase>e.g.</foreignphrase>, “<code>&lt;p:with-input/&gt;</code>”)
is equivalent to an
input connection that contains only “<code>&lt;p:pipe/&gt;</code>”, which is
in turn equivalent to a binding to the default readable port.
</para>

<para>An input declaration may contain foreign element, scoped outside of XProc vocabulary
(<uri type="xmlnamespace">http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc</uri>) namespace. Each element is treated
as if wrapped with a <tag>p:inline</tag> element. For definition of this implicit behaviour
see <tag>p:inline</tag>.</para>

<para>A default connection does not satisfy the requirement that a
primary input port is automatically connected by the processor, nor is
it used when no default readable port is defined. In other words, a
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> can define
defaults for all of its inputs, whether they are primary or not, but
defining a default for a primary input usually has no effect. It's
never used by an atomic step since the step, when it's called, will
always connect the primary input port to the default readable port (or
cause a static error). The only case where it has value is on a
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> when that pipeline is invoked directly by the
processor. In that case, the processor <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> use the
default connection if no external connection is provided for the
port.</para>

</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="p.output">
<title>p:output</title>

<para>A <tag>p:output</tag> identifies an output port, optionally
connecting an input for it, if necessary.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="OutputDeclaration"/>

<para>The attributes that can appear on <tag>p:output</tag> are
<link linkend="common-attr">the common attributes</link> and:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">port</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">port</tag> attribute defines the name
of the port. <error code="S0011">It is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> to identify two ports with the same name on the same
step.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">sequence</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>An output declaration can indicate if a sequence of documents is
allowed to appear on the declared port. If <tag class="attribute"
>sequence</tag> is specified with the value <literal>true</literal>,
then a sequence is allowed. <error code="D0007">If <tag
class="attribute">sequence</tag> is not specified on
<tag>p:output</tag>, or has the value false, then it is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the step does not produce
exactly one document on the declared port.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">primary</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">primary</tag> attribute is used to
identify the primary output port. An output port is a primary output
port if <tag class="attribute">primary</tag> is specified with the
value <literal>true</literal> or if the step has only a single output
port and primary is not specified. <error code="S0014">It is a
<glossterm>static error</glossterm> to identify more than one output
port as primary.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">content-types</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>An output declaration can indicate the content types of the
  documents appearing on that port. If <tag class="attribute">content-types</tag>
  is specified then only documents matching these content types are allowed
  to appear on that port. If the attribute is not specified,
  <literal>*/*</literal> is assumed. <error code="D0042">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
  if a document arrives on an output port whose content type is not accepted
  by the output port specification.</error></para>

<note role="editorial">
<title>Editorial Note</title>
<para>Implementations are free to perform a static checking of the
connected ports and indicate, that the content types of the connected
ports will not match, however they <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> raise a
static error.
</para>
</note>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">serialization</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">serialization</tag> attribute can
be used to provide <link linkend="serialization">serialization
parameters</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>On <glossterm baseform="compound step">compound
steps</glossterm>, the declaration <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> be
accompanied by a <glossterm>connection</glossterm> for the
output.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="OutputConnection"/>

<para>The additional attributes that can appear on an output connection
are:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">href</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is a shortcut for a
<tag>p:document</tag> child element with the specified
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute. <error code="S0081">If
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:output</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:output</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">pipe</tag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>The <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> attribute is a shortcut for one or
    more <tag>p:pipe</tag> children. The attribute value <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
    space-separated list of port@step pairs of the form
    “<replaceable>port-name</replaceable>@<replaceable>step-name</replaceable>”.
    If “port-name” is omitted, the connection is to the primary output port of
    the step named “step-name”. If the “@step-name” is omitted, the connection is
    to the specified port on the same step as the step associated with the
    current default readable port. An empty or all whitespace attribute value is a shortcut
    for the binding to the default readable port.</para>
<para><error code="S0082">If
<tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:output</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:output</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> allows the pipeline
author to exclude some namespace declarations in inline content, see <tag>p:inline</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para><error code="S0029">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
to specify a connection for a <tag>p:output</tag> inside a
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> for an atomic step.</error></para>

<para>If a connection is provided for a <tag>p:output</tag>, documents
are <emphasis>read from</emphasis> that connection and those documents
form the output that <emphasis>is written</emphasis> to the output
port. In other words, placing a <tag>p:document</tag> inside a
<tag>p:output</tag> causes the processor to <emphasis>read that
document</emphasis> and provide it on the output port. It
<emphasis>does not</emphasis> cause the processor to
<emphasis>write</emphasis> the output to that document.</para>

<section xml:id="serialization">
<title>Serialization parameters</title>

<!-- This ID exists so that old links to the p.serialization section
     will come here. Not that it will matter, but that's why.
-->
<para xml:id="p.serialization">The <tag class="attribute">serialization</tag>
attribute allows the user to request serialization parameters on an
output port. These parameters control XML serialization as defined
by <biblioref linkend="xpath-serialization"/>.
The attribute value is an XPath expression which returns
a map from strings to atomic values.</para>

<para>If the pipeline processor serializes the output on a port, it
<rfc2119 feature="ser-must-use">must</rfc2119> use the serialization
parameters specified. If the processor is not serializing (if, for
example, the pipeline has been called from another pipeline), then the
<tag class="attribute">serialization</tag>
<rfc2119 feature="ser-must-ignore">must</rfc2119> be
ignored.</para>

<para><impl>The default value of any serialization parameters not
specified on a particular output is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
<error code="D0020">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the combination of serialization options specified or defaulted is not
allowed.</error> Implementations <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> check that
all of the specified serialization options are allowed if they
serialize the specified output. If the specified output is not being
serialized implementations
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> but are not required to check that the
specified options are allowed.</para>

<para>For XML outputs, see <xref linkend="xml-serialization"/>.
For non-XML outputs, see <xref linkend="non-xml-serialization"/>.
<error code="D0041">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the
map contains any property name not recognized as a serialization
parameter.</error></para>

<section xml:id="xproc-serialization">
<title>XML serialization</title>

<para>The names and values of XML serialization parameters are defined
by <biblioref linkend="xml-serialization"/>.</para>

<para>The following parameters may be present in the serialization
map:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><option>byte-order-mark</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a boolean.
If it's not specified, the default varies by encoding: for UTF-16 it's
true, for all others, it's false.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>cdata-section-elements</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a list of
<type>EQName</type>s. They are interpreted as element names.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>doctype-public</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a string.
The public identifier of the doctype.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>doctype-system</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an
<type>anyURI</type>. The system identifier of the doctype. It need not
be absolute, and is not resolved.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>encoding</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>A character set name. <impl>If no <option>encoding</option> is
specified, the encoding used is <glossterm>implementation
defined</glossterm>. If the <option>method</option> is
“<literal>xml</literal>” or “<literal>xhtml</literal>”, the
implementation defined encoding <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be either
UTF-8 or UTF-16.</impl></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>escape-uri-attributes</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
boolean. It is ignored unless the specified method is
“<literal>xhtml</literal>” or “<literal>html</literal>”.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>include-content-type</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a boolean.
It is ignored unless the specified method is
“<literal>xhtml</literal>” or “<literal>html</literal>”.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>indent</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
boolean.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>media-type</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a string. It
specifies the media type (MIME content type). If not specified, the
default varies according to the <option>method</option>:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>xml</literal></term>
<listitem><simpara><literal>application/xml</literal></simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>html</literal></term>
<listitem><simpara><literal>text/html</literal></simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>xhtml</literal></term>
<listitem><simpara><literal>application/xhtml+xml</literal></simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>text</literal></term>
<listitem><simpara><literal>text/plain</literal></simpara></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para><impl>For methods other than <literal>xml</literal>, <literal>html</literal>,
<literal>xhtml</literal>, and <literal>text</literal>; the
<option>media-type</option> is <glossterm>implementation defined</glossterm>.
</impl></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>method</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an
<type>EQName</type>. It specifies the serialization method.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>normalization-form</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an NMTOKEN,
one of the enumerated values <code>NFC</code>, <code>NFD</code>,
<code>NFKC</code>, <code>NFKD</code>, <code>fully-normalized</code>,
<code>none</code> or an implementation-defined value.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>omit-xml-declaration</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
boolean.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>standalone</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an NMTOKEN,
one of the enumerated values <code>true</code>, <code>false</code>, or
<code>omit</code>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>undeclare-prefixes</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
boolean.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>use-character-maps</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a list of
<type>EQName</type>s. For each name provided, there must be a matching
<tag>p:character-map</tag> with that name.
<error code="D0100">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
<option>use-character-maps</option> includes a name for which there
is not a corresponding <tag>p:character-map</tag>.</error>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><option>version</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>The value of this option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a
string.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>In order to be consistent with the rest of this specification,
boolean values for the serialization parameters must use one of the
XML Schema lexical forms for boolean: "true", "false", "1", or "0".
This is different from the <biblioref linkend="xml-serialization"/>
specification which uses “yes” and “no”. No change in
semantics is implied by this different spelling.</para>

<para>The <option>method</option> option controls the serialization
method used by this component with standard values of 'html', 'xml',
'xhtml', and 'text' but only the 'xml' value is required to be
supported. The interpretation of the remaining options is as
specified in <biblioref linkend="xml-serialization"/>.</para>

<para><impl>Implementations may support other method values but their
results are <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
</para>

<para>A minimally conforming implementation must support the
<code>xml</code> output method with the following option
values:</para>

<itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>The <code>version</code> must support the value <code>1.0</code>.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>The <code>encoding</code> must support the values <code>UTF-8</code>.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>The <code>omit-xml-declaration</code> must be supported.  If the value is not specified or has the value <code>no</code>, an XML declaration must be produced.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>All other option values may be ignored for the <code>xml</code>
output method.</para>

<para>If a processor chooses to implement an option for serialization,
it must conform to the semantics defined in the <biblioref
linkend="xml-serialization"/> specification.</para>

<note xml:id="note-use-char-maps">
<para>The use-character-maps parameter in
<biblioref linkend="xml-serialization"/> specification has not been provided in
the standard serialization options provided by this
specification.</para>
</note>

</section>
<section xml:id="non-xml-serialization">
<title>Non-XML serialization</title>

<para><impl>The names and values of non-XML serialization parameters are
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>
</section>

</section>
</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="variables-options">
<title>Variables and Options</title>

<para>Variables and options provide a mechanism for pipeline authors
to construct temporary results and hold onto them for reuse.</para>

<para>Variables are created in compound steps and, like XSLT
variables, are single assignment, though they may be shadowed by
subsequent declarations of other variables with the same name.</para>

<para>Options can be declared on atomic or compound steps. The value
of an option can be specified by the caller invoking the step. Any
value specified by the caller takes precedence over any default value
specified in the declaration.</para>

<section xml:id="p.variable">
<title>p:variable</title>

<para>A <tag>p:variable</tag> declares a variable and associates a
value with it. Variable declarations may optionally specify the type
of the variable using an
XPath Sequence Type<superscript>[citation needed]</superscript>.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="VariableSelect"/>

<para>The attributes that can appear on <tag>p:variable</tag> are
<link linkend="common-attr">the common attributes</link> and:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">name</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The name of the variable <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an EQName. If
it does not contain a prefix then it is in no namespace. <error
code="S0028">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to declare an
option or variable in the XProc namespace.</error> <error code="S0087">It is
a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the name attribute on
<tag>p:option</tag> or <tag>p:variable</tag> has a prefix which is not
bound to a namespace.</error>
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">as</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The type of the value may be specified in the <tag
class="attribute">as</tag> attribute using an XPath Sequence
Type<superscript>[citation needed]</superscript>. If an atomic type,
or sequence of atomic types, is specified, the value provided for the
option will be atomized according to the standard XPath rules.
<error code="D0049">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the sequence type is not syntactically valid.</error>
<error code="D0036">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the computed value does not match the specified sequence
type.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">select</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The variable's value is specified with a <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> attribute. The <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> attribute <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
specified. The content of the <tag class="attribute">select</tag>
attribute is an XPath expression which will be evaluated to provide
the value of the variable.</para>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression
is evaluated as an XPath expression using the appropriate context as
described in <xref linkend="xpath-context"/>, for the enclosing
<glossterm>container</glossterm>.
<impl>The precise details about what XPath expressions are allowed
(for example, can the expression declare a function) is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
</para>
<para>Since all <glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> are present
in the Processor XPath Context as variable bindings, <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> expressions may refer to the value of
<glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> by variable reference. If a
variable reference uses an QName that is not the name of an <glossterm
baseform="in-scope bindings">in-scope binding</glossterm>, an XPath
evaluation error will occur.</para>

<para>If a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression is given,
the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm> available for document
connections are computed as if <tag>p:variable</tag> was an atomic step.</para>

<para>If a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression is given but
no document connection is provided, the implicit connection is to the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm> computed as if <tag>p:variable</tag>
was an atomic step. If there is no default readable port, the
connection is treated as if <tag>p:empty</tag> was specified.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">collection</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0008">If <tag class="attribute">collection</tag> is
unspecified or has the value <literal>false</literal>,
it is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if a sequence of more than one document appears on the connection for
a <tag>p:variable</tag>.</error>
</para>

<para>If <tag class="attribute">collection</tag> is <literal>true</literal>,
the context item is undefined. All of the documents that appear on the
connection for the <tag>p:variable</tag> will be available as the
default collection within <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression.</para>

<para><error code="D0026">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression makes reference to
the context node, size, or position when the context item is
undefined.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">href</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is a shortcut for a
<tag>p:document</tag> child element with the specified
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute. <error code="S0081">If
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:variable</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:variable</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">pipe</tag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>The <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> attribute is a shortcut for one or
    more <tag>p:pipe</tag> children. The attribute value <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
    space-separated list of port@step pairs of the form
    “<replaceable>port-name</replaceable>@<replaceable>step-name</replaceable>”.
    If “port-name” is omitted, the connection is to the primary output port of
    the step named “step-name”. If the “@step-name” is omitted, the connection is
    to the specified port on the same step as the step associated with the
    current default readable port. An empty or all whitespace attribute value is a shortcut
    for the binding to the default readable port.</para>
<para><error code="S0082">If
<tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:variable</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:variable</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> allows the pipeline
author to exclude some namespace declarations in inline content, see <tag>p:inline</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Steps are connected together by their input and output
ports. Variables are connected to steps by their input, which provides
the context node for the expression, and by the expressions that contain
references to them. Any step which contains a reference to a variable
effectively consumes the “output” of the variable.
<error code="S0076">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if
there are any loops in the connections between steps and variables:
no step can refer to a variable if there is any sequence of connections
from that step that leads back to the input that provides the context
node for the expression that defines the value of the variable.</error>
</para>
</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="p.option">
<title>p:option</title>

<para>A <tag>p:option</tag> declares an option and may associate a
default value with it. The <tag>p:option</tag> tag can only be used in
a <tag>p:declare-step</tag>.</para>

<para>The name of the option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an EQName. If it
does not contain a prefix then it is in no namespace. <error
code="S0028">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to declare an
option or variable in the XProc namespace.</error></para>

<para><error code="S0087">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if the name attribute on <tag>p:option</tag> or <tag>p:variable</tag>
has a prefix which is not bound to a namespace.</error></para>

<para><error code="S0004">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
to declare two or more options on the same step with the same
name.</error></para>

<e:rng-pattern name="OptionDeclaration"/>

<para>An option may declare its type. The type is specified in the
<tag class="attribute">as</tag> attribute using an XPath Sequence
Type<superscript>[citation needed]</superscript>. If an atomic type,
or sequence of atomic types, is specified, the value provided for the
option will be atomized according to the standard XPath rules.
<error code="D0049">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the sequence type is not syntactically valid.</error>
<error code="D0036">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the computed value does not match the specified sequence
type.</error></para>

<para>An option may declare that it is required by specifying
the value <literal>true</literal> for the
<tag class="attribute">required</tag> attribute. <error code="S0018">If an
option is required, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to
invoke the step without specifying a value for that
option.</error> Options are only required if they are specifically
declared to be so; in other words, the default value for the
<tag class="attribute">required</tag> attribute is <code>false</code>.
</para>

<para>If an option is not declared to be required, it
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> be given a default value. The value is
specified with a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> attribute.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="OptionSelect"/>

<para>If a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> attribute is specified,
its content is an XPath expression which will be evaluated to provide
the value of the option, which may differ from one instance of the
step type to another.</para>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression is only
evaluated when its actual value is needed by an instance of the step
type being declared. In this case, it is evaluated as described in
<xref linkend="p.with-option"/> except that</para>

<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The
              context item is undefined.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the variable bindings consist only of bindings for options whose declaration
              precedes the <tag>p:option</tag> itself in the surrounding step
                <glossterm>signature</glossterm>;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the in-scope namespaces are the in-scope namespaces of the <tag>p:option</tag>
              itself.</para>
          </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><error code="S0017">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
to specify that an option is both <tag
class="attribute">required</tag> <emphasis>and</emphasis> has a
default value.</error></para>

<para><error code="D0026">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression makes reference to
the context node, size, or position.</error></para>

</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="p.with-option">
<title>p:with-option</title>

<para>A <tag>p:with-option</tag> provides an actual value for an
option when a step is invoked.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="WithOptionSelect"/>

<para>The attributes that can appear on <tag>p:with-option</tag> are
<link linkend="common-attr">the common attributes</link> and:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">name</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The name of the option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a EQName. If it
does not contain a prefix then it is in no namespace.
<error code="S0031">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to use an
option name in <tag>p:with-option</tag> if the step type being invoked
has not declared an option with that name.</error>
(This error does not apply for steps in the XProc namespace when the processor
is operating in
<link linkend="vers-forwcomp">forwards-compatible mode</link>.)</para>

<para><error code="S0080">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
to include more than one <tag>p:with-option</tag> with the same option
name as part of the same step invocation.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">as</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The type of the value may be specified in the <tag
class="attribute">as</tag> attribute using an XPath Sequence
Type<superscript>[citation needed]</superscript>. If an atomic type,
or sequence of atomic types, is specified, the value provided for the
option will be atomized according to the standard XPath rules.
<error code="D0049">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the sequence type is not syntactically valid.</error>
<error code="D0036">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the computed value does not match the specified sequence
type.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">select</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The actual value is specified with a <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> attribute. The <tag
class="attribute">select</tag> attribute <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
specified. The value of the <tag class="attribute">select</tag>
attribute is an XPath expression which will be evaluated to provide
the value of the variable.</para>

<para>All <glossterm>in-scope bindings</glossterm> for the step
instance itself are present in the Processor XPath Context as variable
bindings, so <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expressions may refer
to any option or variable bound in those <glossterm>in-scope
bindings</glossterm> by variable reference. If a variable reference
uses a QName that is not the name of an <glossterm
baseform="in-scope-bindings">in-scope binding</glossterm> or preceding
sibling option, an XPath evaluation error will occur.</para>

<para>If a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression is used but
no document connection is provided, the implicit connection is to the
<glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>. If there is no default
readable port, the connection is treated as if <tag>p:empty</tag> was
specified.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">collection</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para><error code="D0008">If <tag class="attribute">collection</tag> is
unspecified or has the value <literal>false</literal>,
it is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if a sequence of more than one document appears on the connection for
the <tag>p:with-option</tag>.</error>
</para>

<para>If <tag class="attribute">collection</tag> is <literal>true</literal>,
the context item is undefined. All of the documents that appear on the
connection for the <tag>p:with-option</tag> will be available as the
default collection within <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression.</para>

<para><error code="D0026">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression makes reference to
the context node, size, or position when the context item is
undefined.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">href</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute is a shortcut for a
<tag>p:document</tag> child element with the specified
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute. <error code="S0081">If
<tag class="attribute">href</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:with-option</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:with-option</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">pipe</tag></term>
<listitem>
  <para>The <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> attribute is a shortcut for one or
    more <tag>p:pipe</tag> children. The attribute value <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
    space-separated list of port@step pairs of the form
    “<replaceable>port-name</replaceable>@<replaceable>step-name</replaceable>”.
    If “port-name” is omitted, the connection is to the primary output port of
    the step named “step-name”. If the “@step-name” is omitted, the connection is
    to the specified port on the same step as the step associated with the
    current default readable port. An empty or all whitespace attribute value is a shortcut
    for the binding to the default readable port.</para>
<para><error code="S0082">If
<tag class="attribute">pipe</tag> is specified, it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if <tag>p:with-option</tag> has any child elements other than <tag>p:documentation</tag> and
<tag>p:pipeinfo</tag>.</error></para>
<para><error code="S0085">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if a <tag>p:with-option</tag>
has a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute and a <tag class="attribute">pipe</tag>
attribute.</error></para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag></term>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> allows the pipeline
author to exclude some namespace declarations in inline content, see <tag>p:inline</tag>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="opt-bindings"><title>Namespaces on variables and options</title>

<para>Variable and option values carry with them not only
their literal or computed string value but also a set of namespaces.
To see why this is necessary, consider the following
step:</para><programlisting language="xml"><xi:include
href="../../../build/examples/opns-1.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting><para>The
<tag>p:delete</tag> step will delete elements that match the
expression “<literal>html:div</literal>”, but that expression can only
be correctly interpreted if there's a namespace binding for the prefix
“<literal>html</literal>” so that binding has to travel with the
option.</para>

<para>The default namespace bindings associated with a variable or
option value are computed as follows:</para><orderedlist>

<listitem>
<para>If the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> attribute was used to
specify the value and it consisted of a single
<literal>VariableReference</literal> (per <biblioref
linkend="xpath31"/>), then the namespace bindings from the referenced
option or variable are used.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If the <tag class="attribute">select</tag> attribute was used to specify the value
              and it evaluated to a node-set, then the in-scope namespaces from the first node in
              the selected node-set (or, if it's not an element, its parent) are used.</para>
            <para>The expression is evaluated in the appropriate context, See <xref
                linkend="xpath-context"/>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Otherwise, the in-scope namespaces from the element providing the value are used.
              (For options specified using <link linkend="option-shortcut">syntactic
                shortcuts</link>, the step element itself is providing the value.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist><para>The default namespace is never included in the namespace bindings for a
          variable or option value. Unqualified names are always in
          no-namespace.</para>
<para>Unfortunately, in more complex situations, there may be no
          single variable or option that can reliably be expected to have the correct set
          of namespace bindings. Consider this
          pipeline:</para><programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/opns-2.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting><para>It
          defines an atomic step (“<literal>ex:delete-in-div</literal>”) that deletes elements that
          occur inside of XHTML div elements. It might be used as
          follows:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/opns-3.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>In this case, the <varname>match</varname> option passed to the
<tag>p:delete</tag> step needs <emphasis>both</emphasis> the namespace
binding of “<literal>h</literal>” specified in the
<tag>ex:delete-in-div</tag> pipeline definition
<emphasis>and</emphasis> the namespace binding of
“<literal>html</literal>” specified in the <varname>divchild</varname>
option on the call of that pipeline. It's not sufficient to provide
just one of the sets of bindings.</para>

<para>If pipeline authors cannot arrange for all of the necessary namespace
bindings to be in scope, then EQNames can be used to remove the dependency
on namespace bindings:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/opns-4.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>In this example, the expression will match “<literal>p</literal>”
elements in the XHTML namespace irrespective of any bindings that may or may
not be in scope.</para>

</section>
    </section>
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="p.declare-step">
<title>p:declare-step</title>

<para>A <tag>p:declare-step</tag> provides the type and
<glossterm>signature</glossterm> of an <glossterm>atomic
step</glossterm> or pipeline. It declares the inputs, outputs, and
options for all steps of that type.</para>

      <e:rng-pattern name="DeclareStep"/>

<para>The value of the <tag class="attribute">type</tag> can be from
any namespace provided that the expanded-QName of the value has a
non-null namespace URI. <error code="S0025">It is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> if the expanded-QName value of the <tag
class="attribute">type</tag> attribute is in no namespace or in the
XProc namespace.</error> Except as described in <xref
linkend="versioning-considerations"/>, the XProc namespace
<rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be used in the type of steps. Neither
users nor implementers may define additional steps in the XProc
namespace.</para>

<para>Irrespective of the context in which the
<tag>p:declare-step</tag> occurs, there are initially no option or
variable names in-scope inside a <tag>p:declare-step</tag>. That is,
<tag>p:option</tag> and <tag>p:variable</tag> elements can refer to
values declared by their preceding siblings, but not by any of their
ancestors.</para>

<para><impl>When a declared step is evaluated directly by the XProc
processor (as opposed to occurring as an atomic step in some
<glossterm>container</glossterm>), how the input and output ports are
connected to documents is
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl></para>

<para>A step declaration is not a <link
linkend="step-concept">step</link> in its own right. Sibling steps
cannot refer to the inputs or outputs of a <tag>p:declare-step</tag>
using <tag>p:pipe</tag>; only instances of the type can be
referenced.</para>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute identifies the version
of XProc for which this step declaration was authored. If the
<tag>p:declare-step</tag>
has no ancestors in the XProc namespace, then it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
have a <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute.
See <xref linkend="versioning-considerations"/>.</para>

<para>If the <tag>p:declare-step</tag> is a child of a <tag>p:library</tag> the
<tag class="attribute">visibility</tag> attribute controls whether the step is
visible to an importing pipeline. If <tag class="attribute">visibility</tag> is set to
<literal>private</literal>, the step type is only visible inside the <tag>p:library</tag>
but not visible to any pipeline importing the <tag>p:library</tag>. If the
<tag class="attribute">visibility</tag> attribute is missing, <literal>public</literal>
is assumed. If the <tag>p:declare-step</tag> is not a child of a <tag>p:library</tag> the
attribute is ignored.</para>

<para>For a description of <tag class="attribute">psvi-required</tag>,
see <xref linkend="psvi-support" />. For <tag
class="attribute">xpath-version</tag>, see <xref
linkend="xpath-context"/>. For <tag
class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag>, see
<tag>p:inline</tag>.</para>

<section xml:id="declare-atomic-steps">
        <title>Declaring atomic steps</title>
        <para>When declaring an atomic step, the subpipeline in the declaration
            <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be empty. And, conversely, if the subpipeline in a declaration
          is empty, the declaration <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be for an atomic step.</para>
        <para><impl>Implementations may use <glossterm baseform="extension
attribute">extension
              attributes</glossterm> to provide <glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>
            information about a declared step.</impl> For example, such an attribute might identify
          the code which implements steps of this type.</para>
        <para>It is not an error for a pipeline to include declarations for steps that a particular
          processor does not know how to implement. It is, of course, an error to attempt to
          evaluate such steps.</para>
      </section><section xml:id="declare-pipelines">
        <title>Declaring pipelines</title>
        <para>When a <tag>p:declare-step</tag> declares a pipeline, that pipeline encapsulates the
          behavior of the specified <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. Its children declare inputs,
          outputs, and options that the pipeline exposes and identify the steps in its subpipeline. </para>
        <para><impl>The subpipeline may include declarations of additional steps (e.g., other
            pipelines or other step types that are provided by a particular implementation or in
            some <glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm> way) and import other
            pipelines.</impl> If a pipeline has been imported, it may be invoked as a step within
          the subpipeline that imported it.</para>
        <para>The environment inherited by the <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm> is the
            <glossterm>empty environment</glossterm> with these modifications:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>All of the declared inputs are added to the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>
              in the environment.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If a <glossterm>primary input port</glossterm> is declared, that port is the
                <glossterm>default readable port</glossterm>, otherwise the default readable port is
              undefined.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If a <glossterm>primary output port</glossterm> is declared and that port has no
            <glossterm>connection</glossterm>, then it is connected to the <glossterm>primary output
            port</glossterm> of the <glossterm>last step</glossterm> in the
            <glossterm>subpipeline</glossterm>. <error code="S0006">It is a <glossterm>static
              error</glossterm> if the primary output port is unconnected and the <glossterm>last
              step</glossterm> in the subpipeline does not have a primary output
          port.</error></para>
        <para>The requested <tag class="attribute">xpath-version</tag>
          <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be used to evaluate XPath expressions subject to the constraints
          outlined in <xref linkend="xpath-context"/>.</para>
        <para>The <tag class="attribute">psvi-required</tag> attribute allows the author to declare
          that a step relies on the processor's ability to pass PSVI annotations between steps, see
            <xref linkend="psvi-support"/>. If the attribute is not specified, the value
            “<literal>false</literal>” is assumed. </para>
      </section></section>
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

<section xml:id="p.library"><title>p:library</title><para>A <tag>p:library</tag> is a collection
        of step declarations and/or pipeline definitions.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="Library"/>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute identifies the version
of XProc for which this library was authored. If the
<tag>p:library</tag>
has no ancestors in the XProc namespace, then it <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>
have a <tag class="attribute">version</tag> attribute.
See <xref linkend="versioning-considerations"/>.</para>

      <para>For a description of <tag class="attribute">psvi-required</tag>, see <xref
          linkend="psvi-support"/>; for <tag class="attribute">xpath-version</tag>, see <xref
          linkend="xpath-context"/>; for <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag>, see
          <tag>p:inline</tag>.</para>

<note xml:id="note-step-decl">
        <para>The steps declared in a pipeline library are referred to by their type. It is not an
          error to put a <tag>p:declare-step</tag> without a <tag
            class="attribute">type</tag> in a <tag>p:library</tag>, but there is no standard
          mechanism for instantiating it or referring to it. It is effectively invisible.</para>
      </note><para>Libraries can import pipelines and/or other libraries.
See also <xref linkend="handling-imports"
      />.</para></section>
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section xml:id="p.import"><title>p:import</title><para>An <tag>p:import</tag> loads a pipeline
        or pipeline library, making it available in the pipeline or library which contains the
          <tag>p:import</tag>.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="Import"/>
      <para>An import statement loads the specified IRI and makes any pipelines declared within it
        available to the current pipeline. </para>
<para><error code="S0052">It is a
            <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the URI of a <tag>p:import</tag> cannot be
          retrieved or if, once retrieved, it does not point to a <tag>p:library</tag> or
            <tag>p:declare-step</tag>.</error>
        <error code="S0053">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> to import a single pipeline
          if that pipeline does not have a <tag class="attribute">type</tag>.</error>
      </para>
<para>Attempts to retrieve the library identified by the URI value may be redirected at
        the parser level (for example, in an entity resolver) or below (at the protocol level, for
        example, via an HTTP Location: header). In the absence of additional information outside the
        scope of this specification within the resource, the base URI of the library is always the
        URI of the actual resource returned. In other words, it is the URI of the resource retrieved
        after all redirection has occurred.</para>
<para>As imports are processed, a processor may
        encounter new <tag>p:import</tag> elements whose library URI is the same as one it has
        already processed in some other context. This may happen as a consequence of resolving the
        URI. If the actual base URI is the same as one that has already been processed, the
        implementation must recognize it as the same library and should not need to process the
        resource. Also, a duplicate, circular chain of imports, or a re-entrant import is not an
        error and implementations must take the necessary steps to avoid infinite loops and/or
        incorrect notification of duplicate step definitions. It is not an error for a library to
        import itself. An example of such steps is listed in <xref linkend="handling-imports"
        />.</para>
<para>A library is considered the same library if the URI of the resource
        retrieved is the same. If a pipeline or library author uses two different URI values that
        resolve to the same resource, they must not be considered the same imported
        library.</para>

</section>

<!-- ============================================================ -->
<section xml:id="p.pipe">
<title>p:pipe</title>

<para>A <tag>p:pipe</tag> connects an input to a port on another
step.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Pipe"/>

<para>The <tag>p:pipe</tag> element connects to a readable port of
another step. It identifies the readable port to which it connects
with the name of the step in the <tag class="attribute">step</tag>
attribute and the name of the port on that step in the
<tag class="attribute">port</tag> attribute.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">step</tag> attribute is not specified,
it defaults to the step which provides the default readable port.
If the <tag class="attribute">port</tag> attribute is not specified,
it defaults to the primary output port of the step identified (explicitly
or implicitly).</para>

<para>
<error code="S0067">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
<tag class="attribute">step</tag> attribute is not specified, and there
is no default readable port.
<error code="S0068">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
<tag class="attribute">port</tag> attribute is not specified, and the
step identified has no primary output port.</error>
</error></para>

<para><error code="S0022">In all cases except when the
<tag>p:pipe</tag> is within an <tag>p:output</tag> of a
<glossterm>compound step</glossterm>, it is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> if the port identified by the <tag>p:pipe</tag> is not
in the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm> of the step that contains
the <tag>p:pipe</tag>.</error></para>

<para>A <tag>p:pipe</tag> that is a <glossterm>connection</glossterm>
for an <tag>p:output</tag> of a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>
may connect to one of the readable ports of the compound step or to an
output port on one of the compound step's <glossterm>contained
steps</glossterm>. In other words, the output of a compound step can
simply be a copy of one of the available inputs or it can be the
output of one of its children.</para>

<para><error code="S0078">When the <tag>p:pipe</tag> is within an
<tag>p:output</tag> of a <glossterm>compound step</glossterm>, it is a
<glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the port identified by the
<tag>p:pipe</tag> is not in the <glossterm>readable ports</glossterm>
of the compound step and is not a readable port of a contained
step.</error>
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="p.inline">
<title>p:inline</title>

<para>A <tag>p:inline</tag> provides a document inline.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Inline"/>

<para>The <tag class="attribute">document-properties</tag> attribute
can be used to set the <glossterm>document properties</glossterm> of
the provided document. The document's content type is determined by
the value of the "content-type" key in the provided map. If no
attribute <tag class="attribute">document-properties</tag> is provided
or the provided map does not contain a "content-type" key, the value
"<literal>application/xml</literal>" is assumed.
</para>

<para>How the content of a <tag>p:inline</tag> element is interpreted
depends on the document's content type and the <tag
class="attribute">encoding</tag> attribute.
</para>

<!--
<informaltable>
<thead>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><tag class="attribute">content-type</tag></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><glossterm>XML media type</glossterm></td>
<td><glossterm>text media type</glossterm></td>
<td>Other media types</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<th align="left"><tag class="attribute">encoding</tag> absent</th>
<td>OK</td>
<td>OK</td>
<td>error</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"><tag class="attribute">encoding</tag>
is “<literal>base64</literal>”.</th>
<td>error</td>
<td>OK</td>
<td>OK</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"><tag class="attribute">encoding</tag> is something else.</th>
<td>error</td>
<td>implementation-defined</td>
<td>implementation-defined</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</informaltable>
-->

<para><error code="S0070">It is a
<glossterm>static error</glossterm> if an encoding is specified
and the content type is an <glossterm>XML media type</glossterm>.</error>
</para>

<para><error code="S0071">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if the content type value specifies a character set and the <tag
class="attribute">encoding</tag> attribute is absent.</error>
</para>

<para><error code="S0072">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if an encoding is specified and the content of the <tag>p:inline</tag>
contains any XML markup.</error> In other words, the entire content
must be a single text node. CDATA sections and character references do
not count as markup for this purpose because they will already have
been replaced by the XML parser that read the pipeline.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">encoding</tag> attribute is
present, the content must be decoded. The encoding value
“<literal>base64</literal>” <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be supported and
identifies the content as being base64-encoded.
<impl>An implementation may
support encodings other than <literal>base64</literal>, but these
encodings and their names are
<glossterm>implementation-defined</glossterm>.</impl>
<error code="S0069">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
encoding specified is not supported by the implementation.</error>
<error code="D0040">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if
the body is not correctly encoded per the value of the <tag
class="attribute">encoding</tag> attribute.</error>
</para>

<para>The interpretation of the (possibily decoded) content
depends on the document's content type.
</para>

<section xml:id="inline-non-xml">
<title>Inline non-XML content</title>

<para>If the document's content type is not
an <glossterm>XML media type</glossterm>, then the content is
non-XML.</para>

<para><impl>The representation of non-XML content is
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm></impl>.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="inline-xml-content">
<title>Inline XML content</title>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">document-properties</tag> is not
specified or the map does not contain a key "content-type" or specifies
an <glossterm>XML media type</glossterm>, then
the content is XML. <error code="S0024">It is a <glossterm>static
error</glossterm> if the content of the <tag>p:inline</tag> element
does not consist of exactly one element, optionally preceded and/or
followed by any number of processing instructions, comments or
whitespace characters.</error></para>

<para>The in-scope namespaces of the inline document differ from the
in-scope namespace of the content of the <tag>p:inline</tag> element
in that bindings for all its <emphasis>excluded namespaces</emphasis>,
as defined below, are removed:</para>

<itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                      <para>The XProc namespace itself (<uri>http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc</uri>) is
                          excluded.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                      <para>A namespace URI designated by using an <tag class="attribute"
                          >exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attribute on the enclosing <tag>p:inline</tag> is
                          excluded.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                      <para>A namespace URI designated by using an <tag class="attribute"
                          >exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attribute on any ancestor <tag>p:declare-step</tag> or <tag>p:library</tag> is also excluded. (In other words, the
                          effect of several <tag class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attributes among
                          the ancestors of <tag>p:inline</tag> is cumulative.)</para>
                  </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

          <para>The value of each prefix in the <tag
              class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attribute is
              interpreted as follows:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                  <para>The value of the attribute is either <literal>#all</literal>, or
                      a whitespace-separated list of tokens, each of which is either a
                      namespace prefix or <literal>#default</literal>. The namespace bound
                      to each of the prefixes is designated as an excluded namespace. <error
                          code="S0057">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the <tag
                              class="attribute" >exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attribute does not
                          contain a list of tokens or if any of those tokens (except
                          <literal>#all</literal> or <literal>#default</literal>) is not a
                          prefix bound to a namespace in the in-scope namespaces of the element
                          on which it occurs.</error></para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                  <para>The default namespace of the element on which <tag
                      class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> occurs may be
                      designated as an excluded namespace by including
                      <literal>#default</literal> in the list of namespace prefixes. <error
                          code="S0058">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the value
                          <literal>#default</literal> is used within the <tag class="attribute"
                              >exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> attribute and there is no default
                          namespace in scope.</error>
                  </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                  <para>The value <literal>#all</literal> indicates that all namespaces
                      that are in scope for the element on which <tag
                          class="attribute">exclude-inline-prefixes</tag> occurs are designated
                      as excluded namespaces.</para>
              </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The XProc processor <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> include all in-scope
              prefixes that are not explicitly excluded. If the namespace associated with
              an excluded prefix is used in the expanded-QName of a descendant
              element or attribute,
              the processor <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> include that prefix anyway, or it may
              generate a new prefix.</para>

          <para>Consider this example:</para>

          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../../../build/examples/exclude-pfx.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>

          <para>which might produce a result like this:</para>

          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<doc xmlns:c="http://example.com/c">
   <b:part xmlns:b="http://example.com/b"/>
 </doc>]]></programlisting>

          <para>The declaration for “<literal>c</literal>” must
              be present because it was not excluded. The “<literal>part</literal>” element
              uses the namespace bound to “<literal>b</literal>”, so <emphasis>some</emphasis>
              binding must be present. In this example, the original
              prefix has been preserved, but it would be equally correct if a different
              prefix had been used.</para>

<para>If the <tag class="attribute">expand-text</tag> attribute is not
false, then each attribute value and text node within the
<tag>p:inline</tag> is evaluated as a <glossterm>text value
template</glossterm>. The context node for these expressions is
undefined.</para>

<para xml:id="p.expand-text">Within the descendants of <tag>p:inline</tag> the attribute
<tag class="attribute">p:expand-text</tag> (i.e., the attribute <code>expand-text</code>
<emphasis>in the XProc namespace</emphasis>), may appear on an element.
If it does, the specified value is used as the expand text value
for the descendants of the element on which it occurs. The
<tag class="attribute">p:expand-text</tag> will not appear in the inline content.
</para>

<!--feature="p-inline-no-nesting"-->
<para>If a <tag>p:inline</tag> occurs as
a descendant of another <tag>p:inline</tag>, any <tag
class="attribute">expand-text</tag> within the inner
<tag>p:inline</tag> is treated like an ordinary attribute; that is,
neither will its value influence text expansion nor will it be removed
from the descendant.</para>

<!-- feature="no-p-expand-text-on-p"-->
<para>(A <tag
class="attribute">p:expand-text</tag> attribute on an element in the
XProc namespace is an error. If it occurs on other elements that are
not descendants of <tag>p:inline</tag>, the attribute has no
effect.)</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="implicit-inlines">
<title>Implicit inlines</title>

<para>As an authoring convenience, if one or more element nodes,
optionally preceded and/or followed by whitespace, in any namespace
other than the XProc namespace, occurs where a <tag>p:inline</tag> is
allowed, each is treated as if it was enclosed within a
<tag>p:inline</tag> element (with no attributes). Any preceding or
following whitespace is discarded.</para>

<para>The following example demonstrates this implicit behaviour:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p:identity name="identity" code="my:implicitinline1">
    <p:with-input port="source">
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Some text</para>
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Some other text</para>
    </p:with-input>
</p:identity>]]></programlisting>

<para>Is interpreted as follows:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p:identity name="identity" code="my:implicitinline2">
    <p:with-input port="source">
        <p:inline><para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Some text</para></p:inline>
        <p:inline><para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">Some other text</para></p:inline>
    </p:with-input>
</p:identity>]]></programlisting>

<para>An explicit <tag>p:inline</tag> is required if the author
wants to include top level comments, processing instructions, or whitespace,
or if the document element is in the XProc namespace.</para>

<para><error code="S0079">It is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm>
if comments or processing instructions occur as siblings of an element node
that would be treated as an implicit inline.</error>
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="p.document">
<title>p:document</title>

<para>A <tag>p:document</tag> reads a document from a URI.</para>

<e:rng-pattern name="Document"/>

<para>The value of the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an <type>anyURI</type>. It is interpreted
as an IRI reference. If it is relative, it is made absolute against
the base URI of the <tag>p:document</tag> element.</para>

<para>The semantics of <tag>p:document</tag> are the same as a the
semantics of <tag>p:load</tag> where the <option>href</option> option
comes from the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute, the
<option>document-properties</option> option comes from the
<tag class="attribute">document-properties</tag> attribute, and the
<option>parameters</option> option coes from the
<tag class="attribute">parameters</tag> attribute.
</para>

<para><error code="D0011">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
if the resource referenced by a <tag>p:document</tag> element does not
exist, cannot be accessed, or has an XML content type and is not a
well-formed XML document.</error>
</para>

<note xml:id="note-document">
<para>A <tag>p:document</tag> always <emphasis>reads</emphasis> from
the specified IRI. In the context of a <tag>p:input</tag> or <tag>p:with-input</tag>,
this seems
perfectly natural. In the context of a <tag>p:output</tag>, this may
seem a little asymmetrical. Putting a <tag>p:document</tag> in a
<tag>p:output</tag> causes the pipeline to <emphasis>read</emphasis>
from the specified IRI and provide that document <emphasis>as an
output</emphasis> on that port. </para>

<para>Use <tag>p:store</tag> to store the results that appear on a
<tag>p:output</tag>.</para>
</note>
</section>

    <section xml:id="p.empty"><title>p:empty</title><para>A <tag>p:empty</tag> connects to an
          <glossterm>empty sequence</glossterm> of documents.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="Empty"/>
    </section>

<section xml:id="p.character-map">
<title>p:character-map</title>

<e:rng-pattern name="CharacterMap"/>

<para>When character maps are used during serialization, each occurrence of
the identified character is replaced by the specified string.</para>

<section xml:id="p.output-character">
<title>p:output-character</title>

<e:rng-pattern name="OutputCharacter"/>

<para>Maps a single character to a string at serialization time.</para>

</section>
</section>

    <section xml:id="p.documentation"><title>p:documentation</title><para>A
          <tag>p:documentation</tag> contains human-readable documentation.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="Documentation"/>
      <para>There are no constraints on the content of the <tag>p:documentation</tag> element.
        Documentation is ignored by pipeline processors. See <xref linkend="documentation"/>.
      </para></section>

    <section xml:id="p.pipeinfo"><title>p:pipeinfo</title><para>A <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> contains
        ancillary information for steps in the pipeline.</para>
      <e:rng-pattern name="PipeInfo"/>
      <para>There are no constraints on the content of the <tag>p:pipeinfo</tag> element, see <link
          linkend="annotations"/>.</para></section>
    </section>
  <section xml:id="errors">
    <title>Errors</title>
    <para>Errors in a pipeline can be divided into two classes: static errors and dynamic
      errors.</para>
    <section xml:id="static-errors">
      <title>Static Errors</title>
      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-static-error">A <firstterm>static error</firstterm> is one which can
          be detected before pipeline evaluation is even attempted.</termdef> Examples of static
        errors include cycles in the pipeline graph
        and incorrect specification of inputs and outputs. </para>
      <para>Static errors are fatal and must be detected before any steps are evaluated.</para>
      <para>For a complete list of static errors, see <xref linkend="app.static-errors"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dynamic-errors">
      <title>Dynamic Errors</title>

      <para><termdef xml:id="dt-dynamic-error">A <firstterm>dynamic
      error</firstterm> is one which occurs while a pipeline is being
      evaluated (and cannot be detected before evaluation begins).</termdef>
      Examples of dynamic errors include
      references to URIs that cannot be resolved, steps which fail,
      and pipelines that exhaust the capacity of an implementation
      (such as memory or disk space).</para>

<para>Implementations are required to evaluate the pipeline graph
according to the rules of this specification, but they may choose to
optimize pipeline execution in different ways. This may cause steps to
be evaluated in different orders which consequently has an impact on
error detection.
<impl>The detection of dynamic errors is somewhat
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm> because the order of
step execution may vary.</impl> In cases where an implementation
is able to run a pipeline without evaluating a particular expression,
or running a particular step, the implementation is never
required evaluate the expression or run the step solely in order to determine
whether doing so causes a dynamic error. For example, if a variable is
declared but never referenced, an implementation may choose whether or
not to evaluate the expression which initializes the variable, which means that if
evaluating the variable’s initializer causes a dynamic error, some
implementations will signal this error and others will not.</para>

<para>There are some cases where this specification requires that
steps must not be executed: for example, the content of a <tag>p:when</tag>
<rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> be executed if the <tag class="attribute">test</tag>
condition is false. This
means that an implementation <rfc2119>must not</rfc2119> signal any dynamic errors that
would arise if the contents of the <tag>p:when</tag> were executed.</para>

<para>An implementation may signal a dynamic error before any source
document is available, but only if it can determine that the error
would be signaled for every possible source document and every
possible set of parameter values.</para>

      <para>If a step fails due to a dynamic error, failure propagates
      upwards until either a <tag>p:try</tag> is encountered or the
      entire pipeline fails. In other words, outside of a
      <tag>p:try</tag>, step failure causes the entire pipeline to
      fail.</para>

      <para>For a complete list of dynamic errors, see <xref
      linkend="app.dynamic-errors"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="step-errors">
      <title>Step Errors</title>
      <para>Several of the steps in the standard and option step library can generate dynamic
        errors.</para>
      <para>For a complete list of the dynamic errors raised by builtin pipeline steps, see <xref
          linkend="app.step-errors"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="conformance.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="references.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../../../build/glossary.xml">
    <xi:fallback>
      <glossary xml:id="glossary">
        <title>Glossary</title>
        <para>Glossary needs to be generated</para>
      </glossary>
    </xi:fallback>
  </xi:include>
  <xi:include href="language-summary.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="error-codes.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="namespace-fixup.xml"/>
  <appendix xml:id="handling-imports">
    <title>Handling Circular and Re-entrant Library Imports (Non-Normative)</title>
    <para>When handling imports, an implementation needs to be able to detect the following
      situations, and distinguish them from cases where multiple import chains produce genuinely
      conflicting step definitions:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Circular imports: A imports B, B imports A.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Re-entrant imports: A imports B and C, B imports D, C imports D.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>One way to achieve this is as follows:</para>
    <para><termdef xml:id="dt-step-type-exports">The <firstterm>step type exports</firstterm> of an
        XProc element, against the background of a set of URIs of resources already visited (call
        this set <emphasis>Visited</emphasis>), are defined by cases.</termdef></para>
    <para>The <link linkend="dt-step-type-exports">step type exports</link> of an XProc element are
      as follows:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>p:declare-step</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A singleton bag containing the <code>type</code> of the element</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>p:library</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <glossterm>bag-merger</glossterm> of the <glossterm>step type
              exports</glossterm> of all the element's children</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>p:import</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Let <emphasis>RU</emphasis> be the actual resolved URI of the resource identified by
            the <code>href</code> of the element. If <emphasis>RU</emphasis> is a member of
              <emphasis>Visited</emphasis>, then an empty bag, otherwise update
              <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> by adding <emphasis>RU</emphasis> to it, and return the
              <glossterm>step type exports</glossterm> of the document element of the retrieved
            representation</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>all other elements</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An empty bag</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>The changes to <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> mandated by the <code>p:import</code> case
      above are persistent, not scoped. That is, not only the recursive processing of the imported
      resource but also subsequent processing of siblings and ancestors must be against the
      background of the updated value. In practice this means either using a side-effected global
      variable, or not only passing <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> as an argument to any recursive or
      iterative processing, but also <emphasis>returning</emphasis> its updated value for subsequent
      use, along with the bag of step types.</para>
    <para>Given a pipeline library document with actual resolved URI <emphasis>DU</emphasis>, <error
        code="S0036">it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the <glossterm>step type
          exports</glossterm> of the document element of the retrieved representation, against the
        background of a singleton set containing <emphasis>DU</emphasis> as the initial
          <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> set, contains any duplicates.</error></para>
    <para>Given a top-level pipeline document with actual resolved URI <emphasis>DU</emphasis>,
        <error code="S0036">it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
          <glossterm>bag-merger</glossterm> of the <glossterm>step type exports</glossterm> of the
        document element of the retrieved representation with the <glossterm>step type
          exports</glossterm> of its children, against the background of a singleton set containing
          <emphasis>DU</emphasis> as the initial <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> set, contains any
        duplicates.</error></para>
    <para>Given a non-top-level <code>p:declare-step</code> element,
        <error code="S0036">it is a <glossterm>static error</glossterm> if the
          <glossterm>bag-merger</glossterm> of the <glossterm>step type exports</glossterm> of its
        parent with the <glossterm>step type exports</glossterm> of its children, against the
        background of a copy of the <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> set of its parent as the initial
          <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> set, contains any duplicates.</error></para>
    <para>The phrase "a copy of the <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> set" in the preceding paragraph is
      meant to indicate that checking of non-top-level
        <code>p:declare-step</code> elements does <emphasis>not</emphasis> have a persistent impact
      on the checking of its parent. The contrast is that whereas changes to
        <emphasis>Visited</emphasis> pass both up <emphasis>and</emphasis> down through
        <code>p:import</code>, they pass only <emphasis>down</emphasis> through
        <emphasis>p:declare-step</emphasis>.</para>
    <para><termdef xml:id="dt-bag-merger">The <firstterm>bag-merger</firstterm> of two or more bags
        (where a bag is an unordered list or, equivalently, something like a set except that it may
        contain duplicates) is a bag constructed by starting with an empty bag and adding each
        member of each of the input bags in turn to it. It follows that the cardinality of the
        result is the sum of the cardinality of all the input bags.</termdef></para>
  </appendix>
  <xi:include href="parallel.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="mediatype.xml"/>

<appendix xml:id="changelog">
<title>Change Log</title>
<para>This appendix summarizes significant changes in this
draft.</para>

<para>This First Public Working Draft contains a number of significant
changes to the XProc pipeline language. Future drafts will attempt to address
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues?q=is%3Aopen+is%3Aissue">the remaining issues</link>.</para>

<para>In this draft:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>An attempt has been made to simplify how parameters are handled.
There are no more parameter input ports. Instead, parameters are handled
with a map and an otherwise ordinary option named “<code>parameters</code>”.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/28">#28</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Documents have accessible, arbitrary metadata (key/value pairs).
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/46">#46</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Non-XML documents can flow between steps.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/29">#29</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Option shortcut attributes can contain
<link linkend="attribute-value-templates">attribute value templates</link> and
inline XML can contain
<link linkend="text-value-templates">text value templates</link>.
(See issues <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/33">#33</link>
and <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/39">#39</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag>p:variable</tag> and <tag>p:option</tag> elements may
specify a value type.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/62">#62</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag>p:inline</tag> can be omitted when the result is
unambiguous.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/38">#38</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The <tag>p:try</tag> step has been enhanced.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/50">#50</link>)
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>All steps have a primary output port.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/41">#41</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The specification has been split into a language specification
and standard step library specification.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/53">#53</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A version option has been added to <tag>p:validate-with-xml-schema</tag>.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/83">#83</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A version option has been added to <tag>p:xquery</tag>
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/84">#84</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Support for XPath 1.0 has been removed.
(See issue <link xlink:href="https://github.com/xproc/specification/issues/52">#52</link>)
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</appendix>

</specification>
