<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:cs="http://www.w3.org/XML/XProc/2006/04/components#" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.label-elements">
<title>p:label-elements</title>

<para>The <code>p:label-elements</code> step generates a label for each matched
element and stores that label in the specified attribute.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:label-elements">
  <p:input port="source" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml"/>
  <p:output port="result"/>
  <p:option name="attribute" select="'xml:id'" as="xs:QName"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-prefix" as="xs:NCName"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-namespace" as="xs:anyURI"/>
  <p:option name="label" select="'concat(&#34;_&#34;,$p:index)'" as="xs:string" e:type="XPathExpression"/>
  <p:option name="match" select="'*'" as="xs:string" e:type="XSLTMatchPattern"/>
  <p:option name="replace" select="'true'" as="xs:boolean"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The value of the <option>attribute</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <type>QName</type>.
If the lexical value does not contain a colon, then the <tag class="attribute">attribute-namespace</tag> may be used to specify the
namespace of the attribute name. In that case, the <tag class="attribute">attribute-prefix</tag> may be specified to suggest a
prefix for the attribute name. <error code="D0034">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> to specify a new namespace or
prefix if the lexical value of the specified name contains a
colon.</error>
</para>

<para>The value of the <option>label</option> option is an XPath
expression used to generate the value of the attribute label.</para>

<para>The value of the <option>match</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XSLTMatchPattern. <error code="C0023">It
is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if that expression matches
anything other than element nodes.</error></para>

<para>The value of the <option>replace</option>
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a boolean value and is used to indicate
whether existing attribute values are replaced.</para>

<para>This step operates by generating attribute labels for each
element matched. For every matched element, the expression is
evaluated with the context node set to the matched element. An
attribute is added to the matched element using the attribute name is
specified the <option>attribute</option> option and the string value
of result of evaluating the expression. If the attribute already
exists on the matched element, the value is replaced with the string
value only if the <option>replace</option> option has the value of
<literal>true</literal>.</para>

<para>If this step is used to add or change the value
of an attribute named “<literal>xml:base</literal>”, the base URI
of the element <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> also be amended accordingly.</para>

<para>An implementation must bind the variable
“<literal>p:index</literal>” in the static context of each evaluation
of the XPath expression to the position of the element in the sequence
of matched elements. In other words, the first element (in document
order) matched gets the value “<literal>1</literal>”, the second gets
the value “<literal>2</literal>”, the third, “<literal>3</literal>”,
etc.</para>

<para>The result of the p:label-elements step is the input document with the
attribute labels associated with matched elements.  All other non-matching content
remains the same.</para>

</section>