<?xml-model href="../../../schema/dbspec.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><specification xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="xvrl" class="ed" version="5.0-extension w3c-xproc">
  <info>
    <title>Extensible Validation Report Language (XVRL)</title>
    <!-- defaults to date formatted <pubdate>2014-12-18</pubdate> -->
    <copyright>
      <year>2019</year>
      <holder>@@FIXME:</holder>
    </copyright>

    <bibliorelation type="isformatof" xlink:href="specification.xml">XML</bibliorelation>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>Gerrit Imsieke</personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>Matthieu Ricaud-Dussarget</personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>Norman Walsh</personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <abstract>
      <para>This specification describes a unified vocabulary for validation reports. Its main focus is to express the
        findings of the most common XML validation languages, Schematron, XML Schema, DTD, and Relax NG. It is meant to
        be extensible in multiple ways. It should both be able to express the results of other XML validation methods
        and of validation methods that apply to non-XML formats such as JSON or RDF graphs (irrespective of their
        serialization format). Another extension axis is that it allows addition of custom attributes or elements. While
        XVRL at its core is specified in terms of an XML vocabulary with a Relax NG schema, there may also be
        non-normative serialization formats and schemas, namely a JSON serialization and schema.</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice role="status">
      <para><emphasis>This section describes the status of this document at the time of its publication. Other documents
          may supersede this document.</emphasis></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>XVRL provides a unified format for expressing possibly multiple validation methods, applied to possibly 
      multiple documents. The need arises because not every validation language has a standardized report format,
    making it difficult to render the results of multiple validations in a single report.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="xvrl-vocabulary">
    <title>XVRL Vocabulary</title>
    
    <para>XVRL elements are in the namespace <uri>http://www.xproc.org/ns/xvrl</uri>. XVRL documents may contain
      elements in other namespaces at certain locations. The XVRL elements and attributes and their semantics are given
      in the following lists. More details about the XVRL grammar are encoded in the Relax NG Compact Syntax version of
      the XVRL schema, which is also normative.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="xvrl-vocabulary-structure">
      <title>Document Structure</title>
      <glosslist>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.detection">
          <glossterm><tag>detection</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>A single finding, typically with an associated error code and/or message(s). A <tag>report</tag>
              element primarily contains <tag>detection</tag> elements. See <xref linkend="xvrl-vocabulary-detection"/>
              for details.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.digest">
          <glossterm><tag>digest</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>A <tag>report</tag> may contain a <tag>digest</tag> element in order to provide a summary of the
                <tag>detection</tag> elements. For the distinct severity levels, counts of the <tag>detection</tag>
              elements for a given level may be specified on <tag>digest</tag>, for example in an <tag class="attribute">@error-count</tag> attribute. In addition, the <tag class="attribute">@worst</tag> attribute may give
              the highest severity level that occurs in the <tag>detection</tag> elements that are contained by the
                <tag>digest</tag>’s parent element.</para>
            <para>A <tag>digest</tag> element may occur in addition to or instead of <tag>detection</tag> elements. If
              no <tag>detection</tag> element is included, a <tag>digest</tag> element <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be
              included.</para>
            <para>All information in digest is understood to be aggregated at some point from the actual detection
              elements. It is the responsibility of an XVRL creating/processing application to keep them up to date or
              to remove them when the underlying detection information is changed. A digest may be inserted either
              before or after the detection elements.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.metadata">
          <glossterm><tag>metadata</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>Information about the time of validation, the validator used, the document(s) under test, etc. See
                <xref linkend="xvrl-vocabulary-metadata"/> for details.</para>
            <para>A single <tag>metadata</tag> element need not contain all relevant metadata. Metadata infomation will
              be inherited from surrounding <code language="xpath">reports/metadata</code> elements, that is, if a given
                <tag>metadata</tag> does not provide <tag linkend="v.validator">validator</tag> information but the
              parent <code language="xpath">reports/metadata</code> does, the parent’s <code language="xpath">metadata/validator</code> will also pertain
              to the current <tag>metadata</tag> element’s siblings and their descendants, unless overridden further
              down.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.report">
          <glossterm><tag>report</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The result of a single validation method, typically using a single schema, typically applied to
              a single document (also referred to as the <firstterm>source document</firstterm>). The individual errors
              (or other findings) are included as <tag>detection</tag> elements.</para>
            <note role="editorial" xml:id="ednote.naming-things">
              <title>Naming things…</title>
              <para>Previously, what is called “detection” here was called “report”, while a collection of detections
                was called “validation-report”. Now this collection ist called “report”, while a collection of
                (new-terminology) reports is now called “reports” (previously: “validation-reports”). I changed the
                names because I didn’t think that both an individual finding and a collection of individual findings
                should both be called a “report”, with the prefix “validation-” discerning between both. Since the
                individual finding is also the result of a validation, there is no reason it couldn’t have been called
                “validation-report” in the first place. It took quite some time to come up with a term for the
                individual findings. Candidates were: “finding”, “observation”, “detection”, “incidence”, and
                “incident”. I’m willing to rename it to something that seems more fitting.</para>
            </note>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.reports">
          <glossterm><tag>reports</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>A collection of <tag>report</tag> elements. It may contain the same <tag>metadata</tag> information as
              a single <tag>report</tag> in order to denote common information, for example if all validations have been
              applied to the same document or if all validations use the same schema or validation engine.</para>
            <para><tag>reports</tag> elements may nest in order to group <tag>report</tag> elements with common sets of
              metadata.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
      </glosslist>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="xvrl-vocabulary-detection">
      <title>Detection</title>
      <para>As described in <xref linkend="xvrl-vocabulary-structure"/>, <tag>detection</tag> is the main container for individual
        validation findings. It contains optional <tag class="attribute" linkend="v.severity">severity</tag> and 
        <tag class="attribute" linkend="v.code">code</tag> attributes, and the following elements in arbitrary order:</para>
      <glosslist>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.category">
          <glossterm><tag>category</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>In order to filter or group messages for a formatted report, individual <tag>detection</tag>s may be categorized
            according to arbitrary category systems, using the repeatable <tag>category</tag> element. Its optional attribute
            <tag class="attribute">vocabulary</tag> can hold a string that designates the category system. There are no 
              pre-defined values to choose from.</para>
            <para>Categorization that applies to all <tag>detection</tag>s in a <tag>report</tag> can be included
            in the <tag>report</tag>’s <tag>metadata</tag>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.code">
          <glossterm><tag class="attribute">code</tag> attribute</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>An error code. The term “error code” is used in a colloquial sense here. It need not relate to an error, but
            to any kind of message that has a distinctive identifying string.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.context">
          <glossterm><tag>context</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The purpose of this element is to present a piece of content that surrounds the element that the detection
              pertains to. It contains an optional <tag linkend="v.location">location</tag> element, followed by (optional) 
              arbitrary text or non-XVRL element content.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.location">
          <glossterm><tag>location</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>Within a single <tag>detection</tag> element, the location in the source document that the validation
              error, warning, etc. pertains to is given by the <tag>location</tag> element’s attributes.</para>
            <para>If not present, <tag class="attribute">href</tag> is taken from the closest ancestor’s
                <code language="xpath">metadata/document/@href</code> attribute. If there are multiple <code language="xpath">document/@href</code>
              attributes in the closest ancestor’s metadata, the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute should not
              be omitted on <tag>location</tag>, or at least a disambiguating relative URI should be given in the <code language="xpath">location/@href</code>
              attribute.</para>
            <para>The attribute <tag class="attribute">xpath</tag> contains an XPath expression that gives the location
              within the document. The in-scope value of the attribute <tag class="attribute">xpath-default-namespace</tag>
              that is permitted on any element may give a namespace for the element names in this XPath expression.
              Apart from that, the <code language="xpath">Q{namespace-uri}local-name</code> syntax <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> be used, but
              in-scope namespace prefixes or XPath predicates like <code language="xpath">[namespace-uri() = 'uri']</code> may also be
              used.</para>
            <para>The attributes <tag class="attribute">line</tag> and <tag class="attribute">column</tag> may also be
              used to point at lines and columns in a textual representation of the source document.</para>
            <para>The attribute <tag class="attribute">octet-position</tag> may be used to give the byte position
              (1-offset) of the error. This may be useful for binary documents.</para>
            <para>In order to support JSON document validations, the attributes <tag class="attribute">jsonpath</tag> and
                <tag class="attribute">jsonpointer</tag> may be used.</para>
            <para>Giving multiple alternative pointers is not forbidden. However, it is beyond the scope of this
              specification to define mechanisms to enforce or check consistency between the attribute values. It is
              evident that <tag class="attribute">jsonpointer</tag> or <tag class="attribute">jsonpath</tag> are
              meaningless in the context of XML documents.</para>
            <para>Other attributes are permitted if they are in a non-XVRL namespace.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.message">
          <glossterm><tag>message</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>An error message that pertains to a <tag>detection</tag>. There may be multiple <tag>message</tag>
              elements in a single <tag>detection</tag> element, typically to convey localized versions of essentially
              the same message. A message may contain arbitrary markup in non-XVRL namespaces. Messages are typically
              generated for consumption by humans.</para>
            <note xml:id="n.error-msg-code-colloquial">
              <para>Whenever the term “error message” is used in a colloquial sense (that is, not highlighted as the
                severity level “<literal>error</literal>” or as the XVRL element “<tag>message</tag>”) throughout this
                specification, a <tag>detection</tag> element with any <tag class="attribute">@severity</tag> level, not
                necessarily “<literal>error</literal>”, and any number of localized <tag>message</tag>s is implied.
                Likewise, the term “error code” does not imply the severity level “<literal>error</literal>”.</para>
            </note>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.provenance">
          <glossterm><tag>provenance</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>In multi-step conversion pipelines it is sometimes required to save a common origin location that a portion
            of the validated document is derived from. This may be necessary in order to patch back error messages of later 
            conversion stages into the source document.</para>
            <para>The optional <tag>provenance</tag> element within a <tag>detection</tag> conveys exactly this information, in a
              contained <tag>location</tag> element that points to the provenance location in the original source document.
                A <tag>provenance</tag> element may contain multiple <tag>location</tag> elements; it is up to processing
              applications to discern between different roles that they may have.</para>
            <para>Although it is possible to omit the <tag class="attribute">@href</tag> attribute in the contained
                <tag>location</tag> elements, this URI is not inherited from a containing element’s
                <code language="xpath">metadata/document/@href</code> attribute.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.severity">
          <glossterm><tag class="attribute">severity</tag> attribute</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The <tag class="attribute">severity</tag> attribute is permitted on a <tag>detection</tag> element.
              XVRL establishes a finite set of error levels that correspond to the impact of a detected issue. Each
                <tag>detection</tag> element may have a severity level, from highest (worst impact) to lowest, of
                “<literal>fatal-error</literal>”, “<literal>error</literal>”, “<literal>warning</literal>”, or
                “<literal>info</literal>”. In addition, the <tag class="attribute">severity</tag> attribute may have the
              value “<literal>unspecified</literal>” which is equivalent to omitting the attribute.</para>
            <note xml:id="n.severities">
              <para>Which severity level is attached to a given error code depends on, among other things, the audience
                that the validation report is prepared for. For Schematron’s SVRL output, the values of 
                <code language="xpath">@role</code> will typically translate to XVRL <code language="xpath">@severity</code>
                attributes, but this mapping may be configured, see below.</para>
            </note>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.summary">
          <glossterm><tag>summary</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>An abstract of a <tag>report</tag>, a <tag>reports</tag> collection, or an individual <tag>detection</tag>.
              This element is repeatable, for example, in order to support multiple natural languages. In the context of
                <tag>detection</tag>, it can serve as an abridged version of a full message that contains lengthy lists and the
              like.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.supplemental">
          <glossterm><tag>supplemental</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>This repeatable element may contain arbitrary textual or non-XVRL element content. It may appear in
                <tag>metadata</tag> and in <tag>detection</tag>. Its <tag class="attribute">role</tag> attribute may be used to
              further classify the purpose of its content. Like any other XVRL element, it may be localized using the <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute.</para>
            <para>Purposes can be, but are not limited to, conveying the SVRL source that the XVRL report was created from,
              or a disclaimer, a confidentiality statement, or introductory content that should be included in a rendered report.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
      </glosslist>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="xvrl-vocabulary-metadata">
      <title>Metadata</title>
      <para>All elements in this section are optional within <tag linkend="v.metadata">metadata</tag>.
      The order in which they appear is arbitrary. Some are repeatable.</para>
      <glosslist>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.creator">
          <glossterm><tag>creator</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>Information about the tool that created the source document. There is no content, only the optional attributes 
              <tag class="attribute">@name</tag>, <tag class="attribute">@version</tag>, and <tag class="attribute">@invocation</tag>.
            The <tag class="attribute">@invocation</tag> attribute is meant to hold a command line that contains the invocation of the 
            program that was responsible for generating the source document. This information can be useful for later diagnosing
            dependencies between errors and command line options.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><tag>category</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>See <xref linkend="v.category"/></para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.document">
          <glossterm><tag>document</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The URI of a source document may be specified in the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute.
              In addition or instead, the document may be given as the element content.
              See also <xref linkend="v.location"/> about inheritance of <tag class="attribute">href</tag>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.schema">
          <glossterm><tag>schema</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The URI of a schema document may be specified in the <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute.
              In addition or instead, the document may be given as the element content. The namespace of the 
            schema may be given in the attribute <tag class="attribute">schematypens</tag>. The version of the 
            schema language may be given in the attribute <tag class="attribute">version</tag>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><tag>summary</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>See <xref linkend="v.summary"/>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><tag>supplemental</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>See <xref linkend="v.supplemental"/>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>        
        <glossentry xml:id="v.timestamp">
          <glossterm><tag>timestamp</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>&gt;The content needs to be an <literal>xsd:dateTime</literal> value, for example 
              “<literal>2017-12-04T12:21:37.381+01:00</literal>”.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.title">
          <glossterm><tag>title</tag> element(s)</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>The title of a <tag>report</tag>, a <tag>reports</tag> collection, or an individual <tag>detection</tag>.
            This element is repeatable, for example, in order to support multiple natural languages.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        <glossentry xml:id="v.validator">
          <glossterm><tag>validator</tag> element</glossterm>
          <glossdef>
            <para>Information about the validation program that generated the report(s) or the underlying messages (if XVRL was
              not generated natively by the program). There are optional attributes <tag class="attribute">@name</tag> and <tag class="attribute">@version</tag>, both are arbitrary strings. Arbitrary text or element (in a non-XVRL namespace)
            content may be contained, for example to describe a configuration or to include an actual configuration file.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
      </glosslist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <appendix xml:id="xvrl-schema">
    <title>The XVRL Schema</title>
    <programlisting># Schema for XML Validation Report Language; adapted from a proposal
# by Matthieu Ricaud incorporating some suggestions by Gerrit Imsieke
# See https://github.com/xproc/3.0-steps/issues/15

namespace a = "http://relaxng.org/ns/compatibility/annotations/1.0"
namespace local = ""
default namespace xvrl = "http://www.xproc.org/ns/xvrl"

start = reports | report

xmllang.attr = attribute xml:lang { xsd:language }
xmlid.attr = attribute xml:id { xsd:ID }
xmlbase.attr = attribute xml:base { xsd:anyURI }
# Default namespace URI for location XPaths:
xpdns.attr = attribute xpath-default-namespace { xsd:anyURI }
anyother.attr = attribute * - (local:* | xvrl:* | xml:*) { text }
any.attr = attribute * - xvrl:* { text }
message.attr  = attribute (* - (xvrl:* | xml:*)) { text }


common.attr =
  xmllang.attr?
  &amp; xmlid.attr?
  &amp; xmlbase.attr?
  &amp; xpdns.attr?
  &amp; anyother.attr*

href.attr =
  attribute href { xsd:anyURI }
  
any.element = 
  element * - xvrl:* { (any.attr | text | any.element)* }

reports =
  element reports {
    common.attr,
    report.metadata,
    (report | reports | digest)+
  }
report =
  element report {
    common.attr,
    report.metadata,
    ((digest?, detection+) | (detection+, digest) | digest)
  }

## All information in digest is understood to be aggregated at some point from the actual detection elements. 
## It is the responsibility of an XVRL creating/processing application to keep them up to date or to remove them 
## when the underlying detection information is changed. If the individual detections are omitted, a digest must be present. 
## A digest may be inserted either before or after the detection elements.
digest =
  element digest {
    common.attr,
    attribute valid { "true" | "false" | "partial" | "undetermined" }?,
    attribute fatal-error-count { xsd:integer }?,
    attribute error-count { xsd:integer }?,
    attribute warning-count { xsd:integer }?,
    attribute info-count { xsd:integer }?,
    attribute unspecified-count { xsd:integer }?,
    attribute fatal-error-codes { list { token* } }?,
    attribute error-codes { list { token* } }?,
    attribute warning-codes { list { token* } }?,
    attribute info-codes { list { token* } }?,
    attribute unspecified-codes { list { token* } }?,
    attribute worst { "fatal-error" | "error" | "warning" | "info" | "nothing" | "unspecified" }?
  }
report.metadata =
  element metadata {
    common.attr,
    (timestamp?
     &amp; validator?
     &amp; creator?
     &amp; document*
     &amp; title*
     &amp; summary*
     &amp; category*
     &amp; schema*
     &amp; supplemental*)
  }

document = 
  element document {
    common.attr,
    href.attr?,
    (text | any.element)
  }
  
detection =
  element detection {
    common.attr,
    attribute severity { "info" | "warning" | "error" | "fatal-error" | "unspecified" }?,
    attribute code { text }?,
    (location?
     &amp; provenance?
     &amp; title*
     &amp; summary*
     &amp; category*
     &amp; (let*, message*)
     &amp; supplemental*
     &amp; context?)
  }

let =
    element let {
        common.attr,
        attribute name { xsd:QName },
        (attribute value {xsd:string} | (text | any.element))*
    }

value-of =
    element value-of {
        attribute name { xsd:QName }
    }

location = element location { location.model }
location.model =
  xpdns.attr?,
  # XPaths may use the Q{namespace-uri}local-name notation.
  attribute xpath { text }?,
  # These are different syntaxes to address JSON documents.
  # JSON docs may be represented as XPath maps and arrays
  # and then addressed via, e.g., xpath=".(3)('foo')"
  # for the 3rd array item, which is a map, and then the map’s
  # value for the 'foo' key.
  attribute jsonpointer { text }?,
  attribute jsonpath { text }?,
  attribute href { xsd:anyURI }?,
  attribute line { xsd:positiveInteger }?,
  attribute column { xsd:positiveInteger }?,
  # For binary data:
  attribute octet-position { xsd:positiveInteger }?,
  anyother.attr*
provenance = element provenance { location+ }

message =
  element message {
    common.attr,
    (text | message.element)*
  }
message.element =
    element (* - (xvrl:* - xvrl:value-of)) {
      (message.attr | text | message.element | value-of)*
  }

supplemental =
  element supplemental { common.attr, (text | any.element)* }
context =
  element context {
  common.attr, location?, (text | any.element)* }
validator =
  element validator {
    common.attr,
    attribute name { text },
    attribute version { text }?,
    (text | any.element)*
  }
creator =
  element creator {
    common.attr,
    attribute name { text },
    attribute version { text }?,
    element invocation { text }?
  }
schema =
  element schema {
    common.attr,
    attribute href { xsd:anyURI }?,
    attribute schematypens { xsd:anyURI },
    attribute version { text }?,
    (text | any.element)?
  }
title = element title { common.attr, (text | any.element)* }
summary = element summary { common.attr, (text | any.element)* }
category =
  element category {
    common.attr,
    attribute vocabulary { xsd:token }?,
    (text | any.element)*
  }
timestamp = element timestamp { common.attr, xsd:dateTime }</programlisting>
  </appendix>
  
  <appendix xml:id="xvrl-generation">
    <title>Parameters for Controlling XVRL Generation</title>
    <para>The following parameters should be understood by XVRL report generators when converting underlying validation
      reports, for example, from SVRL or from the XProc error vocabulary, <tag>c:errors</tag> etc.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>xvrl:default-severity</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When no severity is associated with a source vocabulary element that is mapped to <tag>detection</tag>,
            this property can be specified in order to assign a default severity to any of these source vocabulary
            constructs. It can be argued that the XProc error vocabulary, <tag>c:error</tag>, already conveys the
            severity level <literal>error</literal>. The view that this specification takes is to regard these messages
            as generic findings of severity “<literal>error</literal>”, but that the
              <literal>xvrl:default-severity</literal> may be given to override this.</para>
          <para>Implementations are free to provide other parameters, in a different namespace, that permit a more
            detailed mapping, for example from error code to severity.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>xvrl:serialization-format</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Anticipates future alternative serialization If no value is given, <literal>xml</literal> is assumed.
            Other possible values may be, but are not limited to, <literal>json</literal>, <literal>rdf/xml</literal>,
              <literal>turtle</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>xvrl:language</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A space separated list of language abbreviations, typically according to ISO 639-1. The preferred
            language is given first, followed by fallback languages. The result is that localized elements within a
              <tag>detection</tag> will be reduced to messages, categories, or summaries in the preferred language.
            Example: <literal>de en</literal> instructs the XVRL generator to include German messages only and to use an
            English message when no German message is present. If no language matches for a given localizable element in
            a <tag>detection</tag> context, a corresponding element with the same attributes, but with no <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute, should be included. Localizable elements with an <tag class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute that is not listed in this property should be ignored.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>xvrl:map-to-severity</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This parameter contains space-separated QNames that correspond to elements or attributes of an
            underlying reporting language, in particular SVRL attributes. A value of <literal>flag role</literal>
          instructs an SVRL to XVRL converter to preferentially map the SVRL <tag class="attribute">flag</tag> attribute
          to the XVRL <tag class="attribute">severity</tag> attribute. If it is not present or its value cannot be mapped,
          it should try to map the SVRL <tag class="attribute">role</tag> value to XVRL’s 
            <tag class="attribute">severity</tag>.</para>
          <para>The following attribute values are considered mappable, after folding the source value to lower case:
            “information”, “informational” map to “info”; “warn” maps to “warning”; “fatal” maps to ”fatal-error”.
            A conversion tool may consider other variants, including translations that correspond to the natural 
          language of the corresponding error message, for mapping.</para>
          <para>If the content of an (for example) SVRL attribute cannot be mapped, it should be attached to the corresponding
            XVRL <tag>detection</tag> either as a category or as a namespaced attribute (that is,
              <literal>role="foo"</literal> in SVRL may become <literal>svrl:role="foo"</literal> in XVRL, with
          <literal>xmlns:svrl="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/svrl"</literal>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>xvrl:xpath-notation</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This parameter controls how XPath attributes given in <tag>location</tag> elements should be structured.
          Possible values are “<literal>Q</literal>”, “<literal>namespace-uri</literal>“, and “<literal>name</literal>”.</para>
          <para>Example: The path <code language="xpath">/TEI/text[1]</code> in the namespace
              <literal>http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0</literal> will be represented in these notations as follows:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><literal>Q</literal></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><code language="xpath">/Q{http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0}TEI/Q{http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0}text[1]</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><literal>namespace-uri</literal></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><code language="xpath">/*:TEI[namespace-uri()='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0']/*:text[namespace-uri()='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'][1]</code></para>
                <para>This corresponds to the parameter setting <literal>full-path-notation=1</literal> in the SVRL output 
                  of the Schematron skeleton implementation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><literal>name</literal></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><code language="xpath">/tei:TEI/tei:text[1]</code></para>
                <para>This corresponds to the parameter setting <literal>full-path-notation=2</literal> in the SVRL output 
                  of the Schematron skeleton implementation. It takes namespace prefix declarations from the source 
                document and it needs to copy these declarations to an appropriate location in the resulting XVRL document.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>If the XVRL attribute <tag class="attribute">xpath-default-namespace</tag> is present on an ancestor
            element, the namespace URI given in this attribute on the closest ancestor should be used to omit this
            namespace from the resulting XPath. If <literal>xpath-default-uri="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"</literal> 
            is in force in a given context, the paths in any of the three notations should reduce to 
            <code language="xpath">/TEI/text[1]</code>.</para>
          <para>If an XVRL-generating application is unable to generate the preferred notation, any XPath notation that 
          it can produce is acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </appendix>
  
  <appendix xml:id="xvrl-xslt">
    <title>XSLT Stylesheets (Non-Normative)</title>
    <para>As a convenience, XSLT stylesheets will be made available for the following purposes:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>SVRL → XVRL conversion</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>It is recommended that XProc processor vendors make this XSLT available under the import URI
          <uri>http://xproc.org/xvrl/xsl/svrl2xvrl.xsl</uri>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><tag>c:errors</tag> → XVRL conversion</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>It is recommended that XProc processor vendors make this XSLT available under the import URI
          <uri>http://xproc.org/xvrl/xsl/c-errors2xvrl.xsl</uri>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Filter/transform XVRL</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>It is recommended that XProc processor vendors make this XSLT available under the import URI
          <uri>http://xproc.org/xvrl/xsl/xvrl2xvrl.xsl</uri>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>All stylesheets accept the parameters given in <xref linkend="xvrl-generation"/>.</para>
  </appendix>
    

</specification>