<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:cs="http://www.w3.org/XML/XProc/2006/04/components#" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.add-attribute">
<title>p:add-attribute</title>

<para>The <code>p:add-attribute</code> step adds a single attribute to
a set of matching elements. The input document specified on the
<code>source</code> is processed for matches specified by the match
pattern in the <option>match</option> option. For each of these
matches, the attribute whose name is specified by the
<option>attribute-name</option> option is set to the attribute value
specified by the <option>attribute-value</option> option.
</para>

<para>The resulting document is produced on the <code>result</code>
output port and consists of a exact copy of the input with the
exception of the matched elements. Each of the matched elements is
copied to the output with the addition of the specified attribute
with the specified value.
</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:add-attribute">
  <p:input port="source" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml"/>
  <p:output port="result" content-types="application/xml"/>
  <p:option name="match" select="'/*'" as="xs:string" e:type="XSLTMatchPattern"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-name" required="true" as="xs:QName"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-prefix" as="xs:NCName"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-namespace" as="xs:anyURI"/>
  <p:option name="attribute-value" required="true" as="xs:string"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The value of the <option>match</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XSLTMatchPattern. <error code="C0023">It
is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the match pattern matches a node
which is not an element.</error></para>

<para>The value of the <option>attribute-name</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <type>QName</type>.
If the lexical value does not contain a colon, then the <tag class="attribute">attribute-namespace</tag> may be used to specify the
namespace of the attribute. In that case, the <tag class="attribute">attribute-prefix</tag> may be specified to suggest a
prefix for the attribute name. <error code="D0034">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> to specify a new namespace or
prefix if the lexical value of the specified name contains a
colon.</error>
The corresponding expanded name is used to construct the attribute.</para>

<para>The value of the <option>attribute-value</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a legal attribute value according to XML.</para>

<para>If an attribute with the same name as the expanded name
from the <option>attribute-name</option> option exists on the matched
element, the value specified in
the <option>attribute-value</option> option is used to set the
value of that existing attribute.  That is, the value of the
existing attribute is changed to the <option>attribute-value</option>
value. </para>

<note xml:id="note-multattr"><para>If multiple attributes need to be set on the same
element(s), the <tag>p:set-attributes</tag> step can be used to set them
all at once.</para>
</note>

<para>This step cannot be used to add namespace declarations. <error code="C0059">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the QName
value in the <option>attribute-name</option> option uses the prefix
“<literal>xmlns</literal>”
or any other prefix that resolves to the namespace name
<uri>http://www.w3.org/2000/xmlns/</uri>.
</error> Note, however, that while namespace declarations cannot be
added explicitly by this step, adding an attribute whose name is in a
namespace for which there is no namespace declaration in scope on the
matched element may result in a namespace binding being added by
namespace fixup.</para>

<para>If an attribute named
<tag class="attribute">xml:base</tag> is added or changed, the base URI
of the element <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> also be amended accordingly.</para>

<section>
<title>Document properties</title>
<para feature="add-attribute-preserves-all">All document properties are preserved.</para>
</section>
</section>
