<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:cs="http://www.w3.org/XML/XProc/2006/04/components#" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.split-sequence">
<title>p:split-sequence</title>

<para>The <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step accepts a sequence of
documents and divides it into two sequences.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:split-sequence">
  <p:input port="source" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml" sequence="true"/>
  <p:output port="matched" sequence="true" primary="true" content-types="application/xml"/>
  <p:output port="not-matched" sequence="true" content-types="application/xml"/>
  <p:option name="initial-only" select="false()" as="xs:boolean"/>
  <p:option name="test" required="true" as="xs:string" e:type="XPathExpression"/>
</p:declare-step>

 <para>The value of the <option>test</option> option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XPathExpression.</para>

<para>The XPath expression in the <option>test</option> option is
applied to each document in the input sequence. If the effective
boolean value of the expression is true, the document is copied to the
<port>matched</port> port; otherwise it is copied to the
<port>not-matched</port> port.</para>

<para>If the <option>initial-only</option> option is true, then when
the first document that does not satisfy the test expression is
encountered, it <emphasis>and all the documents that follow
it</emphasis> are written to the <port>not-matched</port> port.
In other words, it only writes the initial series of matched
documents (which may be empty) to the <port>matched</port> port.
All other documents are written to the <port>not-matched</port> port,
irrespective of whether or not they match.</para>

<para>The <olink targetdoc="../xproc/xproc.xml" targetptr="xpath-context">XPath context</olink> for the
<option>test</option> option changes over time. For each document that
appears on the <code>source</code> port, the expression is evaluated
with that document as the context document. The context position
(<code>position()</code>) is the position of that document within the
sequence and the context size (<code>last()</code>) is the total
number of documents in the sequence.</para>

<note xml:id="note-stream">
<para>In principle, this component cannot stream because it must
buffer all of the input sequence in order to find the context size. In
practice, if the test expression does not use the
<function>last()</function> function, the implementation can stream
and ignore the context size.</para>
</note>

<para>If the implementation supports passing PSVI annotations between
steps, the <tag>p:split-sequence</tag> step <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> preserve
any annotations that appear in the input.</para>

<section>
<title>Document properties</title>
<para feature="split-sequence-preserves-all">All document properties are preserved.</para>
</section>
</section>
