<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:cs="http://www.w3.org/XML/XProc/2006/04/components#" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.wrap">
<title>p:wrap</title>

<para>The <tag>p:wrap</tag> step wraps matching nodes in the
<port>source</port> document with a new parent element.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:wrap">
   <p:input port="source" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml"/>
   <p:output port="result" content-types="application/xml"/>
   <p:option name="wrapper" required="true" as="#QName"/>
   <p:option name="wrapper-prefix" as="xs:NCName?"/>
   <p:option name="wrapper-namespace" as="xs:anyURI?"/>
   <p:option name="match" required="true" as="#XSLTSelectionPattern"/>
   <p:option name="group-adjacent" as="#XPathExpression?"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>The value of the <option>wrapper</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <type>QName</type>. If the lexical value
does not contain a colon, then the <tag class="attribute">wrapper-namespace</tag>
may be used to specify the namespace of the wrapper. In that case, the
<tag class="attribute">wrapper-prefix</tag> may be specified to suggest a
prefix for the wrapper element.
<error code="D0034">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm>
to specify a new namespace or prefix if the lexical value of the specified
name contains a colon.</error></para>

<para>The value of the <option>match</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XSLTSelectionPattern. <error code="C0023">It
is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the pattern matches
anything other than document, element, text, processing instruction, and comment
nodes.</error>
</para>

<para>The value of the <option>group-adjacent</option> option
<rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an XPathExpression.</para>

<para>If the node matched is the document node (<code>match="/"</code>),
the result is a new document where the document element is a new
element node whose QName is the value specified in the
<option>wrapper</option> option. That new element contains copies of
all of the children of the original document node.</para>

<para>When the match pattern does not match the document node,
every node that matches the specified <option>match</option>
pattern is replaced with a new element node whose QName is the value
specified in the <option>wrapper</option> option.
The content of that new element is a copy of the original,
matching node. The <tag>p:wrap</tag> step performs a "deep" wrapping, the children
of the matching node and their descendants are processed and wrappers
are added to all matching nodes.
</para>

<para>The <option>group-adjacent</option> option can be used to group
adjacent matching nodes in a single wrapper element. The specified
XPath expression is evaluated for each matching node with that node
as the XPath context node. Whenever two or more adjacent matching nodes
have the same “group adjacent” value, they are wrapped together in
a single wrapper element.</para>

<para>Two matching nodes are considered adjacent if and only if they
are siblings and either there are no nodes between them or all
intervening, non-matching nodes are whitespace text, comment, or processing
instruction nodes.</para>

<simplesect>
<title>Document properties</title>
<para feature="wrap-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.</para>
</simplesect>
</section>
