<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:cs="http://www.w3.org/XML/XProc/2006/04/components#" xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax" xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="c.xslt">
<title>p:xslt</title>

<para>The <tag>p:xslt</tag> step applies an
<biblioref linkend="xslt10"/> or
<biblioref linkend="xslt20"/> stylesheet to a document.</para>

<p:declare-step type="p:xslt">
  <p:input port="source" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml"
           sequence="true" primary="true"/>
  <p:input port="stylesheet" content-types="application/xml text/xml */*+xml"/>
  <p:option name="parameters" as="map(xs:QName,item())"/>
  <p:output port="result" primary="true" sequence="true" content-types="*/*"/>
  <p:output port="secondary" sequence="true"/>
  <p:option name="initial-mode" as="xs:QName"/>
  <p:option name="template-name" as="xs:QName"/>
  <p:option name="output-base-uri" as="xs:anyURI"/>
  <p:option name="version" as="xs:string"/>
</p:declare-step>

<para>If present, the value of the <option>initial-mode</option>
option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <type>QName</type>.</para>

<para>If present, the value of the <option>template-name</option>
option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be a <type>QName</type>.</para>

<para>If present, the value of the <option>output-base-uri</option>
option <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be an <type>anyURI</type>. If it is
relative, it is made absolute against the base URI of the element on
which it is specified (<tag>p:with-option</tag> or <tag>p:xslt</tag> in the
case of a <olink targetdoc="../xproc/xproc.xml" targetptr="option-shortcut">syntactic shortcut</olink>
value).</para>

<para>If the step specifies a <option>version</option>, then that version
of XSLT <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> be used to process the transformation.
<error code="C0038">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the specified version
is not available.</error> If the step does not specify a version, the
implementation may use any version it has available and may use any means
to determine what version to use, including, but not limited to,
examining the version of the stylesheet.</para>

<para>The XSLT stylesheet provided on the <port>stylesheet</port> port
is applied to the document on the <port>source</port> port. Any
parameters passed in the <option>parameters</option> option are used
to define top-level stylesheet parameters. The primary result document
of the transformation, if there is one, appears on the
<port>result</port> port. At most one document can appear on the
<port>result</port> port. All other result documents appear on the
<port>secondary</port> port. <impl>The order in which result documents
appear on the <port>secondary</port> port is
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl> If XSLT 1.0 is
used, an empty sequence of documents <rfc2119>must</rfc2119> appear on
the <port>secondary</port> port.</para>

<para>If a sequence of documents is provided on the
<port>source</port> port, the first document is used as the
primary input document. The whole sequence is also the default
collection.
If no documents are provided on the <port>source</port> port,
the primary input document is undefined and the default collection
is empty.
<error code="C0039">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if a sequence of documents (including
an empty sequence) is provided
to an XSLT 1.0 step.</error>
</para>

<para>A dynamic error occurs if the XSLT processor signals a fatal
error. This includes the case where the transformation terminates due
to a <tag>xsl:message</tag> instruction with a <tag class="attribute">terminate</tag> attribute value of
“<literal>yes</literal>”. <impl>How XSLT message termination
errors are reported to the XProc processor is
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</impl></para>

<para>The invocation of the transformation is controlled by the
<option>initial-mode</option> and <option>template-name</option>
options that set the initial mode and/or named template in the XSLT
transformation where processing begins. <error code="C0056">It is a
<glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the specified initial mode
or named template cannot be applied to the specified stylesheet.</error>
</para>

<para>The <option>output-base-uri</option> option sets the context's
output base URI per the XSLT 2.0 specification, otherwise the base URI
of the <port>result</port> document is the base URI of the first
document in the <code>source</code> port's sequence. If the value of
the <option>output-base-uri</option> option is not absolute, it will
be resolved using the base URI of its <tag>p:option</tag>
element. An XSLT 1.0 step <rfc2119>should</rfc2119> use the value of the
<option>output-base-uri</option> as the base URI of its output, if the
option is specified.</para>

<para>If XSLT 2.0 is used, the outputs of this step
<rfc2119>may</rfc2119> include PSVI annotations.</para>


<para>The static and initial dynamic contexts of the XSLT processor
are the contexts defined in
<olink targetdoc="../xproc/xproc.xml" targetptr="step-xpath-context-20"/>
with the following adjustments.</para>

<para>The dynamic context is augmented as follows:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Context item</term>
<listitem>
<para>The first document that appears on the <port>source</port> port.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Variable values</term>
<listitem>
<para>Any parameters
passed in the <option>parameters</option> option are available as variable bindings
to the XSLT processor.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Function implementations</term>
<listitem>
<para>The function implementations provided by the XSLT processor.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Default collection</term>
<listitem>
<para>The sequence of documents provided on the <port>source</port> port.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<section>
<title>Document properties</title>
<para feature="xslt-preserves-none">No document properties are preserved.</para>
</section>
</section>
